<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
      <title>Aerosols on Sam Clifford </title>
    <link>/./tags/aerosols/</link>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
    <updated>2015-12-14 00:00:00 &#43;0000 UTC</updated>
    
    <item>
      <title>Workshops</title>
      <link>/./2015/12/14/workshops/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Dec 2015 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2015/12/14/workshops/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I had a very full week last week, with the annual &lt;a href=&#34;https://botb2015.wordpress.com/&#34;&gt;Bayes on the Beach&lt;/a&gt; (BOB) at the Gold Coast (Mon-Wed) and &lt;a href=&#34;https://bode2015.wordpress.com&#34;&gt;Bayesian Optimal Design of Experiments&lt;/a&gt; (BODE) on Friday. BOB is an annual workshop/retreat, run by Kerrie Mengersen and the BRAG group at QUT, that brings together a bunch of Australian and international statisticians for a few days of workshops, tutorials, presentations and fun in the sun. This year was, I think, my fourth year at BOB. One of the recurring features is the workshop sessions, where around three researchers each pose a problem to the group and everyone decides which one they’re going to work on. This year I was asked to present a problem based on the air quality research I do and so my little group worked on the issue of how to build a predictive model of indoor PM&lt;sub&gt;10&lt;/sub&gt; based on meteorology, outdoor PM&lt;sub&gt;10&lt;/sub&gt; and temporal information. We were fortunate to have &lt;a href=&#34;http://dicook.github.io/&#34;&gt;Di Cook&lt;/a&gt; in our group, who did a lot of interesting visual analysis of the data (she later presented a tutorial on how to use ggplot and R Markdown). We ended up discussing why tree models may not be such a great idea, the difference in autocorrelation and the usefulness of distributed lag models. It gave me a lot to think about and I hope that everyone found it as valuable as I did. The two other workshop groups worked on ranking the papers of Professor &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mas.ncl.ac.uk/~nrjb2/&#34;&gt;Richard Boys&lt;/a&gt; (one of the keynote speakers) and building a Bayesian Network model of PhD completion time. Both groups were better attended than mine, which I put down to the idea that those two were “fun” workshops and mine sounded a lot like work. Still, a diverse range of workshops means something for everyone. &lt;a href=&#34;http://staff.qut.edu.au/staff/mcgreej/&#34;&gt;James McGree (QUT)&lt;/a&gt; asked me if I could come to the BODE workshop to discuss some open challenges in air quality research with regards to experimental design. I gave a brief overview of regulatory monitoring, the UPTECH project’s random spatial selection and then brought in the idea that the introduction of low cost sensors gives us the opportunity to measure in so many places at once but we still need to sort out where we want to measure if we want to characterise human exposure to air pollution. While it was a small group I did get to have a good chat with the attendees about some possible ways forward. It was also good to see &lt;a href=&#34;http://data.aims.gov.au/staffcv/jsf/external/view.xhtml?partyId=900000428&#34;&gt;Julian Caley (AIMS)&lt;/a&gt; talk about monitoring on the Great Barrier Reef, Professor &lt;a href=&#34;http://staff.qut.edu.au/staff/pettitt/&#34;&gt;Tony Pettitt (QUT)&lt;/a&gt; talk about sampling for intractable likelihoods and &lt;a href=&#34;http://staff.qut.edu.au/staff/perez5/&#34;&gt;Tristan Perez (QUT)&lt;/a&gt; discuss the interplay between experimental design and the use of robots. It’s been a great end to the year to spend it in the company of statisticians working on all sorts of interesting problems. While I do enjoy my air quality work and R usage is increasing at ILAQH it’s an entirely different culture to being around people who spend their time working out whether they’re better off with data.table and reshape2 or dplyr and tidyr.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Australia-China Centre turns 1</title>
      <link>/./2015/12/04/australia-china-centre-turns-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Dec 2015 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2015/12/04/australia-china-centre-turns-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Has it already been a year? This week the Australia-China Centre for Air Quality Science and Management had its second annual meeting, at QUT. We got updates on the various research activities that have happened, are happening and are planned. There’s lots of interesting stuff being done to tackle a variety of problems, such as reducing workplace exposure to air pollution, quantifying the exposure of individuals and using unmanned aerial vehicles to measure air quality. &lt;img src=&#34;img_1215.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;IMG_1215.jpg&#34; /&gt; Tuesday night we had the conference dinner out at the Mount Coot-tha Botanic Gardens, at the function space at the cafe/restaurant out there. I don’t think I’ve been there since my cousin’s wedding reception 15-20 years ago. I really liked that efforts were made to ensure each table had a mix of senior professors, mid- and early-career researchers and PhD students. It made for a very inclusive dinner and many different topics of conversation. Luckily I was sat with a co-worker with whom I could trade my fish entree and mains for something a little more land-based. There was even a birthday cake (chocolate mousse cake) and a number of people joined in singing “Happy Birthday” to the ACC. Wednesday we spent the day workshopping the various planned projects to determine what issues need to be addressed in the collection and analysis of data. I ended up sitting with a group looking at the impacts of indoor temperature on mortality rates, particularly trying to estimate the relative risk of extreme heat and cold. It was good to be confronted with some new challenges to think about, rather than the same stuff I’ve been working on almost non-stop this year. All in all, it was a good meeting even though the stress levels around here were through the roof in the lead-up. I ended up taking photos of nearly all of the presenters on the Tuesday as well as group photos with our Chinese collaborators and special invited guests.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Just got back from China</title>
      <link>/./2014/12/09/just-got-back-from-china/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2014 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2014/12/09/just-got-back-from-china/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve spent the last few days travelling to and from Beijing, China for the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.qut.edu.au/institute-of-health-and-biomedical-innovation/about/news/news?news-id=83099&#34;&gt;launch of the new Australia-China Centre for Air Quality Science and Management.&lt;/a&gt; This is a huge thing for us at ILAQH because it sets up an international collaborative agreement between a bunch of institutions in Australia and China who each have a different set of expertise that they can bring to the table, allowing us to undertake more ambitious projects than before and seek funding from a wider range of sources. There was a lot of prep and behind the scenes meetings to take place on the first day, so Mandana (a colleague of mine) and I took a trip downtown to the Forbidden City and Tian Anmen Square and did some shopping Wangfujin. It would have been cold enough without the wind but it was such a clear day and everything was wonderful. &lt;a href=&#34;https://flic.kr/p/q1zV8c&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://flic.kr/p/q1zV8c&lt;/a&gt; The first day of the launch, held at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.craes.cn/cn/english/welcome.html&#34;&gt;CRAES&lt;/a&gt;, featured the constituent groups giving a short presentation about their work. There’s a lot of great people working on some really interesting stuff and I’m very excited about the prospect of working with some of them over the coming years. &lt;a href=&#34;https://flic.kr/p/q26qn7&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://flic.kr/p/q26qn7&lt;/a&gt; The second day had us split into three groups to propose various objectives and projects and put names on paper for who might be good leaders or key players in these fields as part of our centre. I joined the Transport Emissions group to discuss the control of emissions at their source, the investigation of atmospheric transformation processes and the development and uptake of new technologies. A lot of the ground work had already been laid at a planning meeting earlier in the year but it was good to put together some more concrete research topics. After this, we went out to the National Jade Hotel for dinner, where we got to try another of the varied styles of Chinese cuisine; this time from a coastal region in North-Eastern China. I wish I had’ve paid more attention to the names of the various styles, but I enjoyed trying everything over the course of the trip, even the tripe. &lt;a href=&#34;https://flic.kr/p/pntrDK&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://flic.kr/p/pntrDK&lt;/a&gt; The final day saw us tidying up the proposals, and an early finish meant that I got the afternoon off with Mandana, Felipe and Dion. After stumbling our way through a menu with pictures but no English translations, we had a big lunch and set off on the subway to the Temple of Heaven. It was certainly warmer than the Forbidden City (less stone, more trees) and was a very peaceful and pleasant end to the trip as we sat down at a bakery café and discussed If You Are The One while eating cream buns and drinking coffee (or in my case, peach black tea with milk). After heading back to the hotel, Mandana and I took a walk around the Bird’s Nest stadium which was only a block from our hotel. It looks like Beijing is putting effort into maintaining the area as a public plaza rather than just the grounds of a sports stadium, so even late in the cold evening it was full of families and groups of friends walking, talking and taking photographs. &lt;a href=&#34;https://flic.kr/p/q3vTaT&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://flic.kr/p/q3vTaT&lt;/a&gt; An early morning taxi to the airport saw the start of 18 hours of travel. It’s nice to be back in one’s own bed, but I’m off to the airport again tomorrow for a 5:30am flight to Sydney for a workshop on exposure assessment with colleagues from the Centre for Air quality and health Research and evaluation. After a week of disastrously bad coffee, I’m glad that I booked accommodation which advertises itself as being 15m from the Toby’s Estate café.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Two pieces of good news this week</title>
      <link>/./2014/11/05/two-pieces-of-good-news-this-week/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2014 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2014/11/05/two-pieces-of-good-news-this-week/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The full paper from the EMAC2013 conference last year is now available online. If you’re interested in the statistical methodology we used for estimating the inhaled dose of particles by students in the UPTECH project, you should check out our paper at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://journal.austms.org.au/ojs/index.php/ANZIAMJ/article/view/7819&#34;&gt;ANZIAM Journal&lt;/a&gt; (click the link that says “PDF” down the bottom under Full Text). More importantly, though, we were successful in applying for an ARC Discovery Project! This project will run for three years and combines spatio-temporal statistical modelling, sensor miniaturisation and mobile phone technologies to allow people to minimise their exposure to air pollution. Our summary of the project, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.arc.gov.au/pdf/DP15/DP15_Listing_by_State_and_Org.pdf&#34;&gt;the list of successful projects&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This interdisciplinary project aims to develop a personalised air pollution exposure monitoring system, leveraging the ubiquitousness and advancements in mobile phone technology and state of the art miniaturisation of monitoring sensors, data transmission and analysis. Airborne pollution is one of the top contemporary risks faced by humans; however, at present individuals have no way to recognise that they are at risk or need to protect themselves. It is expected that the outcome will empower individuals to control and minimise their own exposures. This is expected to lead to significant national socioeconomic benefits and bring global advancement in acquiring and utilising environmental information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other people at ILAQH were also successful in getting a Discovery Project grant looking at new particle formation and cloud formation in the Great Barrier Reef. I won’t be involved in that project but it sounds fascinating.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Revising another paper</title>
      <link>/./2014/09/11/revising-another-paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2014 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2014/09/11/revising-another-paper/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We got a paper back from the reviewers a few days ago and there are some comments requesting revisions to the explanation of the statistical methods and the analysis. It’s interesting coming back to this paper, about a year after I last saw it (it’s been sent around to a few different journals to try to find a home for it). The PhD student who is the main author got into R and ggplot2 last year and has done some good work with linear mixed effects models and visualisation but some of the plots are the same sort of thing one might do in Excel (lots of boxplots next to each other rather than making use of small multiples). So now I get to delve back into some data and analysis that’s about a year old with fresh eyes. Having done more with ggplot2 over the last 12 months, there are some things that I will definitely change about this. The student and I had a chat this morning about how to tackle it, and we’re trying to choose the best way to split up our data for visualisation: 6 treatments, 4 measurement blocks, two different measures (PM2.5 mass concentration and PNC), a total of 48 boxplots, density plots or histograms. A paper with another PhD student has had its open discussion finalised now, which means more writing is probably going to happen. I find &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.atmos-chem-phys.net/&#34;&gt;ACP&lt;/a&gt;’s model quite interesting. The articles are peer reviewed, published for discussion, and then revised by the authors for final publication. I guess it spreads the review work out a bit and allows for multiple voices to be heard before final publication, each with a different approach and background.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Posterior samples</title>
      <link>/./2014/05/22/posterior-samples/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 May 2014 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2014/05/22/posterior-samples/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.compoundchem.com/2014/04/02/a-rough-guide-to-spotting-bad-science/&#34;&gt;A rough guide to spotting bad science&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;http://simplystatistics.org/2014/05/07/why-big-data-is-in-trouble-they-forgot-about-applied-statistics/&#34;&gt;Why big data is in trouble: they forgot about applied statistics&lt;/a&gt;. Big data analytics are all well and good but you have to keep in mind that there are statistical properties that govern which inferences are valid. While I’m comfortable giving a lecture I really struggled to get through them in undergrad. &lt;a href=&#34;http://news.sciencemag.org/education/2014/05/lectures-arent-just-boring-theyre-ineffective-too-study-finds&#34;&gt;It turns out they may not be the most effective way to get information to students.&lt;/a&gt; My supervisors, Professor Lidia Morawska, is giving a public talk (free to register) at QUT soon, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.qut.edu.au/institute-for-future-environments/about/news-events/news?news-id=71015&#34;&gt;“Air Quality Reports On Our Mobiles - Do We Care?”&lt;/a&gt; June 6 2014&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Posterior samples</title>
      <link>/./2014/04/26/posterior-samples/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Apr 2014 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2014/04/26/posterior-samples/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I’m teaching science students how to do statistics. It would be great if we could turn them into Bayesians, especially seeing as we’ve just covered the Agresti-Coull correction for estimating proportions from small experiments. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stat.columbia.edu/~gelman/research/published/teachingbayes.pdf&#34;&gt;Andrew Gelman has an interesting paper&lt;/a&gt; on teaching Bayesian statistics to non-statisticians that focuses on the delivery of skills rather than concepts. I would definitely agree with his approach, especially when you consider how he stresses that discussing the model is probably the most important part. NASA have done some work simulating global aerosols and it’s been compiled into &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.itsokaytobesmart.com/post/82630633966/one-of-my-favorite-gifs-of-one-of-my-favorite-nasa&#34;&gt;a neat video&lt;/a&gt; (via &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.itsokaytobesmart.com/&#34;&gt;It’s Okay To Be Smart’s Joe Hanson&lt;/a&gt;). CSIRO have been doing some interesting stuff looking at the production of organic aerosols as well, so this is something I’m paying a bit more attention to at the moment. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.datacamp.com/&#34;&gt;Datacamp&lt;/a&gt; is a set of online labs for learning to use R, covering the basics of R, data analysis and statistical inference, and computational finance and econometrics. &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/of-games-and-code/d90a50c5d58e&#34;&gt;Learn to be a better coder&lt;/a&gt; by improving your communication skills. The most practical (in terms of coding, at least) aspect of this includes using meaningful names and writing comments that describe what the code does when it’s not clear from the code itself.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New papers on the way</title>
      <link>/./2013/08/17/new-papers-on-the-way/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Aug 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2013/08/17/new-papers-on-the-way/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In addition to the Endotoxin paper which was accepted after revisions earlier this week, we are very close to submitting papers on the following topics:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;trends in and ratios of indoor and outdoor PNC in the UPTECH schools&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;24 hour personal sampling and dose metrics for children in the UPTECH schools&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;modern Bayesian spatial statistical techniques&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;particle losses by size in diffusion dryers and thermodenuders&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to these, a few papers are nearing completion but are not yet ready for submission. These include&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;fungus concentrations in the UPTECH schools&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;flame retardants in dust in the UPTECH schools&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;particle emission and deposition rates for indoor sources in the UPTECH schools&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, yes, my plate has been rather full recently with all the various research activities in which I’ve been enlisted. These are all fascinating examples of the interaction of statistics and science and have all required different approaches to quantify what’s going on. Some of these have been fairly obvious modifications to things I’ve already done and some have required me to look quite deeply into new approaches and figure out both what the model is and how we go about implementing it. I am particularly happy with coming to terms with the combination of a Poisson regression model for total counts and a multinomial for proportions within that count, particularly when some of the classes in the multinomial may have zero counts. That model was a challenge but and I think the paper that it gets used in is much stronger than similar papers which have just taken a very naive approach to analysing the data. One of the biggest challenges with this particular paper has been communicating with the scientists I’m working with. These people are definitely not Bayesian statisticians and don’t come from a medical science background, which tends to be more accepting of complex models that replace ANOVA. I’ve had to write a few paragraphs for the flame retardants in dust paper that describe the model we’re using. Hopefully that helps make the analysis more accessible to the co-authors but also those reading the paper who haven’t got postgraduate qualifications in statistics.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Conference posters and an accepted paper</title>
      <link>/./2013/08/09/conference-posters-and-an-accepted-paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Aug 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2013/08/09/conference-posters-and-an-accepted-paper/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Thomas Lumley &lt;a href=&#34;http://notstatschat.tumblr.com/post/57747270796/speed-sessions-at-jsm-2013&#34;&gt;has some thoughts&lt;/a&gt; on poster sessions at JSM 2013. Healthy Buildings 2012 had something I hadn’t seen before - poster presenters were given two minutes at the end of the technical session most relevant to their poster to describe the work they are presenting in the poster session immediately after the talk slot. This gave poster presenters a small taste of presenting at a conference without them needing to prepare a full talk. QUT’s Nano and Molecular Sciences discipline had a poster session during its one day symposium a few months ago and the posters were run off &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thecube.qut.edu.au/&#34;&gt;The Cube&lt;/a&gt;, which allowed people to zoom and rotate a static image of their poster (PDF preferred). Our group will have a few posters at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://eac2013.cz/&#34;&gt;European Aerosol Conference&lt;/a&gt; in a few weeks. Mandana Mazaheri and I have been discussing the issues of transporting posters back and forth internationally, including whether or not to print on cloth and the unwieldy nature of poster tubes. I am a big fan of mailing your poster home once it’s presented but a cloth poster can be folded up and put in your luggage and you can just give it a quick iron before presenting it. I’ve also seen way too many posters that are too busy and have gradient backgrounds. Hopefully by teaching SEB113 students about the principles of good visualisation of data QUT can produce graduates who know not to make ugly posters. &lt;a href=&#34;http://pubs.acs.org/doi/abs/10.1021/es4023706&#34;&gt;Our endotoxin paper got accepted in Environmental Science &amp;amp; Technology&lt;/a&gt; after a frantic couple of days of finalising amendments and responses to reviewer comments. This paper gave me a much better understanding of Bayesian hierarchical linear models and I’m very happy with how the paper turned out. The next step is to resubmit our fungus paper, which includes similar modelling but also uses a Multinomial model with Dirichlet prior to look at the proportions of different fungal genera across the UPTECH schools. There’s yet another paper looking at chemicals in floor dust which we’re also finalising that uses a similar methodology to the fungus paper but has its own subtleties due to some chemicals not being present across all schools.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Posterior samples - July wrap</title>
      <link>/./2013/07/29/posterior-samples---july-wrap/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Jul 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2013/07/29/posterior-samples---july-wrap/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I had some Posterior Samples to share before going on leave but didn’t get around to posting them. Here’s what’s been on my mind this month: Maths and science units are popular with (Kentucky) students until they realise that &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.wsj.com/economics/2013/07/08/math-science-popular-until-students-realize-theyre-hard/&#34;&gt;they’re hard&lt;/a&gt;. While not directly relevant to the Australian university education model it’s probably an important thing for the Science and Engineering Faculty to keep in mind. &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.wsj.com/economics/2013/07/08/math-science-popular-until-students-realize-theyre-hard/&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; I’m looking at ggplot2 more these days, so the idea of a “grammar of graphics” is beginning to resonate with me. &lt;a href=&#34;//www.youtube.com/watch?v=xyGggdg31mc&#34;&gt;Here’s a talk&lt;/a&gt; about building one for &lt;a href=&#34;http://clojure.org/&#34;&gt;clojure&lt;/a&gt; (which I don’t use). Something for me to keep in mind when delivering SEB113 slides this semester is &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/p0sgdgo7mxkoj4h/What%20your%20math%20slides%20dont%20need.pdf&#34;&gt;what your maths slides don’t need&lt;/a&gt;. Probably also good pointers for any PhD students graduating soon. &lt;a href=&#34;http://well.blogs.nytimes.com/2013/07/22/the-kitchen-as-a-pollution-hazard/&#34;&gt;An interesting article in the New York Times&lt;/a&gt; about air pollution from cooking. This is something that ILAQH has a research interest in and our nanotracer paper contains a bit of analysis of inhaled surface area dose from particles that originate from cooking. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2013/07/22/business/in-climbing-income-ladder-location-matters.html&#34;&gt;Another NYT article&lt;/a&gt;, this time with a delicious visualisation of the geographical trends in income disparity and social mobility. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.slate.com/articles/health_and_science/science/2013/07/statistics_and_psychology_multiple_comparisons_give_spurious_results.html&#34;&gt;Andrew Gelman writes at Slate&lt;/a&gt; about some of the problems with scientific publishing and the publication of spurious findings (which isn’t always willingly dishonest). A special “Big Bayes Stories” issue of “Statistical Science” will be published soon, focussing on the real world application of Bayesian statistics where other methods were inapplicable. &lt;a href=&#34;http://xianblog.wordpress.com/2013/07/29/big-bayes-stories/&#34;&gt;Christian Robert has written the preface&lt;/a&gt;; the issue is being edited by Robert, Kerrie Mengersen (one of my PhD supervisors) and Sharon McGrayne, author of “&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Theory-That-Would-Not-Die/dp/1452636850&#34;&gt;The Theory That Would Not Die&lt;/a&gt;”. Also I went to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.questacon.edu.au/&#34;&gt;Questacon&lt;/a&gt; and it was awesome.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I know the impact factor&#39;s not the be all and end all, but...</title>
      <link>/./2013/05/09/i-know-the-impact-factors-not-the-be-all-and-end-all-but.../</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 May 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2013/05/09/i-know-the-impact-factors-not-the-be-all-and-end-all-but.../</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In Australia, at least, the impact factor of the journals you publish in plays a large role in your advance in academia. Universities are always under pressure to publish their research in more prestigious journals, conflating the impact factor of the journal and the impact of the research published in it. There are many ways journals can game their impact factor, many ways researchers can game the indices that describe the impact of their work, etc. That said, it’s always good to aim to produce research that will be accepted in a high quality journal. I’ve been excited about the PLoS journals since their launch and I believe QUT is a subscribing member, which means our publication fees are covered. It’s one of the best Open Access journal groups around and doesn’t appear to be a cash grab like some other publishers who are attempting to use Open Access as a business model to increase profits rather than because they believe in the free dissemination of research. UPTECH collected fungi and endotoxin data at the 25 schools, and we’re about to submit the fungi paper (which means work must continue on the endotoxin paper). I was considering whether we should submit to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.plosone.org/&#34;&gt;PLoS One&lt;/a&gt; (IF 2011: 4.092) and then had a look at what other journals they have which may be an appropriate home. I really think once we get the clinical data from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.woolcock.org.au/&#34;&gt;our Southern collaborators&lt;/a&gt; we should aim to do the best statistical modelling we can. I’m heartened by the fact that the head of the clinical group we’re working with has a strong background in stats and a desire to learn more Bayesian statistics. I don’t know if we can pull it off, but the prospect of having something investigating the role of fungi and endotoxin on child health published in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.plospathogens.org/&#34;&gt;PLoS Pathogens&lt;/a&gt; (IF 2011: 9.172) is exhilarating.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New things in Science and Engineering at QUT</title>
      <link>/./2013/02/18/new-things-in-science-and-engineering-at-qut/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Feb 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2013/02/18/new-things-in-science-and-engineering-at-qut/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today was the first day of O week at QUT, a time when the relative calm of the summer break is disturbed by an influx of 17 year olds and university-run activities that always seem to generate a lot of noise. Is it possible to be a grumpy old man a week shy of 29? I received an email from my supervisor this morning asking if I could take over from one of the other PhD students in our group who had fallen ill last week and not recovered in time for a presentation this morning. The presentation, scheduled for 9am, was to be the first of the inaugural Nanotechnology and Molecular Science HDR (Higher Degree Research, i.e. Doctoral and Masters students) symposium. I’ve been moaning quietly, since starting my PhD in the School of Physical and Chemical Sciences, that the physics discipline had nothing like the School of Mathematics’ &lt;a href=&#34;http://samclifford.info/2012/09/07/qut-school-of-mathematics-postgrad-day-day-1/&#34; title=&#34;QUT School of Mathematics Postgrad Day - Day 1&#34;&gt;Postgrad Day&lt;/a&gt;. I really like Postgrad Day as it’s a good way to see what the other postgrad students are working on, what the research foci are within the school, and for students to improve their public speaking skills by delivering their research to a room of their peers and the other researchers in the school in an environment which is much more supportive than any conference is likely to be. The NMS HDR symposium brought together a number of students and staff from optics, aerosol science, nanomaterials, biotechnology, forensics and other fields within the discipline and allows them to see, perhaps for the first time, the research that others around them are doing. Even though my lab, ILAQH, is part of the Institute for Health and Biomedical Innovation, the distance between us and the remainder of IHBI is probably greater than just the physical distance between the two campuses. We do not seem to be particularly engaged with the culture of the remainder of IHBI and it’s very rare that our group will make the trek across to Kelvin Grove to see a presentation that is a short elevator ride away from the bulk of the IHBI membership. I have really only been to IHBI a few times. The two most recent appearances have been for the IHBI Olympics (a week of activities where research domains compete against each other in fun activities such as Iron Chef and photo scavenger hunt) in 2011 where I performed as part of the Health and Human Wellbeing domain’s talent quest entry, a four person improvisation troupe called “Ha ha… what?”, and to present the work that the PhD students of the UPTECH project had been working on (where we killed half an hour of time before the presentations by playing impro warm-up games). Continuing in this spirit of improvising in front of scientists, I spoke to the NMS HDR symposium at 45 minutes’ notice and in an eight minute talk managed to touch on the key points of the UPTECH project, explaining a small fraction of the science and discussing the richness of the dataset, the questions it will allow us to answer, and the diverse range of people we have involved in the project. I was told by one of the research staff in our group afterwards that it was refreshing to see a talk with no slides and that they were impressed at the quality of a talk that contained such a small amount of preparation and wondered whether I could give a presentation without speaking. Professor Dennis Arnold, the organiser of the symposium, is now based on the same floor as me; he is one of a handful of people on our floor who are not members of ILAQH. I asked him if he thought the day was a success and he was very positive. I sincerely hope that the NMS HDR symposium continues next year and well into the future, as a way to foster interest across the traditional divide of physics vs chemistry. I had to duck out of the symposium early to attend a meeting about one of the new units in the revamped Bachelor of Science degree. Dr Sama Low Choy, one of my supervisors, has asked me to run one of the collaborative workshops in the new &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.qut.edu.au/study/unit-search/unit?unitCode=SEB113&amp;amp;idunit=44499&#34;&gt;quantitative methods unit&lt;/a&gt; (she says it’s because of my impro skills). Today was one of the planning days where we got to grips with the structure of the unit, the way the workshops are to be run and how what we are doing is significantly different to anything we’ve done before. I’ll write more about it later, such as after my first tutorial, but it’s very exciting to see QUT break with tradition and make this unit happen. Through case studies with data sets relevant to their discipline, students will learn about quantitative methods in mathematics and statistics. We are ditching &lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt; tests, removing the need for statistical tables, adding structure to the group work to ensure people don’t get to ride on the effort of others and teaching R and MATLAB in a first year unit that only supposes Maths B. I’m really excited that we’re teaching first year students how to use software that is free (well, at least R is) and far more powerful than Microsoft Excel. One of the problems with MAB101, the old unit, was that the computation was done in Minitab, a piece of software that I’ve never known any researcher to use. One of the workshop leaders said that they want to go back and do undergrad again knowing that this unit now exists; I don’t blame them. This will definitely be an exciting year for me, academically. A new course with new units, new facilities in the Science and Engineering Centre, new collaboration opportunities and the chance to pick somewhere new to move to at the end of the year.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Major achievements this week</title>
      <link>/./2013/02/08/major-achievements-this-week/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Feb 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2013/02/08/major-achievements-this-week/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height:12px;&#34;&gt;final draft of final thesis paper ready to be submitted (pending feedback from one co-author)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;final draft of thesis ready to be submitted (pending feedback from one supervisor)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;got the code working properly for a paper I’m second author on, looking at deposition of ultrafine particles within the lung. While not as big a coding task as the Finnish paper this has been a major slog over the last few weeks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;pretty much sorted out the analysis and graphs for the paper on fungal counts indoor and outdoor in the UPTECH (for which I’m author some way down the line)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;appointment form submitted for my postdoc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Posterior samples</title>
      <link>/./2012/12/27/posterior-samples/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Dec 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/12/27/posterior-samples/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height:12px;&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://andrewgelman.com/2012/12/textbook-for-data-visualization/&#34;&gt;Gelman recommends&lt;/a&gt; Cleveland’s “&lt;a href=&#34;http://books.google.com.au/books/about/The_elements_of_graphing_data.html?id=Y2pqAAAAMAAJ&#34;&gt;The Elements of Graphing Data&lt;/a&gt;” over Tufte’s work for someone looking to put together a data analysis and visualisation couse. I’ll see if I can grab a copy from the library, it sounds interesting.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/video/2012/12/24/science/100000001947354/wrights-law.html&#34;&gt;Jeffrey Wright uses wacky experiments to teach children about the universe, but it is his own personal story that teaches them the true meaning of life.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.quora.com/Google/What-do-statisticians-do-at-Google&#34;&gt;Quora - What do statisticians do at Google?&lt;/a&gt; Some of the answer is deliberately vague, but the answer appears to be “Figure out whether the engineers have made the search algorithms better” and “Try to quantify whether changes to the way ads work have been positive”.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I work in an aerosol science group which has studied tobacco smoke. Something I can’t find in our publication history is a study on marijuana smoke. NORML have &lt;a href=&#34;http://norml.org/library/health-reports/item/norml-s-marijuana-health-mythology&#34;&gt;a page&lt;/a&gt; dedicated to disputing some of the myths surrounding marijuana that come from both the pro- and anti-marijuana camps. The review was done in 1994 so I’d be interested to see how the epidemiological evidence has changed as our equipment has improved. I don’t know that the Queensland government (or QUT) would let us purchase any marijuana to do the study.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hmm. Are bullet points really the way to do this? Merry Christmas!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>GitHub</title>
      <link>/./2012/11/21/github/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Nov 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/11/21/github/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;GitHub for Windows can be such a pain sometimes. I guess it’s partially my fault for attempting to use version control on the compiled PDF of a LaTeX document, but I spent a fair amount of time today attempting to fix up a colleague’s local repository. I’m now a bit more familiar with cherry-pick and rebase but it would have been nice to have it just work. For some reason, GitHub for Windows on this colleague’s computer simply &lt;em&gt;will not sync properly&lt;/em&gt;; my colleague has had to become a bit more familiar with the common commands (push, pull, fetch, commit, merge). It works fine on their Mac, though. I run GitHub for OS X at home and it’s an absolute dream. At work (Windows XP) I have had no end of trouble with various programs like TortoiseGit. I think when I start my post-doc I’ll organise to have my computer converted to a Linux system. After all that, though, we did make some pretty good progress on the modelling in this paper. I’m not quite sure which journal we’ll be sending it to but it’s a really nice piece of work with some personal monitoring data, simple but informative analysis and some very creative use of the base graphics system in R.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Graphs again</title>
      <link>/./2012/11/19/graphs-again/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Nov 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/11/19/graphs-again/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Now that I’ve handed a draft of my final thesis paper to my supervisors/co-authors, I’ve got a little head space to work on another paper that’s been sitting on my to do list for a while. One of the challenges with this paper is coming up with a way to represent data relating to a total of over 100 students at 24 schools. Summarising at the school level ignores a lot of the within-school variation but attempting to use standard plotting approaches can lead to some very complex and visually busy graphs. Add to this that we can’t really use colour and it’s getting a bit tricky. I’ve had a few more looks at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stat.columbia.edu/~gelman/research/published/dodhia.pdf&#34;&gt;Gelman, Pasarica and Dodhia paper&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://samclifford.info/2012/10/30/turning-tables-into-graphs/&#34; title=&#34;Turning tables into graphs&#34;&gt;that I’ve previously talked about&lt;/a&gt;. While it doesn’t have an example of what I actually want to plot, it does make me think more about what kind of data I’ve got, whether they’re continuous, categorical or count, what their ranges are and what sort of variation occurs. With 24 schools it’s possible to do a 4 x 6 or 6 x 4 grid of sub-plots, and within those subplots we can generally get across what sort of variation there is at the school level. Not everyone likes such a layout, though, so I’ve been looking into grouped/stacked barplots, changing the ordering of the grouping (variable by school vs school by variable) and combining time series and barplots in the same graph (which is actually quite a good way of visualising the data we have, but can’t be done for 100 students). In the end, it’s going to come down to being creative enough to come up with a few alternatives and asking my co-authors which version they think sells the message best. I pretty much refuse to resort to pie graphs (because the scaling in area can be misleading) and feel really uncomfortable about using box-plots to summarise school-level variation. I have nothing against box plots, but for the size of the data we have at each school, summarising with a minimum, maximum and the 25th, 50th and 75th percentiles is going to be very difficult without shifting to a &lt;a href=&#34;http://samclifford.info/2012/10/25/anova-again/&#34; title=&#34;ANOVA again&#34;&gt;Bayesian ANOVA&lt;/a&gt;. Still, it’s a really interesting piece of science with some quite unique challenges in terms of the analysis and representation of that analysis (and the raw data). Edit: and it also makes me appreciate what designers (including my two housemates) have to go through, with people saying “No, I don’t like it” but not always having some constructive advice that’s actually possible to put into practice. Edit 2: &lt;a href=&#34;http://andrewgelman.com/2012/11/tradeoffs-in-information-graphics/&#34;&gt;Relevant new Gelman blog post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Where do I want to go?</title>
      <link>/./2012/11/01/where-do-i-want-to-go/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Nov 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/11/01/where-do-i-want-to-go/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As my PhD draws to a close, I’m beginning to spend some time thinking about where I want to go to work after QUT. I applied for, have been offered and now accepted, a 0.5 full time equivalent position for one year with the NHMRC Centre for Air quality and health Research and evaluation (CAR) which will start when I submit my PhD. ILAQH will contribute the remaining 0.5 FTE so that I’ve got full time employment, jointly between CAR and QUT, and I’ll be based in Brisbane. The next year is going to be a flurry of paper writing, collaboration and reviewing the work the group does. I’ve been talking about moving overseas for work for quite some time. I’ve been at QUT since I started undergrad in 2002 and while I’ve done a few subjects here and there at other universities (computational physics at UQ, some climatology at USQ) and taught maths at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.kromestudios.com/&#34;&gt;Krome Studios&lt;/a&gt; for about a year (one or two sessions a week) I’ve been at QUT almost constantly. This wouldn’t necessarily be a permanent move overseas, I am open to coming back to Australia (after all, it’s where my family is) after a few years of postdoctoral work overseas. The list below is a few places I’ve been considering and have previously checked their websites for postdoc work. I would like to continue working on Bayesian statistical applications but also perhaps continue to go further into methodology and work a bit more on the computational statistics side of things as I feel my undergrad/honours skills are getting a bit rusty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.helsinki.fi/bsg/&#34;&gt;University of Helsinki - Bayesian Statistics Group&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://becs.aalto.fi/en/research/bayes/&#34;&gt;Aalto University - Bayesian Statistical Methods&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sph.umn.edu/biostatistics/ourfaculty/bayesian/&#34;&gt;University of Minnesota - Biostatistics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stat.osu.edu/&#34;&gt;Ohio State University - Statistics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.isds.duke.edu/&#34;&gt;Duke University - Statistical Science&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stat.colostate.edu/&#34;&gt;Colorado State University (Boulder) - Statistics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.samsi.info/&#34;&gt;Statistical and Applied Mathematical Sciences Institute&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://ncar.ucar.edu/&#34;&gt;National Center for Atmospheric Research&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m undecided as to whether I should apply to work at Berkeley, Stanford, MIT, Harvard, or any other big name places. Sure, they’re prestigious but I got some advice from a friend a few months ago that what you want in a job is&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;good people to work with&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a project that interests you&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a project that’s interesting to others (which means they can hire you next)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and don’t want to end up slogging my way through six to twelve months of interesting work with someone at a big name institution that I don’t really want to work with.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Third time&#39;s a charm</title>
      <link>/./2012/09/25/third-times-a-charm/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Sep 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/09/25/third-times-a-charm/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;After getting rejected by an applied statistics journal and a more methodological statistics journal we’ve decided to send the Finnish paper to an environmental statistics journal. I think it’s a more natural home for this paper as it straddles the boundary of model development and the analysis of observational environmental data. A new version of the preprint will appear &lt;a href=&#34;http://arxiv.org/abs/1207.0558&#34;&gt;on arXiv&lt;/a&gt; in about 12 hours. I’m also still redrafting the first UPTECH paper of my thesis. With the Finnish paper resubmitted it’ll be the focus of my work over the next few days. I think the modelling is now much improved (although I might try an alternative specification) after taking reviewer comments into account from its earlier rejection. Once I’ve got this last modelling question sorted out and the analysis is written up (not much has to change in the methodology section) I can restart work on my final thesis paper. There are two similar papers coming up in my immediate post-thesis future where I’m going to have the chance to learn more about the use of Gaussian processes. While INLA does some nice GMRF approximations for Gaussian fields [1] there are some challenges that we’ll face with this data. I might also need to read up on the use of dynamic linear models for modelling the evolution of a parameter with time. [1] Lindgren, F.; Rue, H. &amp;amp; Lindström, J. (2011) An explicit link between Gaussian fields and Gaussian Markov random fields: the stochastic partial differential equation approach, _Journal of the Royal Statistical Society: Series B (Statistical Methodology)__ 73_, 423-498. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.math.ntnu.no/inla/r-inla.org/papers/spde-jrssb-revised.pdf&#34;&gt;R-INLA&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UPTECH paper review</title>
      <link>/./2012/09/19/uptech-paper-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Sep 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/09/19/uptech-paper-review/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I’m currently reworking the &lt;a href=&#34;http://arxiv.org/abs/1206.3833&#34;&gt;second paper&lt;/a&gt; of my thesis (or at least the paper that was planned as the second paper) to address the reviewers’ comments. Probably the biggest problem with the split panel design we’ve ended up with is that there are no measurements from the long term monitoring stations at the same time as the first ten schools’ measurements are being taken. So, what’s due to annual variation [1] and what’s due to spatial variation, e.g. [2]? This has meant going back to our models and looking at more appropriate ways to model the spatial and temporal trends to allow us to decouple the spatial and temporal variation. I’ve still got to finalise things with my supervisors, but I think if we focus less on model comparison and talk more about the computational issues and put forward a single model (which will be used as the basis for the third paper of my PhD) then we’ll have a good paper for a journal which focuses more on the scientific application than the statistical theory. After all, the paper is not a novel contribution to the field of semi-parametric regression but it’s a very novel application of semi-parametric regression to multi-site observational data recorded from a split panel design. All in all I think the paper is much more at home in the aerosol science literature than the applied statistics literature and the comments we got upon the previous rejection will make it a better paper. I’m certainly much more optimistic about this paper than I was immediately after its rejection. I showed some of the results of the new modelling to some colleagues today and while the interpretation of the graphs wasn’t immediately obvious (I showed them pictures without explanatory text) they seemed interested in what it said about the UPTECH study. [1] Mejía, Jaime F., Wraith, Darren E., Mengersen, Kerrie L., &amp;amp; Morawska, Lidia (2007) Trends in size classified particle number concentration in subtropical Brisbane, Australia, based on a 5 year study. Atmospheric Environment, 41(5), pp. 1064-1079. &lt;a href=&#34;http://eprints.qut.edu.au/5778/&#34;&gt;QUT ePrints&lt;/a&gt;. [2] Mejía, Jaime F., Morawska, Lidia, &amp;amp; Mengersen, Kerrie L. (2008) Spatial variation in particle number size distributions in a large metropolitan area. Atmospheric Chemistry and Physics, 8(5), pp. 1127-1138. &lt;a href=&#34;http://eprints.qut.edu.au/15395/&#34;&gt;QUT ePrints&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My first field work</title>
      <link>/./2012/09/17/my-first-field-work/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Sep 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/09/17/my-first-field-work/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It’s been three and a half years since I started my PhD program and the UPTECH measurement campaign finished a matter of weeks ago. So I’m a little late to the game but last week was my first field trip campaign. Rohan Jayaratne had been trying to organise this trip over the last two weeks, waiting for a time where the wind would be blowing in the right direction, checking the wind forecasts every day for a while. On Tuesday we finally headed out to do the measurements with another PhD student, Megat Azman Megat Mokhtar. We’d had talks about what sort of questions we’d be attempting to answer and how we could ensure we collected data that would allow us to answer them. What started out as a fifteen minute chat about equipment turned into a long discussion about semi-parametric regression and how interactions of non-linear effects can be fit. What was going to originally be just a publication of some observational results is probably going to end up with some generalised additive models attempting to model the interactions we expect to see. Rohan, Megat and I packed up the car at about 8:30 and drove out to the Gateway Motorway to do some roadside measurements. We took some &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.aerasense.com/&#34;&gt;Nanotracers&lt;/a&gt; and a CPC and spent the day taking continous measurements. The Nanotracers are very new and we’ve been using them with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ilaqh.qut.edu.au/Misc/UPTECH%20Study%20Design%2029%20July%202011.pdf&#34;&gt;UPTECH&lt;/a&gt; to measure child exposure to ultrafine particles. It was interesting to see the setup of the equipment and gave me a greater appreciation for just how much work everyone put in to the UPTECH study. [caption id=“attachment_478” align=“aligncenter” width=“225”][&lt;img src=&#34;p9120053.jpg?w=225&#34; title=&#34;Sam wearing nanotracers&#34; /&gt;](&lt;a href=&#34;http://samcliffordinfo.files.wordpress.com/2012/09/p9120053.jpg&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;http://samcliffordinfo.files.wordpress.com/2012/09/p9120053.jpg&lt;/a&gt;) The Philips Aerasense Nanotracer: fastest personal sampler in the West[/caption] Megat brought two walkie-talkies with him for us to use to communicate when one of us was away from where we’d set up. To relieve the (my?) boredom in some parts, I treated Megat and Rohan to a rendition of Toto’s “Africa” and Four Non Blondes’ “What’s Up?” (often called “What’s going on?”). The weather was very pleasant, the wind more or less exactly what we wanted and we managed to get about six hours of measurements before heading home. We’re now at the stage of having the data cleaned (checking for errors in the measurements) and doing some exploratory data analysis. In the coming weeks, provided I’ve got time for it, we’ll be looking at our modelling. I hope to put a preprint up when we’ve submitted it. It’s going to be a very interesting piece of modelling and Rohan sees it as an update to a paper our group has previously written but with better analysis and a more novel data collection technique. I’m excited.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rejection of second paper</title>
      <link>/./2012/09/03/rejection-of-second-paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Sep 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/09/03/rejection-of-second-paper/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This morning I heard back from Annals of Applied Stats about the rejection of a paper I’d submitted there maybe a month ago. Again, the reviewer comments are insightful and helpful and will help improve the paper for its publication in an environmental science journal. I find that reading the reviewer comments is a great way to overcome the crushing feeling one gets as a young scientist when dealing with a letter of rejection of a paper.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A few things from today</title>
      <link>/./2012/08/16/a-few-things-from-today/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Aug 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/08/16/a-few-things-from-today/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://xianblog.wordpress.com/&#34;&gt;Christian Robert&lt;/a&gt; is visiting my stats research group at the moment. This morning he spoke to our group’s fortnightly meeting about a few issues in model choice and how to improve our Bayesian computation. The meeting was fairly well attended and was in fact &lt;a href=&#34;http://conidialcoleopticide.wordpress.com/&#34;&gt;Luisa&lt;/a&gt;‘s first BRAG meeting. The model choice stuff was interesting and involved a discussion of Bayes factors, the BIC and DIC, and posterior predictive densities and checks. I’m not especially familiar with the Bayes factor approach (despite our group reading a paper about them recently) but did pick up the criticism from Robert that while the BIC is consistent with Bayes factors, it’s not a very Bayesian approach and is a limited representation of the impact of the prior. There were some good little bits about the need to ensure that when using the BF to choose between nested models you don’t end up using priors that are so diffuse that there’s no concentration of support in the posterior. He also spoke briefly about the Kullback-Leibler Divergence and got into a discussion with Chris Strickland about model averaging with the BF to compare candidate models. Clearly I’ve got some reading to do. We didn’t have much time to talk about improved mixing for MCMC but Robert did offer tempering as a way to come up with better proposals. The basic idea is that instead of using the posterior, π(θ)×f(x’θ), you look at {π(θ)×f(x’θ)}^α (for α &amp;lt;&amp;lt; 1) to flatten out the posterior in order to allow a fuller exploration of the target distribution. This may end up giving you more density in the tails of the posterior (which is probably multidimensional) but the argument could be made (perhaps by Aad van der Vaart) that it’s more important to have a vague posterior that better captures the truth than a very tight posterior CI around something which is wrong. Tempering is apparently Robert’s “go to” trick when his MCMC is slowly mixing. I know Sama Low Choy, one of my supervisors, has mentioned it a few times. So I might try looking at it for the Finnish paper’s successors. One of my aerosol science group’s PhD students, Tenzin Wangchuk, gave his confirmation seminar today. Tenzin is with us for three months every year and spends the rest of his time in Bhutan. Tenzin’s work will look at indoor air quality in rural Bhutan and what factors (e.g. cooking, outdoor air exchange, fuel types) influence the concentration of fine particles and gaseous pollutants. I had a few meetings with Tenzin last time he was here, where we discussed approaches to data analysis, and experimental design. Tenzin’s a really nice guy; one of my favourite things about working at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ilaqh.qut.edu.au/&#34;&gt;ILAQH&lt;/a&gt; is the opportunity to meet people from around the world who have different experiences and interesting projects. Tenzin’s work is similar to t&lt;a href=&#34;http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/j.1600-0668.2010.00679.x/full&#34;&gt;he studies ILAQH have done in Laos&lt;/a&gt; but don’t focus on the health aspect. It’ll be interesting to see the results of his work. I’m also trying to get a beginners’ R reading group up and running between ILAQH and BRAG. A few ILAQH members attended a two day course run by one of the PhD students in BRAG but I’ve really found the reading group structure to be quite useful for learning from a shared position of ignorance of, but interest in, a topic. I think the real strength of the model is that it encourages attendees to be self-reliant for their learning while still providing an environment for seeking help. If you don’t do the readings and the work then it’s very hard to keep up with what the group is doing and to participate in the discussion. So hopefully it discourages the kind of person who wants to sit back and have everyone else do the work (undergrad group assignments are the worst for this) or at least encourages them to do the work. I’ve got a few PhD students expressing interest so far, as well as one or two of the academics! I’ll come along to the first few meetings to get the ball rolling, get everyone aware of each others’ learning styles and backgrounds, give an overview of what R is and then give them a few resources and references to get started before leaving them to their own devices to study what they want to learn.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Starting more papers</title>
      <link>/./2012/07/17/starting-more-papers/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jul 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/07/17/starting-more-papers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the benefits of being a statistically curious researcher is that you get to read about all sorts of cool stuff. The UPTECH project is generating a huge amount of time series data, some of which have change points, non-linear behaviour, trends, and all sorts of other quirks. I’ve spent most of my time learning about the use of splines but over the last year have been exposed to Gaussian processes (and I guess I would say splines are a special case) and Gaussian Markov Random Fields. I’ve been having the occasional chat with the other researchers about how to analyse the time series data they’re working with and have stumbled across some really neat methods. Apart from the work I’ve been doing on spline models with my Finnish collaborators, interesting ideas for analysing time series data include Treed Linear Models, Treed Gaussian Processes [1,2] and Dirichlet Process Mixtures of GLMs [3]. The tree nature of the first two models I mentioned is apparent in its partitioning of the covariate space into regions in which the behaviour is locally linear. Change points are placed where the behaviour changes and each partition has its own linear mean and its own variance estimate. This is a fairly simple model to fit but it’s a bit limited by its only using linear functions. The treed GP relaxes this and spends its time fitting a more GP within each partition, with the focus on the covariance relationship. The third, DP mixtures of GLMs gives much smoother estimates of the mean and credible interval and has some really nice properties courtesy of the DP (which looks to be superior to tree based clustering). I find the tree structure of these models quite interesting and the treed linear model appears to be, conceptually, a mix of a multiple changepoint model and a piecewise linear regression spline with wombling knots. I’m not 100% sure how to apply these but an initial chat makes me think they will be very applicable and I’m looking forward to some exploratory data analysis. [1] [Gramacy, R. B. (2007). tgp: An r package for bayesian nonstationary, semiparametric nonlinear regression and design by treed gaussian process models. Journal of Statistical Software 19(9), 1-46.](&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jstatsoft.org/v19/i09/&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;http://www.jstatsoft.org/v19/i09/&lt;/a&gt;) [2] [Gramacy, R. B. and H. K. H. Lee (2008). Bayesian treed gaussian process models with an application to computer modeling. Journal of the American Statistical Association 103(483), 1119-1130.](&lt;a href=&#34;http://amstat.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1198/016214508000000689&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;http://amstat.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1198/016214508000000689&lt;/a&gt;) (&lt;a href=&#34;http://arxiv.org/abs/0710.4536&#34;&gt;arXiv preprint&lt;/a&gt;) [3] [Hannah, L. A., D. M. Blei, and W. B. Powell (2011). Dirichlet process mixtures of generalized linear models. Journal of Machine Learning Research 12, 1923-1953.](&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.princeton.edu/~blei/papers/HannahBleiPowell2011.pdf&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;http://www.cs.princeton.edu/~blei/papers/HannahBleiPowell2011.pdf&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Two papers submitted</title>
      <link>/./2012/07/06/two-papers-submitted/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jul 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/07/06/two-papers-submitted/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the last two weeks I’ve sent two papers to Annals of Applied Statistics and uploaded them to the arXiv. This fulfills the minimum publication requirements for a PhD by publication at QUT. So it’s a milestone on the way to completion. Now I just have to sort out a fourth paper as backup, give two presentations at next week’s conference, organise a final seminar session, compile all my work into a thesis and get it to my supervisors. On top of my immediate thesis work on spatio-temporal modelling, I’ve got a paper for Healthy Buildings on methods for analysing the UPTECH survey data that’ll get published, a paper on which I’m coauthor (particle losses in a thermodenuder system) that’s almost finished and the microbiology paper I wrote about previously. Busy.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Wald is not enough</title>
      <link>/./2012/06/25/the-wald-is-not-enough/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jun 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/06/25/the-wald-is-not-enough/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I’m working on a talk I’m presenting at Healthy Buildings 2012 while I do some travel to ISBA. My supervisor, who is president of the Healthy Buildings conference this year, saw &lt;a href=&#34;http://samclifford.info/2012/06/01/statistics-not-just-for-statisticians/&#34;&gt;a blog post of mine&lt;/a&gt; and thought that it would make a good presentation for the student plenary session. The basic point of the talk is that the quality of scientific research is greatly improved by ensuring that appropriate statistical analysis is performed and presented clearly. There have been so many papers and presentations I’ve seen where the authors just stop at descriptive statistics of their data and draw inferences just from describing the data. If we’re lucky they’ll do a t-test or ANOVA. If we’re not, they’ll just calculate summary statistics and perhaps a correlation between the response and the covariates rather than doing any statistical modelling. The problem isn’t restricted to indoor air quality and climate, the focus of this conference, though. &lt;a href=&#34;http://conidialcoleopticide.wordpress.com/&#34;&gt;A friend of mine&lt;/a&gt; has come across the same issue in her literature review for using microbes to control insect pests. There are some groups doing some amazing scientific work with robust statistics, such as Hugh Possingham’s group at UQ who look at applying econometric principles to conservation (think triage for species rather than patients). At the risk of spoiling the ending of my talk, being “the statistician” in my group has given me the opportunity to work on some interesting aerosol science problems such as particle loss in instrumentation, the multi-modality of SMPS data and how it affects automatic processing, microbiology populations in classrooms, the fate of non-background ions and determining exposure measures from personal samplers and monitoring equipment that have different time steps. In turn, I have introduced the researchers I’m working with to new statistical techniques (often with R code) which they can adapt and use in future work. Every group needs a statistician in it, but not just to be handed the data to analyse and used as a black box where data goes in and analysis comes out. For starters, the statistician needs to know what the data actually describe. But the statistician should be there to build the skill set of the group. We can’t expect that every scientist has PhD level statistical skills but the scientist needs to be comfortable going beyond ANOVA to investigate what’s happening in their experimental or observational data. P.S. the title for this talk was inspired by a brief conversation with my ISBA room-mate about how great statistics-based puns are.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hug a Climate Scientist Day</title>
      <link>/./2012/06/12/hug-a-climate-scientist-day/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Jun 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/06/12/hug-a-climate-scientist-day/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;According to Crikey.com.au’s “First Dog on the Moon” today, June 12, is &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.crikey.com.au/hug-a-climate-scientist-day-2012/&#34;&gt;Hug a Climate Scientist Day&lt;/a&gt;. The day was proclaimed by First Dog in response to the threats that climate scientists receive. The aim of the day is to show climate scientists that their work is appreciated and that we love them as people. I work in an air quality research group so it’s not difficult to find a climate scientist to hug (although not all of us in the group work in climate research). If you happen to not be one of the small group of people who have ready access to climate scientists, First Dog recommends you “&lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.crikey.com.au/firstblog/files/2012/05/HugAClimateScientistJune.jpg&#34;&gt;find a fellow warmenist and cling trembling to each other in the knowledge that it’s too late for even the adorable climate scientists to save us&lt;/a&gt;”. I’m going to try to get a photo of me hugging a climate scientist today. Unfortunately, our group’s director isn’t in today. [caption id=“attachment_260” align=“aligncenter” width=“228”][&lt;img src=&#34;hugaclimatescientistjune.jpg?w=228&#34; title=&#34;HugAClimateScientistJune&#34; /&gt;](&lt;a href=&#34;http://samcliffordinfo.files.wordpress.com/2012/06/hugaclimatescientistjune.jpg&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;http://samcliffordinfo.files.wordpress.com/2012/06/hugaclimatescientistjune.jpg&lt;/a&gt;) First Dog on the Moon’s “Hug a Climate Scientist Day”[/caption]&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Statistics - not just for statisticians</title>
      <link>/./2012/06/01/statistics---not-just-for-statisticians/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jun 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/06/01/statistics---not-just-for-statisticians/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;An article in &lt;a href=&#34;http://theconversation.edu.au/top-cited-academics-honoured-but-wheres-the-humanity-7348&#34;&gt;The Conversation&lt;/a&gt; made the rounds in our office yesterday and prompted a discussion with one of my colleagues about the role of statistics in scientific papers. The article itself talks about Australians who received an award from Thomson Reuters on the basis of publishing frequently cited work and discusses the different culture in science and the humanities when it comes to publication and citation. The basic argument is that the awards are skewed to the sciences where publication is traditionally by journal article and citation in other journal articles is picked up more than in the humanities where monographs/books are the traditional means of disseminating information. One of the academics interviewed makes the point that science is much more collaborative, with researchers working in teams to achieve the goals of a project. One of the email discussants in our group offered the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Graham Farquhar from the Australian National University is Australia’s citation laureate. Graham’s belief is this: start with a really good hypothesis driven question that no-one has answered and answer it. Deliver the answer with robust science and, voila, you have highly cited work. Coming up with the questions is hard though. Thinking seven impossible questions before breakfast is probably a daily norm in Graham’s existence. Doing this, and maintaining a normal personality is difficult though, but he manages quite well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A colleague talked to me about this idea of Farquhar’s in terms of a paper of his that he thought did well to answer an unanswered question. The aim of the paper was to offer an explanation for a physical phenomenon that is known in aerosols but it’s not well known why this phenomenon occurs. We then got into an argument about the robustness of the science, not based on the science that had been done (it was a synthesis of previous work by other authors), but because the evidence hadn’t all been included in a model that drew all these reviews together in a statistical manner. Scientists love &lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt; tests. They are simple tests which tell you if there’s a difference between two groups and are appropriate in some, but not all, instances, and are a good first step for exploratory data analysis. I was making the point that a Bayesian meta-analysis would have been far more appropriate as it’s a technique which is specifically designed to draw multiple sources of information together in a single model to provide a better estimate of an effect size. The Bayesian approach would have also helped here as a review of the literature could be used to determine priors such that even if no new data was collected for this paper, inferences could be drawn based on the current state of knowledge. I think every research group should hire a statistician, have them retrain the researchers in how to use statistics, including GLMs/GAMs, spatial analysis, time series methods, and Bayesian inference in order to build capacity within the group. The statistician can then work with the scientists to ensure that new papers include the best analysis of results possible and to also review old papers to see if there’s any low hanging fruit in terms of interesting experiments/observations which could be re-analysed with something more than ANOVA or linear regression. Statistics isn’t just for statisticians; we need to get away from the idea that doing more than the bare minimum for a paper is going too far. Apparently QUT is reviewing the way it teaches statistics to science students (something which is long overdue, my recollection is that MAB101 is an awful unit full of statistical techniques relevant to agricultural trials) so I’m hopeful that we can teach students statistical techniques that are relevant to them in an exciting way. I hope we don’t swing too far and just give them the exact tools they need and nothing else, because then we’re limiting graduates. If you’ve got the brain power to deal with atmospheric chemistry and/or physics, you should be able to handle statistics. Not everyone goes through to do advanced level statistical units but it shouldn’t be too much of a jump from collecting experimental data to analysing it in R with a package appropriate to your field. Edited to add: The point I’m trying to make here is that all researchers should have a basic understanding of exploratory/descriptive data analysis, simple GLMs (even if it’s just using glm() in R) and the ability to communicate the physical results in terms of the statistical modelling. I don’t expect that all scientists will go and become proficient in the use of Bayesian non-parametrics, but scientists should be able to start with some scatter plots, box plots and ANOVA to look for differences and then use regression to explain those differences.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bioaerosols and lab reorganisation</title>
      <link>/./2012/05/22/bioaerosols-and-lab-reorganisation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 May 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/05/22/bioaerosols-and-lab-reorganisation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yesterday I had a meeting with my supervisor and two colleagues about looking at the microbiological measurements we’ve been taking as part of UPTECH. It was an interesting meeting if only for the chance to really see how the four of us are approaching this paper from the point of view of our backgrounds. Heidi Salonen, who has been working on microbiology with us since Caroline Duchaine went back to Canada, will be the lead author on the paper. She’s got a background in OH&amp;amp;S and this was really clear when she was talking about the need to quantify safe levels of microbiology. I was sitting there asking the questions that will shape the data analysis, like what sort of relationships we anticipate. Mandana Mazaheri was focussing on making use of the rest of the UPTECH data as best we can (we have a huge Access database) and Lidia Morawska was making sure none of us got carried away and that we could agree on an approach. I’m going to use this paper as an opportunity to push R as our statistical engine rather than Excel (which is all that scientists seem to use). I’m being brought on as the statistician and really don’t want to about learning how to use Excel and write VBA to do the things that can be done trivially in R. R’s plots are a lot better than what we tend to see in Excel and Mandana and I have been learning how polygon() works so we can shade the region between two particle diameter distributions in a plot for a report she’s working on. Mandana’s actually been quite good about learning R and seems to have stuck with it more than a lot of the other PhD students (except for Farhad Salimi, who is doing some really interesting work). I’d really like to use this paper as an opportunity to have people use git but Mandana and Heidi aren’t programmers, and I think even using R is going to stretch them. A &lt;a href=&#34;windows.github.com&#34;&gt;Windows GUI for git&lt;/a&gt; was released recently and I’m finding it better for committing and pushing than TortoiseGit or the command line git client as neither of these deal with my ssh keys particularly well. I don’t know what the deal is there. Perhaps it’s better under a more modern version of Windows. I also spent some time in the lab today helping reorganise it. Me being in the lab is a rarer event than the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/18141625&#34;&gt;recent annular eclipse&lt;/a&gt;. I don’t work in the lab and so am not responsible for the mess left over from experiments and not putting things away when I’m done, but I do rely on the lab’s monitoring data so it’s only fair that I help out from time to time. Just don’t ask me to help out with any of the science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://knowyourmeme.com/photos/234739-i-have-no-idea-what-im-doing&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;fa5.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bioaerosols</title>
      <link>/./2012/05/17/bioaerosols/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 May 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/05/17/bioaerosols/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of our researchers asked me to come along to a meeting next week to discuss my potential involvement on a paper as “the statistician”. It’s part of the UPTECH project but it’s not the spatial distribution of outdoor aerosols, which is what I’ve been working on for my PhD. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.uku.fi/vaitokset/2009/ISBN978.951.802.908.6salonen.htm&#34;&gt;Heidi Salonen&lt;/a&gt;, a visiting researcher from Finland, is working on UPTECH looking at the concentration of microbiological agents in indoor air. Luckily I don’t have to be &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Egon_Spengler&#34;&gt;an expert on spores, moulds and fungus&lt;/a&gt; but it’ll be interesting to pick up a bit more knowledge from the quite broad field of aerosols. I’ve been asked a few times to be involved with some ILAQH projects but at the moment it’s been limited to helping write the statistical methodology for grant applications or discussing an approach for data from another part of the UPTECH project. As far as I recall, this is the first time that someone from ILAQH has come and said “Hey, I want you to be a co-author on this paper”. This sort of thing is what I’ve been looking forward to as I finish off my PhD, the chance to get out of my specific topic and start looking at other peoples’ work. I’ll probably try to recommend a non-parametric regression technique but I have a feeling it’ll be a classically designed experiment and that all we’ll need is some t-tests.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A mostly Fin(n)ish[ed] paper</title>
      <link>/./2012/05/09/a-mostly-finnished-paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 May 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/05/09/a-mostly-finnished-paper/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The paper I started with some collaborators in Finland (&lt;a href=&#34;https://tuhat.halvi.helsinki.fi/portal/en/persons/bjarke-moelgaard(74a8081d-a379-4e4b-9aff-e9b85bc98c78)/publications.html&#34;&gt;Bjarke Mølgaard&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rni.helsinki.fi/~jic/&#34;&gt;Jukka Corander&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.atm.helsinki.fi/~khameri/&#34;&gt;Kaarle Hämeri&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://tuhat.halvi.helsinki.fi/portal/en/persons/tareq-hussein(3aacf8e7-f431-41b0-9303-1abaf1897bf7)/publications.html?page=5&amp;amp;rendering=vancouver&#34;&gt;Tareq Hussein&lt;/a&gt;) almost a year ago is nearly done. It’s been nearly done a few times, but now all that remains is to do a little bit of model choice regarding the separability of the effects of meteorology on ultrafine particle number concentration. We’ve been using git to send the paper and code back and forth (well, Bjarke and I have) and I’ve found that to be a really simple way of collaboratively writing code and a paper. To see the changes made, one need only look at the commit details. Much nicer than using tracked changes in Word and emailing a bunch of versions of the same file back and forth and trying to do complicated merges of changes. I am really looking forward to submitting this paper, as it’s probably the most methodological work I’ll get out of my PhD (the other papers are largely applications of some novel techniques to the UPTECH project’s data). It’s quite a nice blending of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://tuhat.halvi.helsinki.fi/portal/en/publications/forecasting-sizefra(9c6ae07d-af34-4909-a4f9-d758bc7a4795).html&#34;&gt;work done by the Finnish authors previously&lt;/a&gt; [1] as part of Bjarke’s PhD and some of the ideas in my first paper [2]. While I don’t know that it will totally revolutionise atmospheric modelling (in the way that I’m sure we all hope it will), it’s quite a nice technique that increases the flexibility of the Generalised Additive Model and hopefully encourage anyone interested in doing Bayesian modelling with the GAM to stop using &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.uow.edu.au/~mwand/&#34;&gt;Matt Wand&lt;/a&gt;’s WinBUGS approach [3, 4]. To be clear, I find GAMs in WinBUGS particularly cumbersome to code given that WinBUGS doesn’t deal with matrix operations very well and the use of P-splines requires a lot of matrix operations. Having said that, though, Wand’s code is a nice intro to Bayesian splines where you don’t have to write your own MCMC sampler. I just think it has some limitations that are not easily overcome. I’d like to present this to a statistics conference but it wasn’t anywhere near ready enough to demonstrate at ISBA 2012 when I was submitting an abstract. [1] B. Mølgaard, T. Hussein, J. Corander, K. Hämeri, Forecasting size-fractionated particle number concentrations in the urban atmosphere, Atmospheric Environment, Volume 46, January 2012, Pages 155-163, ISSN 1352-2310, 10.1016/j.atmosenv.2011.10.004. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1352231011010491&#34;&gt;ScienceDirect&lt;/a&gt; [2] S. Clifford, S. Low Choy, T. Hussein, K. Mengersen, L. Morawska, Using the Generalised Additive Model to model the particle number count of ultrafine particles, Atmospheric Environment, Volume 45, Issue 32, October 2011, Pages 5934-5945, ISSN 1352-2310, 10.1016/j.atmosenv.2011.05.004. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1352231011004766&#34;&gt;ScienceDirect&lt;/a&gt; [3] C. M. Crainiceanu, D. Ruppert. M. P. Wand, Bayesian Analysis for Penalized Spline Regression Using WinBUGS, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jstatsoft.org/v14/i14/&#34;&gt;Journal of Statistical Software, Volume 14, Issue 14, September 2005&lt;/a&gt;. [4] J. K. Marley, M. P. Wand, Non-Standard Semiparametric Regression via BRugs, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jstatsoft.org/v37/i05&#34;&gt;Journal of Statistical Software, Volume 37, Issue 5, November 2010&lt;/a&gt;. P.S. I apologise for the awful pun, but &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Micallef_P(r)ogram(me)&#34;&gt;Shaun Micallef&lt;/a&gt; has been on my mind recently.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dear Mr Supercomputer</title>
      <link>/./2012/04/17/dear-mr-supercomputer/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Apr 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/04/17/dear-mr-supercomputer/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;After ensuring that my colleagues were pushing their results to our git repository it’s now all steam ahead on this Finnish paper. I’ve got my MATLAB code running on the QUT supercomputer right now. It’s all very exciting watching it go and not run out of memory. Hopefully I can get these results sorted, do some model comparison, plotting and then send the document around for some final drafting within the next two or three weeks (the bulk of the theory section of the paper is finished). It would’ve been nice to be able to present this work at ISBA but I think I’d rather talk about the applied paper that discusses the spatio-temporal trends from the UPTECH project.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dirty Science today</title>
      <link>/./2012/03/29/dirty-science-today/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Mar 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/03/29/dirty-science-today/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Dirty Science piece on Scope airs today at 4pm on Channel Ten. It will be available to watch later on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://ten.com.au/scope.htm&#34;&gt;Scope site&lt;/a&gt;. Edit: The video has screened and is available online &lt;a href=&#34;http://ten.com.au/video-player.htm?movideo_p=41452&amp;amp;movideo_m=172784&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Scope - dirty science</title>
      <link>/./2012/03/22/scope---dirty-science/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Mar 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/03/22/scope---dirty-science/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There’s a second piece that came out of Channel Ten’s visit to ILAQH a few months ago and it’s about to go to air. Two other PhD students at ILAQH are featured in a piece for the Scope episode “Dirty Science”. The show is aimed at a slightly older audience and the segment features me talking about dust storms, Leigh talking about (if I recall correctly) the instrumentation that we use to measure the physical and chemical properties of aerosols, and Lingli talking about particle deposition in the lung. The segment will air in the 4pm time slot on Thursday 29 March 2012.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
&lt;table style=&#34;width:auto;&#34;&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/C1EiCt2Xz33Iz0OPBoWXXnUco5i8_vaOdUQ4udrE348?feat=embedwebsite&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;DSC04556.JPG&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;font-family:arial,sans-serif;font-size:11px;text-align:right;&#34;&gt;
From &lt;a href=&#34;https://picasaweb.google.com/106543548808921798128/TotallyWildAndScope?authuser=0&amp;amp;authkey=Gv1sRgCIbS7ayFismlWg&amp;amp;feat=embedwebsite&#34;&gt;Totally Wild and Scope&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using R</title>
      <link>/./2012/03/12/using-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Mar 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/03/12/using-r/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am the only statistician in my aerosol science research group; everyone else is either a physicist, chemist, environmental scientist, engineer or some other physical scientist. Most of the people in the group do their data analysis and/or plotting in Excel or custom software like IGOR or Origin. One or two people in the group have used MATLAB in the past but there’s some sort of opportunity cost effect where it’s easier to use the Data Analysis plug-in in Excel than to load up MATLAB and remember how to fit a GLM or perform ANOVA. My background in computational mathematics and a bit of statistics means I’ve been exposed to other mathematics and statistics software and I’ve grown accustomed, through my stats research group, to seeing novel statistical methods and data analysis done in appropriate software packages (R, MATLAB, WinBUGS, and a Python package called &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ccdamc.org.au/files/beachbayes/ChrisStrickland.pdf&#34;&gt;pyMCMC&lt;/a&gt; that some of &lt;a href=&#34;http://eprints.qut.edu.au/43469/&#34;&gt;my colleagues&lt;/a&gt; are working on). As such, it saddens me to see my fellow PhD students doing their stats and plotting in Excel (which has certainly come in leaps and bounds but is still not a good piece of statistical software). I’ve really been pushing &lt;a href=&#34;http://cran.r-project.org/&#34;&gt;R&lt;/a&gt; as a way of doing better data analysis and making better looking graphs (which can easily be exported as PDF or EPS files) over the last year or so and have been heartened to see that a) it’s recognised as a good tool and b) some people are using the scripts I have written for them to do things like randomly sample from a list of strings. One of the other PhD students has found an R package that will make our lives much easier, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.openair-project.org/&#34;&gt;openair&lt;/a&gt;, and has even started investigating how to use R to do repeated calculations of summary statistics from SMPS data rather than writing the formula in a spreadsheet cell in Excel and choosing “fill down”. The risk here, of course, is that we will be asked to write all the statistics code for everyone else. In addition to this, one of the PhD students in the stats research group decided to run a short course in using R (with RStudio, which I’m now attempting to use instead of Notepad++ and NppToR) to manipulate data and do some simple plotting in ggplot2 and most of the (eight) students in my room went to the course. They all got various things out of going but all agreed that using R is the way to go. Some still find more advanced data analysis than t-tests, ANOVA and linear regression a bit daunting but will soldier on with the short courses that are being organised. There’s a bit of a feeling among the aerosol science PhD students that I should teach them data analysis in R, as I’m familiar with both what they’re working on (and thus have some idea of what they need to learn) and with them as people so I’ve got an idea of the sort of level of statistics and mathematics they’ve got. Now’s probably not the time for me to start teaching (PhD to finish) but it looks like I might be around for a little while so if I can help build the capacity of the group then I’d be more than happy to show everyone how to do their favourite data analysis in R and perhaps extend them a little further as scientists. While everyone brings their own strengths to the group in terms of skill sets and bodies of knowledge, I believe that every scientist should be able to do their own data analysis and that they should be able to do it in statistical software rather than something which has been developed for generating accounting reports and has later had scripting and statistical routines shoe-horned on to it (and while widely available isn’t free and “free”).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dust Storms - Totally Wild</title>
      <link>/./2012/02/23/dust-storms---totally-wild/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Feb 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/02/23/dust-storms---totally-wild/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Growing up as a child in the 1990s in Australia meant watching “&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Totally_Wild&#34;&gt;Totally Wild&lt;/a&gt;” after school. Totally Wild is a show about the natural environment in Australia and its many facets. Ranger Tim and Ranger Stacy (from the Queensland Parks and Wildlife Service) would talk about conservation, biodiversity, the urban environment and Australian ecosystems of a weekday afternoon. It wasn’t my favourite show and I would often channel surf in an attempt to find something better to watch (I think it was mainly the theme music that put me off the show) but every once in a while there’d be something quite fascinating on and I’d sit and watch it. Given that the only other environment-themed show on TV at the time appeared to be Captain Planet, it’s pretty neat that Channel Ten put some resources into making a show about Australia’s natural environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Late last year I was approached by my primary supervisor, Lidia Morawska, to be part of a piece on dust storms for Totally Wild that was going to be filmed in our lab. Yes. Of course. Not a moment of hesitation. I don’t consider myself an aerosol scientist but I couldn’t help get caught up in the excitement in September 2009 when a dust storm hit the East coast of Australia. Our group published &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1352231011004481&#34;&gt;a paper on the dust storm&lt;/a&gt; and this was the basis of the Totally Wild piece. The script went through a few revisions, attempting to balance “punchy” with “scientifically accurate” and it was a great way to spend a Friday afternoon, talking to an excitable TV crew about the work that we do at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ilaqh.qut.edu.au/&#34;&gt;ILAQH&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s a piece still to come on &lt;a href=&#34;http://ten.com.au/scope.htm&#34;&gt;Scope&lt;/a&gt; which will feature some speaking parts by Leigh Crilley (atmospheric chemistry) and Lingli Guo (lung deposition) who are shown in the Totally Wild Piece. The Scope piece will go deeper into the aerosol research that we do, not just the formation of dust storms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Totally Wild piece can be viewed at the following link: &lt;a href=&#34;http://ten.com.au/video-player.htm?movideo_p=41457&amp;amp;movideo_m=162536&#34;&gt;Totally Wild - S2, E37 part 2/3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dust Storms - Totally Wild</title>
      <link>/./2012/02/23/dust-storms---totally-wild/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Feb 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/02/23/dust-storms---totally-wild/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Growing up as a child in the 1990s in Australia meant watching “&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Totally_Wild&#34;&gt;Totally Wild&lt;/a&gt;” after school. Totally Wild is a show about the natural environment in Australia and its many facets. Ranger Tim and Ranger Stacy (from the Queensland Parks and Wildlife Service) would talk about conservation, biodiversity, the urban environment and Australian ecosystems of a weekday afternoon. It wasn’t my favourite show and I would often channel surf in an attempt to find something better to watch (I think it was mainly the theme music that put me off the show) but every once in a while there’d be something quite fascinating on and I’d sit and watch it. Given that the only other environment-themed show on TV at the time appeared to be Captain Planet, it’s pretty neat that Channel Ten put some resources into making a show about Australia’s natural environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Late last year I was approached by my primary supervisor, Lidia Morawska, to be part of a piece on dust storms for Totally Wild that was going to be filmed in our lab. Yes. Of course. Not a moment of hesitation. I don’t consider myself an aerosol scientist but I couldn’t help get caught up in the excitement in September 2009 when a dust storm hit the East coast of Australia. Our group published &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1352231011004481&#34;&gt;a paper on the dust storm&lt;/a&gt; and this was the basis of the Totally Wild piece. The script went through a few revisions, attempting to balance “punchy” with “scientifically accurate” and it was a great way to spend a Friday afternoon, talking to an excitable TV crew about the work that we do at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ilaqh.qut.edu.au/&#34;&gt;ILAQH&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s a piece still to come on &lt;a href=&#34;http://ten.com.au/scope.htm&#34;&gt;Scope&lt;/a&gt; which will feature some speaking parts by Leigh Crilley (atmospheric chemistry) and Lingli Guo (lung deposition) who are shown in the Totally Wild Piece. The Scope piece will go deeper into the aerosol research that we do, not just the formation of dust storms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Totally Wild piece can be viewed at the following link: &lt;a href=&#34;http://ten.com.au/video-player.htm?movideo_p=41457&amp;amp;movideo_m=162536&#34;&gt;Totally Wild - S2, E37 part 2/3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
