<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
      <title>Roger Peng on Sam Clifford </title>
    <link>/./tags/roger-peng/</link>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
    <updated>2013-09-11 00:00:00 &#43;0000 UTC</updated>
    
    <item>
      <title>Posterior Samples</title>
      <link>/./2013/09/11/posterior-samples/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Sep 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2013/09/11/posterior-samples/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Roger Peng and Jeff Leek are going to be &lt;a href=&#34;http://simplystatistics.org/2013/08/29/the-return-of-the-stat-computing-for-data-analysis-data-analysis-back-on-coursera/&#34;&gt;re-offering their Coursera courses&lt;/a&gt; on data analysis, including the use of R. A Creative Commons-licensed textbook on Bayesian statistics that teaches in Python rather than mathematics? Sure. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.greenteapress.com/thinkbayes/thinkbayes.pdf&#34;&gt;Have this one&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fCuZ5UUrKrM&#34;&gt;Let’s discuss gender bias in STEM fields&lt;/a&gt;. Australia has a new government and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.abc.net.au/science/articles/2013/09/10/3845442.htm&#34;&gt;that new government has flagged&lt;/a&gt; that it will be keeping a closer eye on the Australian Research Council’s grants process in order to “crack down on Labor’s (the former government) addition to waste by auditing increasingly ridiculous research grants”. The Liberal-National Party coalition government has a history of doing this; former Minister for Education, Brendan Nelson, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.themonthly.com.au/issue/2006/may/1294984634/gideon-haigh/nelson-touch&#34;&gt;personally vetoed grants for humanities projects&lt;/a&gt; that had been approved through the ARC’s independent peer review process.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Posterior samples - SEB113 edition</title>
      <link>/./2013/07/10/posterior-samples---seb113-edition/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2013/07/10/posterior-samples---seb113-edition/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I’m going to be frank, a lot of this relates to SEB113 - Quantitative Methods for Science, a subject I tutored last semester. One of the students from SEB113 last semester, Daniel Franks, is &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/dpfscience&#34;&gt;live-tweeting his Bachelor of Science degree&lt;/a&gt;. Daniel was in my workshop group last semester and I recognise some of the events he talks about in his timeline. It’s interesting to see his perspective not just on SEB113 but on the other three units that form the first semester of QUT’s new Bachelor of Science course. SEB113 is getting a small makeover for Semester 2. One of the things we’re considering is the use of ggplot2 instead of a combination of the base graphics package, heatmaps from dendrograms with colorbars from yet another package, etc. Lattice doesn’t have the nicest interface and it’s nigh on impossible to add elements afterwards (I hate you, levelplot). It’s possible to do &lt;a href=&#34;http://gettinggeneticsdone.blogspot.com.au/2010/01/ggplot2-tutorial-scatterplots-in-series.html&#34;&gt;small multiples in ggplot2&lt;/a&gt; fairly easily. We ought to be sticking to the same steps in data analysis as we did last semester, and Daniel’s tweets refer to an experience in class last semester where we discussed drawing the analysis method out of exploratory plots of the data, rather than trying to pick the “best” model &lt;em&gt;a priori&lt;/em&gt; and making the data fit the model. &lt;a href=&#34;http://simplystatistics.org/2013/06/27/what-is-the-best-way-to-analyze-data/&#34;&gt;Roger Peng’s got a good five step&lt;/a&gt; technique for analysing data:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Exploratory analysis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Model fitting&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Model building&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sensitivity analysis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reporting&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Via &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.quantumforest.com/2013/07/flotsam-13-early-july-links/&#34;&gt;Luis Apiolaza at Quantum Forest&lt;/a&gt; I’ve stumbled across &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.statschat.org.nz/&#34;&gt;Thomas Lumley&lt;/a&gt;’s Tumblr, where he’s doing some personal blogging about statistics. An &lt;a href=&#34;http://notstatschat.tumblr.com/post/54011641155/where-is-bayesian-introductory-statistics-better&#34;&gt;interesting post&lt;/a&gt; of his is on the role of Bayesian stats in introductory classes. I would love to turn SEB113 into a Bayesian statistics based class but for the time being I will have to settle for it dealing with modelling over tests (which is still a big win, pedagogically). Teaching Bayesian statistics generally relies on a good grounding in calculus, otherwise writing down full conditionals is going to be quite difficult. When people tell me that statistics is so different to mathematics I like to point out that it’s just a combination of calculus, linear algebra and some discrete mathematics. &lt;a href=&#34;http://magazine.amstat.org/blog/2013/07/01/calculus-and-statistics/&#34;&gt;Daniel Kaplan writes at &lt;strong&gt;AMSTAT&lt;/strong&gt;News&lt;/a&gt; about ditching mathematical formalism to make statistics more accessible. The American undergraduate model is very different to what we have in Australia, but I take his point about a first year calculus class not being as relevant to graduates as a first year statistics course that teaches statistical thinking over statistical calculation. I really like the focus in SEB113 on modelling using R rather than statistical tests by hand with pages of tables (as MAB101 was when I did my Bachelor of Science). If people finish SEB113 knowing how to read their data in to R and perform a Generalised Linear Model I think we’ll have done our job. If they want to go on to further statistics from there, the statistics units in the School of Mathematical Sciences work from a calculus perspective and while they require a calculus pre-requisite (MAB121 or MAB122 for those QUT students reading) you could do a lot worse than taking MAB210 and MAB314. I hope a follow-up data analysis course will be offered to Bachelor of Science students that builds on SEB113 and covers some more advanced topics and introduces enough mathematics to make those topics worthwhile. We’ll have to see how it all unfolds as this first cohort make their way through.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stop, collaborate and listen</title>
      <link>/./2013/06/27/stop-collaborate-and-listen/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Jun 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2013/06/27/stop-collaborate-and-listen/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://simplystatistics.org/2013/06/25/doing-statistical-research/&#34;&gt;Roger Peng posted at Simply Statistics&lt;/a&gt; about what it is to &lt;a href=&#34;http://stattrak.amstat.org/2013/06/01/how-to-do-statistical-research/&#34;&gt;do statistical research&lt;/a&gt; and how research is essentially solving problems that can’t be solved with the current methods. The message I took from Peng’s post is that often you can 90% solve a problem with current methods and that a lot of the time this is “good enough” and you can come back to the problem later with some new approaches that go beyond the current methods. As part of the UPTECH project I’ve been doing a lot of work with Bayesian hierarchical linear models. While our data has been collected from a panel design (25 schools, two weeks at each) it’s not always appropriate to use a full-blown spatial model. For example, the microbiological work I’ve been doing with my Finnish collaborator is mostly solvable by using exchangeable means priors to estimate classroom level and school level effects. Recently I’ve also had to start looking at clustering techniques, meta-analysis, spatial modelling of high-resolution data, estimating personal exposure, large surveys, and many other applied science problems that require a novel statistical approach. This sort of collaboration/consulting work, according to Terry Speed (whose post Peng is discussing), is a chance to meet lots of people and work on some interesting problems. For me, it has involved learning about existing techniques and trying to figure out how my collaborators and I can apply them to our data to do the best inference we can. With the UPTECH work, there’s always going to be a large list of authors due to the size of the project and the number of people involved in collecting data. Authorship will always be an issue with our papers, both in terms of inclusion and ordering, and we’ve got a decent process in place which makes people aware of papers as they’re finishing up (but not yet ready for submission). My personal belief is that one should always be able to point to a published paper and say “I did that”. Collaboration in applied physics and chemistry seems to be a very different beast to collaboration in statistics and mathematics. Many of the postgraduate students I know in Mathematics have tended to write methods papers with their supervisor(s) and that’s it. There’s the occasional collaboration to apply the method to a problem, but unless you’re working on cross-disciplinary modelling work or a large project involving numerical simulation there doesn’t appear to be much scope for multi-author work. Look back at some of the foundational statistical papers and you’ll see they’ve been written by a single author (some (non-parametric) Bayesian foundations spring to mind: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.numdam.org/item?id=AIHP_1937__7_1_1_0&#34;&gt;de Finetti, 1937&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&#34;http://projecteuclid.org/DPubS?service=UI&amp;amp;version=1.0&amp;amp;verb=Display&amp;amp;handle=euclid.pjm/1102992601&#34;&gt;Kingman, 1967&lt;/a&gt;; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://projecteuclid.org/DPubS?service=UI&amp;amp;version=1.0&amp;amp;verb=Display&amp;amp;handle=euclid.aos/1176342360&#34;&gt;Ferguson, 1973&lt;/a&gt;). The question of when to collaborate, with whom, and what it will add is part and parcel of modern science but there are some fields where collaboration is rare and keeping the author list short &lt;a href=&#34;http://andrewgelman.com/2013/06/25/is-there-too-much-coauthorship-in-economics-and-science-more-generally-or-too-little/&#34;&gt;can lead to problems&lt;/a&gt;. Statistical research is necessary when there’s a problem to be solved that is 0% solvable with the current methods. Some of what I’m doing is novel, within the context of aerosol science, but I haven’t done as much stats research in my postdoc as in my PhD. This is no doubt a result of my doing as much collaboration as I am. I get to work on a lot of problems but there’s not much original statistical work in these papers; if I’m lucky I get to do some of the “10%” research. It’s hard to do statistical research in a physics group, especially as the only statistician here. I think if we had a second statistician in the group there’d be a lot more statistics being done both in terms of collaboration/consultation with the scientists and the methods we use to solve problems. The “Airports of the Future” project has quite a number of statisticians working on, among other things, Bayesian Networks, and they’re extending the BN methodology as well as applying it to a novel problem. Two of the members of this team gave a talk at BRAG this morning about visualisation of BN results. This is something I’ll no doubt need to learn about sooner or later as we plan on using BNs with another project that ILAQH is putting together. Four and a half years ago I was under the impression I was joining a physics group to do computational fluid dynamics. Since then I have been learning statistics almost constantly. It’s opened up many more opportunities for collaboration than CFD would have. The trick for me now is to try and put myself in a position where I’m working with other statisticians on statistics. We’ve got some work coming up soon with a more senior statistician at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ihbi.qut.edu.au/&#34;&gt;IHBI&lt;/a&gt;, which I hope will bring with it some opportunities for more statistical methodology work. Unrelated PS: The &lt;a href=&#34;http://andrewgelman.com/2013/06/26/dont-buy-bayesian-data-analysis/&#34;&gt;3rd edition of Gelman’s Bayesian Data Analysis&lt;/a&gt; is being released soon, with contributions from David Dunson and Aki Vehtari.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
