<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
      <title>Conferences on Sam Clifford </title>
    <link>/./tags/conferences/</link>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
    <updated>2016-03-10 00:00:00 &#43;0000 UTC</updated>
    
    <item>
      <title>Diagnostics for first year students</title>
      <link>/./2016/03/10/diagnostics-for-first-year-students/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Mar 2016 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2016/03/10/diagnostics-for-first-year-students/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The SEB113 teaching team last semester (me, Ruth Luscombe, Iwona Czaplinski, Brett Fyfield) wrote a paper for the HERDSA conference about the relationship between student engagement and success. We collected data on the timing of students’ use of the adaptive release tool we developed, where students confirm that they’ve seen some preparatory material before being given access to the lecture, computer lab and workshop material. We built a regression model that looked at the relationship between the number of weeks of material students gave themselves access to and their end of semester marks (out of 100%), and it showed that students who engaged more obtained better marks, where engagement also included active use of the Facebook group and attendance at workshop classes. I had assumed that we’d be able to get data on students’ maths backgrounds coming in, but with so many ways to enter university, we don’t have the background info on every student. QUT has set Queensland Senior Maths B as the assumed knowledge for SEB113 (and indeed the broader ST01 Bachelor of Science degree) and I’m interested in knowing whether or not the level of maths of students coming in has a bearing on how well they do over the course of the unit. This semester, we decided that it’d be good to not just get a sense of the students’ educational backgrounds but to assess what their level of mathematical and statistical skills are. We designed a diagnostic to run in the first lecture that would canvas students on their educational background, their attitudes towards mathematics and statistics, and how well they could answer a set of questions that a student passing Senior Maths B would be able to complete. The questions were taken from the PhD thesis of Dr Therese Wilson and research published by Dr Helen MacGillivray (both at QUT), so I’m fairly confident we’re asking the right questions. One thing I really liked about Dr MacGillivray’s diagnostic tool, a multiple choice test designed for engineering students, is that each incorrect choice is wrong for a very specific reason, such as not getting the order of operations right, not recognising something as a difference of squares, etc. I’m about to get the scanned and processed results back from the library and it turns out that a number of students didn’t put their name or student number on the answer sheet. Some put their names down but didn’t fill in the circles, so the machine that scans the answer sheet won’t be able to determine who the student is and it’ll take some manual data entry probably on my part to ensure that we can get as many students as possible the results of their diagnostic. So while I’ll have a good sense of the class overall, and how we need to support them, it’ll be harder than it should be to ensure that the people who need the help are able to be targetted for such help. Next semester I’ll try to run the same sort of thing, perhaps with a few modifications. We’ll need to be very clear about entering student numbers and names so that we can get everyone their own results. It’d be good to write a paper that follows on from our HERDSA paper and includes more information about educational background. It might also be interesting to check the relationship between students’ strength in particular topics (e.g. calculus, probability) and their marks on the corresponding items of assessment. Getting it right next semester and running it again in Semester 1 2017 would be a very useful way of gauging whether students who are weak in particular topics struggle to do well on certain pieces of assessment.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Australia-China Centre turns 1</title>
      <link>/./2015/12/04/australia-china-centre-turns-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Dec 2015 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2015/12/04/australia-china-centre-turns-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Has it already been a year? This week the Australia-China Centre for Air Quality Science and Management had its second annual meeting, at QUT. We got updates on the various research activities that have happened, are happening and are planned. There’s lots of interesting stuff being done to tackle a variety of problems, such as reducing workplace exposure to air pollution, quantifying the exposure of individuals and using unmanned aerial vehicles to measure air quality. &lt;img src=&#34;img_1215.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;IMG_1215.jpg&#34; /&gt; Tuesday night we had the conference dinner out at the Mount Coot-tha Botanic Gardens, at the function space at the cafe/restaurant out there. I don’t think I’ve been there since my cousin’s wedding reception 15-20 years ago. I really liked that efforts were made to ensure each table had a mix of senior professors, mid- and early-career researchers and PhD students. It made for a very inclusive dinner and many different topics of conversation. Luckily I was sat with a co-worker with whom I could trade my fish entree and mains for something a little more land-based. There was even a birthday cake (chocolate mousse cake) and a number of people joined in singing “Happy Birthday” to the ACC. Wednesday we spent the day workshopping the various planned projects to determine what issues need to be addressed in the collection and analysis of data. I ended up sitting with a group looking at the impacts of indoor temperature on mortality rates, particularly trying to estimate the relative risk of extreme heat and cold. It was good to be confronted with some new challenges to think about, rather than the same stuff I’ve been working on almost non-stop this year. All in all, it was a good meeting even though the stress levels around here were through the roof in the lead-up. I ended up taking photos of nearly all of the presenters on the Tuesday as well as group photos with our Chinese collaborators and special invited guests.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>EMAC2013 semi-wrap</title>
      <link>/./2013/12/04/emac2013-semi-wrap/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Dec 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2013/12/04/emac2013-semi-wrap/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today’s the final day of EMAC2013, starting with Joe Monaghan’s talk on numerical methods for the dynamics of fluids that contain particles (in 20 minutes, so I’ll be brief). I attended yesterday’s “Education” session and saw some interesting things about how maths education is going around the country. The University of Tasmania is engaging with TasTAFE to deliver maths courses to engineering diploma students in order to prepare them for the mathematics they’ll encounter in their bachelor’s degrees. UTS is doing some interesting analysis of their maths course results to rejig the prerequisite pathways for their maths courses. A particularly interesting case was the use of a first year linear algebra course as a predictor of performance in a second year stochastic models subject that previously only had a first year probability course as its prerequisite. I chaired and presented in yesterday’s “Environment” session, presenting the mathematics behind the &lt;a href=&#34;http://pubs.acs.org/doi/abs/10.1021/es403721w&#34;&gt;personal sampling&lt;/a&gt; that we’ve been working on with the UPTECH project. I got quite a number of good questions and was overall quite happy with the talk I gave. The other talks in the session were about: using approximations to a sum of Pareto distributions, developed by actuaries, to determine whether extreme values in biomass luminescence were real or artifacts from the new sensors; and incorporating insolation into global climate models. Josef Barnes (Griffith) won the student prize (for, I assume, his talk on cardiac geometries), with honorable mentions for Kristen Harley and Lisa Mayo (QUT) and Laith Hermez. Bill Blyth, for whom the prize is named, pointed out the quality of the student talks at EMAC2013 is getting higher year after year. This can only be good news for the applied mathematics sector in Australia (and New Zealand) as these students will likely go on to academic positions and generate high quality research. David Lovell gave a great talk yesterday about multi-, inter-, trans- and ante-disciplinary research. I’m reading &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ploscompbiol.org/article/info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.0010006&#34;&gt;the article&lt;/a&gt; he referred to yesterday about the way disciplines will have to deal with each other and knowledge sharing over the coming years. And I’m off.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Posterior Samples</title>
      <link>/./2013/12/02/posterior-samples/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2013/12/02/posterior-samples/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Thiago Martins has posted &lt;a href=&#34;http://tgmstat.wordpress.com/2013/11/28/computing-and-visualizing-pca-in-r/&#34;&gt;a neat little tutorial&lt;/a&gt; about using R to calculate and visualise Principle Components Analysis, using Fisher’s Iris data. PCA is something I’ve struggled with as I’ve gone further into statistics, as it comes across as being based on mathematics rather than statistics. I’d like to learn more about the Indian Buffet Process and associated non-parametric Bayesian methods but if I’m going to be looking at long and wide data sets (say, UPTECH questionnaire data) I’d like to have somewhere to start. It looks like this may provide that. Rasmus Bååth’s done &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sumsar.net/blog/2013/11/easy-laplace-approximation/&#34;&gt;a tutorial on Laplace Approximations in R&lt;/a&gt; (hat tip to Matt Moores for this one). Laplace Approximations are an alternative to MCMC simulation that can provide good approximations to well-behaved posterior densities in a fraction of the time. The tutorial deals with the issue of reparameterisation for when you’ve got parameters which have bounded values (such as binomial proportions). As a piece of trivia, Thiago (above) is based at NTNU where &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.r-inla.org/&#34;&gt;R-INLA&lt;/a&gt; is developed. I’m at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://emac2013.com.au/&#34;&gt;emac2013&lt;/a&gt; conference this week. We’re about half way through day one of the talks (of three) and there’s already been some fascinating stuff. Professor Robert Mahony (ANU) gave a talk that shows that the development of more advanced unmanned aerial vehicles (UAVs, drones) involves some quite complex but elegant mathematics, involving Lie group symmetries, rather than just coming up with cooler robots. Hasitha Nayanajith Polwaththe Gallage (QUT) showed some really interesting particle method (mesh-free) modelling where forces and energies were used to determine the shape of a red blood cell that had just ejected its nucleus.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Some good news</title>
      <link>/./2013/11/29/some-good-news/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Nov 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2013/11/29/some-good-news/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://pubs.acs.org/doi/abs/10.1021/es403721w&#34;&gt;Our personal sampling paper got accepted for publication&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;line-height:1.714285714;font-size:1rem;&#34;&gt;quite quickly once we’d made the changes the reviewers required. This paper came from almost nothing about a year and a half ago to a really nice piece of mathematical and statistical modelling that will give us a lot to work with in future UPTECH papers, where we’ll be looking at the relationship between inhaled dose and child health. I’m presenting this work at the EMAC2013 conference next week (gotta write slides!) so it’s good to have the paper online now.&lt;/span&gt; My current post-doc is drawing to a close at the end of the year but I’ve got the contract in the email for my position for the next few years. After that, who knows? We got a grant under an international exchange program which means I may be off overseas for a few weeks/months during my next appointment. I’m looking forward to being able to spend some time outside the country at another university, having got a bit more experience now than when I went to Finland about two years in to my PhD. And it looks like I’m about to get my second PhD student to co-supervise.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Upcoming conferences</title>
      <link>/./2013/10/25/upcoming-conferences/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Oct 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2013/10/25/upcoming-conferences/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It’s more a note for myself here but I’ve got an abstract accepted for &lt;a href=&#34;http://emac2013.com.au/&#34;&gt;EMAC2013&lt;/a&gt;, discussing the modelling we did for personal sampling in the UPTECH project. &lt;a href=&#34;http://isba2014.eventos.cimat.mx/node/72&#34;&gt;ISBA 2014&lt;/a&gt; abstracts close December 1. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.asc-ims2014.com/&#34;&gt;ASC-IMS 2014&lt;/a&gt; abstracts close October 30. I need to get abstracts for these conferences together. I’ll probably talk about UPTECH at ASC-IMS as it’s a conference with an Australian focus. I think ISBA 2014 I’ll try and present the modelling associated with the &lt;a href=&#34;http://samclifford.info/2012/09/17/my-first-field-work/&#34; title=&#34;My first field work&#34;&gt;field work&lt;/a&gt; I did about a year ago (we’re still writing the analysis).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Becoming a grown up (at least a grown-up academic)</title>
      <link>/./2013/08/30/becoming-a-grown-up-at-least-a-grown-up-academic/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2013/08/30/becoming-a-grown-up-at-least-a-grown-up-academic/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There are only four months left in my current postdoctoral appointment and I’m discussing plans for next year with my supervisor. There’s still a lot of unfinished UPTECH work that needs to happen, including helping a handful of PhD students with the stats in their papers for their thesis, dealing with the clinical data and putting together some research plans for what to do next. The plan at the moment is to look for some funding both internally and externally to provide a research appointment. I’m also interested in continuing lecturing next year, whether in SEB113 or another mathematics/statistics unit. Most of ILAQH is away as of today or tomorrow, as they travel to Prague for the &lt;a href=&#34;http://eac2013.cz/&#34;&gt;2013 European Aerosol Conference&lt;/a&gt;. The work that I’ve been doing with some colleagues from ILAQH and Italy, on personal sampling, will be featured on a poster. The paper has been submitted to ES&amp;amp;T but hasn’t been accepted yet, so unfortunately I can’t put a preprint up to show off the cool statistics that I had to learn to do the modelling in the paper. As a result of everyone being away, I’ll be one of two academic staff members left here. It’s going to be quiet, with most of the staff and a few PhD students gone. Barring the Finnish paper that I’m still revising, this personal sampling paper has been the paper which has required the most creative and original programming as there have been many different steps along the way. I am particularly proud of this paper and the work that went into it. When I was first brought on board there didn’t appear to be much clarity regarding what we wanted to investigate; we had a lot of personal sampling data but didn’t quite know what to do with it. I think the paper we’ve developed does service to the amount of work that was put into collecting the data and is aligned with what the UPTECH project was set up to do. I’m grateful to all co-authors on the paper (and everyone who was out there in the schools) for the work that they put into bringing this to fruition. I’m still finishing the final corrections for my thesis, due in a few weeks time. After that’s handed in I’ll be taking another step in becoming a grown-up academic: supervising a PhD student. I’ll be the replacement associate supervisor for a student whose original associate supervisor has moved from QUT to another university. QUT requires an internal primary and associate supervisor and I’m the one most familiar with the modelling that this student is doing as part of their thesis. We’ve already set a meeting schedule for the time when his primary supervisor is overseas and have discussed what sort of things I’ll expect to see. It’s a strange responsibility to have for someone who’s only just finishing up their thesis. I wonder how long it will be until I’m the primary supervisor for a student. Two years? Five? Ten? Worrying about funding, writing grant applications, supervising students, lecturing (writing assessment!). It’s a strange place to find oneself.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Conference posters and an accepted paper</title>
      <link>/./2013/08/09/conference-posters-and-an-accepted-paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Aug 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2013/08/09/conference-posters-and-an-accepted-paper/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Thomas Lumley &lt;a href=&#34;http://notstatschat.tumblr.com/post/57747270796/speed-sessions-at-jsm-2013&#34;&gt;has some thoughts&lt;/a&gt; on poster sessions at JSM 2013. Healthy Buildings 2012 had something I hadn’t seen before - poster presenters were given two minutes at the end of the technical session most relevant to their poster to describe the work they are presenting in the poster session immediately after the talk slot. This gave poster presenters a small taste of presenting at a conference without them needing to prepare a full talk. QUT’s Nano and Molecular Sciences discipline had a poster session during its one day symposium a few months ago and the posters were run off &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thecube.qut.edu.au/&#34;&gt;The Cube&lt;/a&gt;, which allowed people to zoom and rotate a static image of their poster (PDF preferred). Our group will have a few posters at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://eac2013.cz/&#34;&gt;European Aerosol Conference&lt;/a&gt; in a few weeks. Mandana Mazaheri and I have been discussing the issues of transporting posters back and forth internationally, including whether or not to print on cloth and the unwieldy nature of poster tubes. I am a big fan of mailing your poster home once it’s presented but a cloth poster can be folded up and put in your luggage and you can just give it a quick iron before presenting it. I’ve also seen way too many posters that are too busy and have gradient backgrounds. Hopefully by teaching SEB113 students about the principles of good visualisation of data QUT can produce graduates who know not to make ugly posters. &lt;a href=&#34;http://pubs.acs.org/doi/abs/10.1021/es4023706&#34;&gt;Our endotoxin paper got accepted in Environmental Science &amp;amp; Technology&lt;/a&gt; after a frantic couple of days of finalising amendments and responses to reviewer comments. This paper gave me a much better understanding of Bayesian hierarchical linear models and I’m very happy with how the paper turned out. The next step is to resubmit our fungus paper, which includes similar modelling but also uses a Multinomial model with Dirichlet prior to look at the proportions of different fungal genera across the UPTECH schools. There’s yet another paper looking at chemicals in floor dust which we’re also finalising that uses a similar methodology to the fungus paper but has its own subtleties due to some chemicals not being present across all schools.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Posterior samples</title>
      <link>/./2013/08/02/posterior-samples/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Aug 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2013/08/02/posterior-samples/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://lindsaybradford.wordpress.com/2013/07/25/the-database-design-goggles-they-do-nothing/&#34;&gt;Database design is important&lt;/a&gt;, especially if someone else has to work with your database. It’s not really something we teach in undergraduate science, perhaps the American model of requiring a certain number of credits from certain fields would help remedy this. Ever wanted a glimpse of &lt;a href=&#34;http://xianblog.wordpress.com/2013/07/22/bayes-notebook/&#34;&gt;Bayes’ notebook&lt;/a&gt;? Laura McInerney’s comments on the benefits of &lt;a href=&#34;http://thesiswhisperer.com/2013/07/31/in-praise-of-the-small-conference/&#34;&gt;small conferences&lt;/a&gt; are similar to my experience with &lt;a href=&#34;http://bayesian.org/node/1657&#34;&gt;8 BNP&lt;/a&gt; in Veracruz, Mexico. As long as you’re within the niche field this sort of conference is a great experience. I felt a little like an outsider at 8 BNP because while I was interested in non-parametrics and was working on smoothing, a lot of people were working on things that I had no experience with which are actually the central elements of the field. I got to learn about a lot of neat things, hear some great talks and meet lots of amazing people, but I don’t think I was steeped in NP Bayes enough to really get the most out of the conference. My research went a bit away from NP Bayes these last few years so I didn’t get to put anything together for 9 BNP in Amsterdam. Perhaps ISBA 2014 in Cancún, Mexico will provide a bit more of a chance to get back to that work. We’re teaching R in SEB113. Perhaps any students reading this might be interested in these &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.computerworld.com/s/article/9239799/60_R_resources_to_improve_your_data_skills&#34;&gt;60 R resources&lt;/a&gt;. I use multiple monitors at work but really enjoyed the virtual monitors setup in Gnome when I ran Ubuntu. &lt;a href=&#34;http://lifehacker.com/5616859/is-the-multiple+monitor-productivity-boost-a-myth&#34;&gt;It turns out&lt;/a&gt; that having a large canvas of pixels, rather than multiple monitors, is the key to workplace productivity. My work setup has two widescreen monitors side by side in portrait orientation. This doesn’t work particularly well with programs that assume you’re using a single landscape monitor (such as RStudio) or give you a single window with multiple documents inside that each have focus one at a time (Microsoft Office, why can’t I have a spreadsheet on each monitor?) but it means I don’t have to keep switching back and forth between TeXStudio and RStudio when I’m writing up my analysis. &lt;a href=&#34;http://chronicle.com/article/Introduction-to-Ancient/140475/&#34;&gt;Flipped classes&lt;/a&gt; are an interesting model for education. I remember taking an Honours level mathematical modelling course a few years ago where the three hours of lecture time allocated us were used to discuss concepts and do modelling. We would read a chapter from the textbook in the lead-up to the class and then have a talk about what it meant and then work out a model based on a case study. I don’t know how well a truly flipped class would translate to a group bigger than about 30 students, but Sue Savage (QUT) tells me that the new lecture theatres in P block are designed to facilitate small group discussions within lectures. Daina Taimiņa explains &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=w1TBZhd-sN0&#34;&gt;hyperbolic geometry&lt;/a&gt; with crochet. Every once in a while something similar pops up and I can’t help but get excited. &lt;a href=&#34;http://longnow.org/essays/richard-feynman-connection-machine/&#34;&gt;Daniel Hills recalls his memories&lt;/a&gt; of working with Richard Feynman on developing a massive parallel computer in the 1980s.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Posterior samples</title>
      <link>/./2013/06/13/posterior-samples/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Jun 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2013/06/13/posterior-samples/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://themonkeycage.org/2013/05/29/how-to-make-an-academic-conference-and-more-accessible-and-more-interesting-live-streaming-and-conference-hashtags&#34;&gt;Josh Tucker at the Monkey Cage&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://simplystatistics.org/2013/06/11/why-not-have-a-future-of-the-field-session-at-a-conference-with-only-young-speakers/&#34;&gt;Jeff Leek at Simply Statistics&lt;/a&gt; have some good ideas and goals as to how to make academic conferences more interesting. Opening up the conference with live streaming is a cheap way to engage the wider public (but risks potential attendees deciding to stay home and watch rather than engaging with the rest of the conference). A youth session is also a really good way to engage in some inter-generational communication by giving the younger researchers a stage for setting out their vision. &lt;a href=&#34;http://f1000research.com/data-policies&#34;&gt;These journals&lt;/a&gt; wouldn’t view publication of data as prior publication when assessing an article based on that data. I spent last week in Sydney with Guy Marks’ group at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.woolcock.org.au/&#34;&gt;Woolcock Institute of Medical Research&lt;/a&gt;. I first met Marks at Bayesian data analysis course run by Kerrie Mengersen; he &lt;a href=&#34;http://sydney.edu.au/medicine/people/academics/profiles/guym.php&#34;&gt;does work&lt;/a&gt; on tuberculosis in Vietnam. Christian Robert, a collaborator of Mengersen’s, just gave 40 students in Ho Chi Minh City a crash course in Bayesian statistics. The slides are available &lt;a href=&#34;http://xianblog.wordpress.com/2013/06/05/teaching-bayesian-statistics-in-hochimin-city/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Speaking of Bayesian stats, the term “derp” is apparently a &lt;a href=&#34;http://au.businessinsider.com/sorry-haters-derp-isnt-going-away-2013-6&#34;&gt;Bayesian way of describing the way someone believes something so strongly&lt;/a&gt; (their prior) that they can not be swayed by data. I’m going to be doing a lot more work teaching people how to use R in the near future. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.computerworld.com/s/article/9239625/Beginner_s_guide_to_R_Introduction&#34;&gt;This looks like a handy resource for beginners&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New things in Science and Engineering at QUT</title>
      <link>/./2013/02/18/new-things-in-science-and-engineering-at-qut/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Feb 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2013/02/18/new-things-in-science-and-engineering-at-qut/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today was the first day of O week at QUT, a time when the relative calm of the summer break is disturbed by an influx of 17 year olds and university-run activities that always seem to generate a lot of noise. Is it possible to be a grumpy old man a week shy of 29? I received an email from my supervisor this morning asking if I could take over from one of the other PhD students in our group who had fallen ill last week and not recovered in time for a presentation this morning. The presentation, scheduled for 9am, was to be the first of the inaugural Nanotechnology and Molecular Science HDR (Higher Degree Research, i.e. Doctoral and Masters students) symposium. I’ve been moaning quietly, since starting my PhD in the School of Physical and Chemical Sciences, that the physics discipline had nothing like the School of Mathematics’ &lt;a href=&#34;http://samclifford.info/2012/09/07/qut-school-of-mathematics-postgrad-day-day-1/&#34; title=&#34;QUT School of Mathematics Postgrad Day - Day 1&#34;&gt;Postgrad Day&lt;/a&gt;. I really like Postgrad Day as it’s a good way to see what the other postgrad students are working on, what the research foci are within the school, and for students to improve their public speaking skills by delivering their research to a room of their peers and the other researchers in the school in an environment which is much more supportive than any conference is likely to be. The NMS HDR symposium brought together a number of students and staff from optics, aerosol science, nanomaterials, biotechnology, forensics and other fields within the discipline and allows them to see, perhaps for the first time, the research that others around them are doing. Even though my lab, ILAQH, is part of the Institute for Health and Biomedical Innovation, the distance between us and the remainder of IHBI is probably greater than just the physical distance between the two campuses. We do not seem to be particularly engaged with the culture of the remainder of IHBI and it’s very rare that our group will make the trek across to Kelvin Grove to see a presentation that is a short elevator ride away from the bulk of the IHBI membership. I have really only been to IHBI a few times. The two most recent appearances have been for the IHBI Olympics (a week of activities where research domains compete against each other in fun activities such as Iron Chef and photo scavenger hunt) in 2011 where I performed as part of the Health and Human Wellbeing domain’s talent quest entry, a four person improvisation troupe called “Ha ha… what?”, and to present the work that the PhD students of the UPTECH project had been working on (where we killed half an hour of time before the presentations by playing impro warm-up games). Continuing in this spirit of improvising in front of scientists, I spoke to the NMS HDR symposium at 45 minutes’ notice and in an eight minute talk managed to touch on the key points of the UPTECH project, explaining a small fraction of the science and discussing the richness of the dataset, the questions it will allow us to answer, and the diverse range of people we have involved in the project. I was told by one of the research staff in our group afterwards that it was refreshing to see a talk with no slides and that they were impressed at the quality of a talk that contained such a small amount of preparation and wondered whether I could give a presentation without speaking. Professor Dennis Arnold, the organiser of the symposium, is now based on the same floor as me; he is one of a handful of people on our floor who are not members of ILAQH. I asked him if he thought the day was a success and he was very positive. I sincerely hope that the NMS HDR symposium continues next year and well into the future, as a way to foster interest across the traditional divide of physics vs chemistry. I had to duck out of the symposium early to attend a meeting about one of the new units in the revamped Bachelor of Science degree. Dr Sama Low Choy, one of my supervisors, has asked me to run one of the collaborative workshops in the new &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.qut.edu.au/study/unit-search/unit?unitCode=SEB113&amp;amp;idunit=44499&#34;&gt;quantitative methods unit&lt;/a&gt; (she says it’s because of my impro skills). Today was one of the planning days where we got to grips with the structure of the unit, the way the workshops are to be run and how what we are doing is significantly different to anything we’ve done before. I’ll write more about it later, such as after my first tutorial, but it’s very exciting to see QUT break with tradition and make this unit happen. Through case studies with data sets relevant to their discipline, students will learn about quantitative methods in mathematics and statistics. We are ditching &lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt; tests, removing the need for statistical tables, adding structure to the group work to ensure people don’t get to ride on the effort of others and teaching R and MATLAB in a first year unit that only supposes Maths B. I’m really excited that we’re teaching first year students how to use software that is free (well, at least R is) and far more powerful than Microsoft Excel. One of the problems with MAB101, the old unit, was that the computation was done in Minitab, a piece of software that I’ve never known any researcher to use. One of the workshop leaders said that they want to go back and do undergrad again knowing that this unit now exists; I don’t blame them. This will definitely be an exciting year for me, academically. A new course with new units, new facilities in the Science and Engineering Centre, new collaboration opportunities and the chance to pick somewhere new to move to at the end of the year.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bayes on the Beach</title>
      <link>/./2012/11/08/bayes-on-the-beach/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Nov 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/11/08/bayes-on-the-beach/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve spent the last three days at the Bayes on the Beach conference/workshop in &lt;a href=&#34;https://maps.google.com.au/maps?q=caloundra&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;sll=-19.457034,145.879162&amp;amp;sspn=35.100111,39.506836&amp;amp;hnear=Caloundra+Queensland&amp;amp;t=m&amp;amp;z=14&amp;amp;iwloc=A&#34;&gt;Caloundra&lt;/a&gt;. The meeting is an annual event where Bayesian statisticians (usually Australians who know Kerrie Mengersen) get together for a very casual set of talks, workshops and other activities in a beachside town.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;design&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Design&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We arrived in Caloundra on Tuesday morning and got down to business with a keynote talk from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.southampton.ac.uk/maths/about/staff/davew.page&#34;&gt;Dave Woods&lt;/a&gt; (University of Southampton). Professor Woods’ talk opened a day in which the over-arching theme was experimental design and made the point that any design is at least implicitly Bayesian. I really agree with this point because any design is based on the prior experience of the experimenter or is pieced together from a review of what’s been done previously. I don’t know of any situation in which an experimental study was carried out totally at random without choosing appropriate covariate values. I don’t have much of a head for design but I think after seeing the talks on Tuesday (particularly Liz Ryan’s, which others in her session praised as giving a good review of utility) I’m a bit more aware of what it all means. What really helped was &lt;a href=&#34;http://pharmacy.otago.ac.nz/our-people/academic-staff/stephen-duffull&#34;&gt;Stephen Duffull&lt;/a&gt; (University of Otago) in his Thursday talk where he spelled out D-optimality (wanting to maximise the effect) and P-optimality (wanting to get the best estimate of parameters). D- and P-optimality work in opposite directions quite frequently (killing all your patients doesn’t tell you much about the parameters in your model, for example) but it’s possible to trade them off with a DP-optimal design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;workshops&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Workshops&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of my favourite aspects of the Bayes on the Beach meetings is the workshops. At my first Bayes on the Beach (2009) we were shown how to do a Bayesian meta-analysis to combine the results of a bunch of disparate studies that dealt with the same topic. Ever since then, I’ve been looking forward to learning some more statistics or getting to grips with interesting data. &lt;a href=&#34;http://datasearch2.uts.edu.au/science/staff/maths/details.cfm?StaffID=11641&#34;&gt;Matt Wand&lt;/a&gt; (University of Technology Sydney), &lt;a href=&#34;http://data.aims.gov.au/staffcv/jsf/external/view.xhtml?partyId=900000428&#34;&gt;Julian Caley&lt;/a&gt; (Australian Institute of Marine Science) and &lt;a href=&#34;http://staff.qut.edu.au/staff/lowchoy/&#34;&gt;Sama Low Choy&lt;/a&gt; (Queensland University of Technology, my associate supervisor) each pitched a problem that people could have a look at, not necessarily solving but, working towards a solution. Wand presented some really interesting spatio-temporal data of extreme rainfall in NSW which I was very keen to sign up to but Kerrie suggested that it might be a bit more of a challenge to do something other than spatio-temporal modelling of environmental data. Sama presented some work that she’s been doing on combining elicited opinions into a subjective prior that represents the aggregate knowledge of experts. I ended up in Caley’s group, where we worked on some data that &lt;a href=&#34;http://scholar.google.com/citations?user=T-nbIuUAAAAJ&amp;amp;hl=en&#34;&gt;Julie Vercelloni&lt;/a&gt; is dealing with as part of her PhD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;reef-workshop&#34; class=&#34;section level4&#34;&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Reef workshop&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Caley, Vercelloni and Mengersen (among others) are working on coral coverage in the Great Barrier Reef in six sectors that run up the length of the reef (2600km). Within each sector there are reef shelves and on each shelf there are multiple reefs with multiple measurement patches. The question we attempted to answer was “How different are the long term trends in coral coverage at these reefs?” Caley has data going back to about 1994, reported annually, which when pooled looked very boring but when plotted (very well by Vercelloni) grouped by reef shelf within sector indicated that there might be quite a lot of interesting variation which may not be so straight forward to model. Our group split up into a few subgroups with different approaches and I ended up working with James McKeone and a few others on a model inspired by &lt;a href=&#34;http://samclifford.info/2012/10/19/anova/&#34; title=&#34;ANOVA&#34;&gt;Cari Kaufmann’s functional ANOVA with GP priors&lt;/a&gt;. Over the next day or so McKeone took what we’d discussed and written down as a model and came up with quite a general Gibbs sampling scheme that is flexible enough to admit any linear predictor. I’m fairly certain James and I both had P-splines in mind but I did talk later to Matt Wand about O’Sullivan splines and I think it might be conceptually easier to use Wand’s low rank thin plate smoothers, particularly as Vercelloni’s quite new to Bayesian statistics and has a background in ecology rather than computational statistics. It was interesting to see how the other workshops went on the Thursday afternoon recap. Sama’s group had split into three groups, each tackling the issue of elicitation with a different topic and a different angle. I must say that my favourite was the group who did an elicitation of predictions of the outcome of the US Presidential Election. &lt;a href=&#34;http://conidialcoleopticide.wordpress.com/&#34;&gt;Luisa Hall&lt;/a&gt; even managed to elicit my opinion for her survey without me even realising it (we talk a lot about politics)! The other groups asked about how risky a life-saving operation would have to be for them to not take it and average completion time for PhD students (which Sama gave a talk about on Thursday).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;real-time-updates-for-mean-field-variational-bayes&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Real time updates for Mean Field Variational Bayes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matt Wand also gave a talk and tutorial about using Mean Field Variational Bayes (a name he attributes to Mike Jordan) to do live, real-time updates of posterior estimates with streamed data such as stock trading. Rather than going into the content of the talk, I suggest you read &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.uow.edu.au/~mwand/ovbpap.pdf&#34;&gt;the paper&lt;/a&gt; he’s written with Tamara Broderick (University of California, Berkeley) and his PhD student Jan Luts (University of Technology Sydney) and check out &lt;a href=&#34;http://realtime-semiparametric-regression.net/&#34;&gt;their website&lt;/a&gt; with neat examples, e.g. &lt;a href=&#34;http://realtime-semiparametric-regression.net/SydneyRealEstate/&#34;&gt;the Sydney rental market&lt;/a&gt; (which I think would be fascinating with the train lines superimposed).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;games-and-posters&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Games and Posters&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tuesday and Wednesday evenings had Luisa and I running some games (&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fictionary&#34;&gt;Dictionary&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://boardgamegeek.com/boardgame/38159/ultimate-werewolf-ultimate-edition&#34;&gt;Werewolf&lt;/a&gt;) before the poster sessions. It’s interesting running games like this with Bayesians because Dictionary is basically a problem of credibility of unknown experts and Werewolf is all about updating an initially uninformative prior with information based on peoples’ behaviour as they accuse others while trying to avoid being lynched. The poster sessions themselves were quite good, with a wide variety of applications and methodologies being presented. Everyone seemed quite keen to talk about their posters and they were generally of a high quality. On Thursday afternoon I gave my talk about spatio-temporal modelling of the UPTECH data as a case study for INLA. I got a few questions about the versatility of INLA and my choice of random walk and spline models instead of other bases as well as comments about the spatial modelling I’m doing. Definitely some things to think about for the next papers I write.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;a-success&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;A success&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The organisers of Bayes on the Beach (Nicole White, Matt Moores, Jannah Baker and Dow Jaemjamrat) all did a really good job and I think everyone had a good time but was also inspired. I had a few minor issues (timekeeping is a perpetual bugbear of mine and I’m yet to go to a conference that runs totally on schedule) but think that the meeting did a really good job of bringing together a disparate group of researchers and introducing them to each other and providing ideas for future work and employment opportunities (Kim-Anh Do did a really good job of selling the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mdanderson.org/&#34;&gt;MD Anderson Cancer Center&lt;/a&gt;). I think the challenge for future Bayes on the Beach meetings will be managing the growth in the number of attendees. I look forward to next year’s meeting; I might even have some time to go to the beach!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Summary of the last week&#39;s Christian Robert visit</title>
      <link>/./2012/08/24/summary-of-the-last-weeks-christian-robert-visit/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Aug 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/08/24/summary-of-the-last-weeks-christian-robert-visit/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I didn’t have any one on one meetings with Professor Robert but he did address two of my stats research group’s meetings and gave two seminars as part of his AMSI talk. In addition to this, there was a few hours one afternoon where QUT statisticians presented some of the Bayesian computation that is worked on here. Christian’s first talk to BRAG focused on model choice and comparison and &lt;a href=&#34;http://samclifford.info/2012/08/16/a-few-things-from-today/&#34;&gt;I wrote about it last week&lt;/a&gt;. The second talk to BRAG (&lt;a href=&#34;http://storify.com/samclifford/christian-robert-s-second-brag-talk&#34;&gt;Storify&lt;/a&gt;) was to finish off the themes on improving MCMC methods that he mentioned. We picked up where we left off, with a discussion of simulated tempering. The choice of &lt;em&gt;α&lt;/em&gt; is probably the key concept here, and Christian recommends choosing a scale based on the number of data points (if π&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt; is the original likelihood, try using π = π&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1/&lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; for &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; data points). Allowing &lt;em&gt;α&lt;/em&gt; to take multiple values (or even have a distribution) means that we now have a space of target posteriors. By moving around in this space of posteriors we are less likely to end up with sticky Markov chains because a sharply peaked posterior in one posterior will likely not be as sharply peaked in another posterior. Robert gave a reference to a paper by Radford Neal which deals with tempering [1]. Another way to ensure movement throughout the posterior space is to either subsample the data or to perturb the data with a small amount of noise. These will again change the posterior (ever so slightly) and help exploration of the space to find the modes. A change of variable is another way to flatten out the posterior. Parallel computation is another option; running the same model with different starting values and using the posterior density (a one dimensional value for each simulation) to get a sense of what the maximum value of the posterior might be. Low density models can be dropped in this way as they are not near the global mode of the posterior. I find this approach quite interesting and if I had a bit more time I’d try implementing it. Some exploration of low density modes is burn-in, but if the exploration is trapped at a local mode (and tempering, etc. aren’t getting it out of there) then perhaps it ought to be dropped. Robert then went on to talk about using auxiliary variables to create joint densities where we can move along level sets of the posterior to get large jumps in the parameter of interest. This is probably where I got lost, but I did manage to get that there’s a paper by Girolami and Calderhead [2] where this is formalised as Langevin and Hamiltonian Monte Carlo. Some of the members of BRAG will be presenting LMC/HMC at a future meeting and I look forward to it. It’s always interesting to find out that so much Bayesian computation started out as a branch of physics (the Metropolis(-Hastings) algorithm as a solution for the Ising/Potts model, for example). I’ve used Storify to publish my notes from the two AMSI sessions (&lt;a href=&#34;http://samclifford.info/2012/08/21/christian-roberts-talk-on-simulation/&#34; title=&#34;Christian Robert&amp;#39;s talk on simulation&#34;&gt;simulation&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://samclifford.info/2012/08/22/christian-roberts-talk-on-abc-for-model-choice-and-open-floor-on-bayesian-computation-2/&#34; title=&#34;Christian Robert&amp;#39;s talk on ABC for Model Choice and open floor on Bayesian computation&#34;&gt;ABC for model choice&lt;/a&gt;) that were part of Christian’s tour. I missed the one at UQ about Rao-Blackwellisation, unfortunately. Some of his slides from his talks are available online at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.slideshare.net/xianblog/presentations&#34;&gt;Slideshare&lt;/a&gt;. The open floor after the ABC talk was quite good as it gave me a chance to see what people are working on. While I have seen a few pyMCMC talks before there seems to be quite a lot of energy from Chris Strickland and Clair Alston for the development of new models in the pyMCMC framework. I’ve previously spoken with Chris about how to go about using it for spline models and spatial modelling and I hope that once I finish my PhD I’ve got some time to check out pyMCMC in greater depth. If you want to have a look, you can clone it from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://bitbucket.org/christophermarkstrickland/pymcmc/&#34;&gt;git repository on bitbucket&lt;/a&gt;. It was also interesting to see the work Ewan Cameron and Tony Pettitt have been doing on ABC for astronomical data (evolution of galaxies, etc.) and the work of Chris Drovandi, James McGree, Liz Ryan and others on using Sequential Monte Carlo with ABC for adaptive clinical study design. All in all a good week of seminars with lots of interesting ideas. &lt;a href=&#34;http://bayesian.org/forums/conferences/3606&#34;&gt;Bayes on the Beach 2012&lt;/a&gt; is &lt;a href=&#34;http://bragqut.wordpress.com/beachbayes2012/&#34;&gt;coming up&lt;/a&gt;. This is one of my favourite events of the year because it’s a chance to get away from uni with a bunch of statisticians and discuss some interesting problems and do little workshops. The beach is also quite a nice part of it and there’s usually some sort of games night (last year I contributed a game which is basically Chinese Whispers mixed with Pictionary and we all had a lot of fun trying to figure out what was going on). It’s also a really good chance for early PhD students to present a poster in a very friendly environment so they can get used to talking to others about their work. I’ve also managed to land myself on the list of presenters for the School of Mathematical Sciences’ “Postgrad Day”. While not a member of the school, two of my supervisors are and I’ve been working on statistical methods during my PhD. I will present the work I’ve been doing with my Finnish collaborators in a 20 minute slot. This will be a sort of practice run for my final seminar and is what I should have submitted to ISBA 2012 (but when abstracts closed we weren’t nearly ready enough). It’ll be good to have an audience of mathematicians and statisticians, because I always feel awkward explaining statistical research to aerosol scientists, chemists, physicists and microbiologists. Perhaps I need to focus a bit more on pitching a particular aspect of my work to the audience I’ve got. [1] [Neal, R. M., (1996) “Sampling from Multimodal Distributions using Tempered Transitions”, &lt;em&gt;Statistics and Computing&lt;/em&gt; 6, pp. 353-366](&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.springerlink.com/content/x6417mm4h7845735/&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;http://www.springerlink.com/content/x6417mm4h7845735/&lt;/a&gt;). [2] [Girolami, M., and Calderhead, B., (2011) “Riemann manifold Langevin and Hamiltonian Monte Carlo methods”, &lt;em&gt;Journal of the Royal Statistical Society - Series B&lt;/em&gt; 73(2), pp. 1-37.](&lt;a href=&#34;http://people.stat.sfu.ca/~cao/Research/GirolamiCalderhead.pdf&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;http://people.stat.sfu.ca/~cao/Research/GirolamiCalderhead.pdf&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Where to start if you&#39;re going to revise statistics</title>
      <link>/./2012/07/13/where-to-start-if-youre-going-to-revise-statistics/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Jul 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/07/13/where-to-start-if-youre-going-to-revise-statistics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I’d like to think it was my plenary speech that has spurred this, but given that they didn’t see it I’m not sure that it was, but one of the academics in my lab has decided it’s time to refresh their statistical knowledge. I think this is great, because they got their PhD a long time ago and have probably been using the same statistical methods for at least the last ten years. The book they’ve decided to use is the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Schaums-Outline-Statistics-Murray-Spiegel/dp/0070602816&#34;&gt;Schaum’s Outline of Statistics&lt;/a&gt;. I’ve used books from this range before to revise linear algebra, differential equations, etc. and have even taught small courses (privately) based on the topics they cover and in the order they cover them. A flick through the book confirmed that it was full of frequentist testing and other similar statistical methods that I spent my talk saying were a good start but not the end of the analysis when writing a scientific paper. The book’s online summary says it covers the use of MINITAB. I’m glad to see that it discusses the use of software other than Excel to perform analysis but I recommend people use books in Springer’s “&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.springer.com/series/6991?detailsPage=titles&#34;&gt;Use R!&lt;/a&gt;” range because R is free (in terms of both speech and beer) and is much more flexible than MINITAB in terms of programming it and running different types of analysis. Where MINITAB is based on a point and click GUI, making it great for a first year statistics class where students may not be familiar with programming, R is driven by the command line and is more easily scripted. Learning to use R means giving yourself the opportunity to use the many &lt;a href=&#34;http://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/available_packages_by_name.html&#34;&gt;packages&lt;/a&gt; that extend its functionality. The books I’ve used in the Use R! range include &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.springer.com/statistics/computational+statistics/book/978-0-387-93836-3&#34;&gt;A Beginner’s Guide to R&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.springer.com/statistics/statistical+theory+and+methods/book/978-0-387-92297-3&#34;&gt;Bayesian Computation with R&lt;/a&gt;. While I’d definitely recommend these Use R! books, as they’re aimed at people wanting to use R to do better analysis, there are a few others that I’ve found incredibly useful. It’s important for me to point out that my background differs from my colleague’s so they may not find the books as relevant or accessible. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stat.columbia.edu/~gelman/book/&#34;&gt;Gelman et. al - Bayesian Data Analysis&lt;/a&gt;. Around my stats group, this book is called “The Bible”. It’s probably the best textbook I’ve come across. It’s full of information, tutorials, detailed descriptions of the theory and methods and how they can be applied. This is certainly a graduate level statistics textbook, though, and it assumes calculus at what I’d say is probably a second year mathematics degree level. You may find this book difficult if you don’t feel comfortable with multiplying integrals together (which is really what Bayesian analysis is). I sent my colleague a link to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stat.columbia.edu/~gelman/research/published/AOS259.pdf&#34;&gt;Gelman’s Annals of Applied Statistics article on ANOVA&lt;/a&gt;. Might as well plug &lt;a href=&#34;http://andrewgelman.com/&#34;&gt;Gelman’s blog&lt;/a&gt; while I’m talking about him. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Biostatistics-Bayesian-Introduction-Probability-Statistics/dp/0471468428&#34;&gt;Woodworth - Biostatistics: a Bayesian introduction&lt;/a&gt;. I found this very useful in giving a more applied approach to introductory Bayesian statistics. There’s a good review of the book &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.theannals.com/content/39/7/1376.2.full&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and I agree with the reviewers about the importance of the preface in that it talks about the philosophy of statistics in science and discusses the differences between frequentist and Bayesian statistics. The book walks the reader through a lot of the topics which frequentist statistics deals with but in a Bayesian setting. I find this sort of comparison very useful (and appreciate when Mike Jordan says that a lot of machine learning techniques are just Bayesian statistics with a different name) as most people who have taken a statistics class will have seen linear modelling, ANOVA and a little about statistical design. The book also introduces the use of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.openbugs.info/w/&#34;&gt;WinBUGS&lt;/a&gt; as a tool for Bayesian modelling. As an aside, I attended an introductory course run by my supervisor, Kerrie Mengersen, where she was teaching us how to use R to write a Gibbs sampler for a very simple problem and how to do it in WinBUGS as well. One of the other attendees, the leader of a medical science research group, had it in their head that they would use Excel to write the Gibbs sampler because it provides nice reports (summary stats, plots, etc.) through a plugin they had. Comparing the time it took WinBUGS and R to run the code against the Excel’s run time was probably what convinced me that Excel was one of the worst pieces of software that one could use for statistics. Great for spreadsheets, awful for statistics. A non-technical book which does a good job extending the philosophical discussion to the history of Bayesian statistics and its use in solving some very complex problems is &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Theory-That-Would-Not-Die/dp/1452636850&#34;&gt;Sharon Bertsch McGrayne’s The Theory That Would Not Die&lt;/a&gt; (which I like to think of as the “A Brief History of Time” of Bayesian statistics). It’s very readable and really drives home the importance of Bayesian statistics and the profundity of Bayes and Laplace in developing this approach. I really don’t think there’s much use revising the basics of frequentism as I disagree with its interpretation of probability and find the idea of confidence intervals problematic. Hypothesis testing is also another problem that I have with frequentism and I think we’re going to see a lot of scientific papers in the near future converting the p values for their ANOVA into a “sigma” level as a result of CERN’s announcement of the 5 sigma certainty of their search for a new boson. Tony O’Hagan has &lt;a href=&#34;http://bayesian.org/forums/news/3648&#34;&gt;a good post&lt;/a&gt; about the “sigma” issue on the ISBA forums. Edited to add: TL;DR? Got a maths degree and some familiarity with stats? Read Gelman. Don’t have a maths degree? Read Woodworth. Want to understand what Bayesian stats is but don’t want to read a textbook? Read McGrayne. Want to know how to use R? Read a Use R! book. Once you’ve got a decent understanding of what statistics is, read papers for specific topics because there is almost never a book about what you want.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Plenary speech</title>
      <link>/./2012/07/12/plenary-speech/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jul 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/07/12/plenary-speech/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This morning I gave a speech as part of the plenary session “Standing on the shoulders of giants”. I was joined on stage by Mengyan Gong from Tsinghua University and Joana Madureira from the University of Porto and the three of us were to talk about our position as students within the field of air quality and how we see ourselves contributing. After the three of us gave our ten minute talks, Professor &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.linkedin.com/profile/view?id=21633181&#34;&gt;Charles Weschler&lt;/a&gt; gave a talk about what we currently know about biochemistry and microbiology &lt;em&gt;vis a vis&lt;/em&gt; the role of chemicals and microbes in indoor air and health. I think it was a great session and I’d like to thank Lidia Morawska for coming up with the idea and &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.bus.qut.edu.au/sefdean/&#34;&gt;Martin Betts&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ce.berkeley.edu/people/faculty/Nazaroff?destination=people%2Ffaculty%2FNazaroff&#34;&gt;William Nazaroff&lt;/a&gt; for chairing the session.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;hb-plenary.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Thursday morning speakers Professor Charles Weschler, Ms Joana Madureira, Mr Sam Clifford and Ms Gong Mengyan. Photo courtesy Professor William Nazaroff.&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Thursday morning speakers Professor Charles Weschler, Ms Joana Madureira, Mr Sam Clifford and Ms Gong Mengyan. Photo courtesy Professor William Nazaroff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spoke about the need for better statistics in science and how it was up to supervisors to encourage their students to look at novel approaches for data analysis and for students to be curious, creative and willing to learn in order to ensure that the field does not grow stagnant. I have &lt;a href=&#34;http://samcliffordinfo.files.wordpress.com/2012/07/hbplen.pdf&#34;&gt;uploaded the slides&lt;/a&gt; (which are quite spare) and a transcript of what I planned to say is available below (perhaps I should try to get this published in Indoor Air as a letter). I did vary from the script in a few parts and I will post the video online when it’s available. I will try to include links in the transcript to references so people can find out about these techniques that I get so excited about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“Quantitative questions, quality answers”&lt;/strong&gt; A talk for the “Standing on the shoulders of giants” session&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I, as a student, am to further the field of indoor air and built environmental health it will be by standing on the shoulders of giants. The scientists, engineers and others who have gone before me in this field have developed a rich body of ideas and questions that have gone unanswered as a result of there being other work that they must do. But as one moves up the academic ladder, writing grant applications and supervising postgraduate students the chance to investigate some of these questions in depth arises. A team of PhD students with a diverse skill set can be assembled to assist the other academics in the team and to help drive the research output of the group. This has happened with my group’s UPTECH project, which is the topic of a session later today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to Graham Farquhar of the Australian National University, Canberra, one of Australia’s most cited academics, the key to producing high quality science is to start with a really good hypothesis driven question that no one has answered and answer it. That seems fairly straight forward? In the case of UPTECH, the unanswered question is “What is the effect of exposure to airborne nano and ultrafine particles emitted from motor vehicles on the health of children in schools?”. Data collected in this project include two weeks of indoor and out aerosol and meteorology measurements at each of 25 primary schools. Indoor microbiology measurements are taken in one or two classrooms at each school and health diagnostic tests are performed on the students in these classes, accompanied by a take home survey which includes questions about family health history, demographics and housing characteristics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project generates a huge amount of data that has the potential to reveal some very interesting relationships. But to do so requires statistics beyond ANOVA and linear regression. The same can really be said of any modern scientific project. Don’t get me wrong, ANOVA is a great tool for exploratory data analysis [1] and testing whether a term in a regression model is zero or not. But to stop the analysis at descriptive statistics and testing for equal means across groups is to cheat yourself out of the opportunity to examine why these differences arise and really get to know what your data is telling you. ANOVA can be replaced with a Generalised Linear Model with factor terms. Any measured covariates can then be included in this GLM rather than just calculating the correlation between the covariate and the response. If the effect is suspected to be non-linear there are a range of regression models which are commonly used in the statistical and computer sciences but have not found their way into the natural sciences and I will talk about these soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The development of new statistical techniques and the ubiquity of computers in the workplace means that there is really no excuse for using statistical techniques that were developed for agricultural field trials are limited in their ability to explain variation in a data set. Expecting senior academics and industry practitioners to maintain statistical education throughout their careers is a bit of a tall ask in some cases. There’s so much work to be done keeping up with the science that the statistics often falls by the wayside. In my mind, the role of the supervisor is to present a problem and then direct the creativity and curiosity of the student. The role of the student is to answer the research question in a paper which weaves together the experience of the supervisor with high quality research and statistical modelling appropriate to the data and hypothesis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And there’s much more to data analysis than doing ANOVA. If you suspect that there might be homogenous groups within a set of observations, why not try a clustering algorithm like k-means [2] or a finite mixture model? [3] Don’t know how many groups there are? Try an infinite mixture model [4]. Think that certain covariates might have a different effect within those groups? A Dirichlet Process Mixture of GLMs is an option [5]. The Indian Buffet Process will help you identify common patterns across a bunch of correlated covariates and reduce the dimension of your data [6]. If you suspect the effect of humidity on particle number concentration is non-linear but aren’t sure about what it’s going to look like you could try a spline model [7,8]. For a smooth spatial relationship across a network of monitors you can use a Gaussian predictive process with a Matern class covariance function [9] or go all out and use a Gaussian process with non-parametric covariance [10]. Want to combine the effect sizes from some previous studies of the same thing to estimate an overall effect? Use Bayesian meta-analysis rather than a weighted average [11].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are all common approaches in the statistical community and I have seen them applied to scientific problems, many related to air quality or health. These techniques are much newer than ANOVA and their development in statistics and computer science means that professional scientists may not ever be exposed to them. So it’s up to students to be aware of new techniques which are applicable to their research. But is it too much to expect that all students are well versed in such a range of statistical techniques? Probably. Especially when you consider that a lot of these things aren’t taught in undergraduate science degrees. Science graduates are the obvious choice when recruiting science PhD students or industry practitioners. But science and engineering is strengthened by solid statistics. And the statistics are solid when a group’s capacity for statistics is solid, whether by employing one directly, choosing candidates with a strong statistical education, building links with a statistics research group at a university or providing for the ongoing statistical training of early career researchers and/or students. Our science must not just demonstrate that something is happening but attempt to understand why that effect occurs. We must quantify it and how and why it varies. Highly influential work, such as the work presented by our keynote speakers, arises when appropriate statistics raises high quality experimental science to where it belongs. The reader has before them a clear picture of what is happening and why. I see my role in my group, and through it, my role in our broad field, as fostering statistical creativity and curiosity. I am there to help provide tools which the people around me can use to solve these unanswered problems. Encouraging people to step outside the “ANOVA and linear regression in Excel” frame of mind has motivated them to ask questions about how best to fit some data which shows a non-linear effect, how to write code to process output from our instruments that will calculate summary statistics and generate plots, how to look at trends in time series data, and so on. In return, I’ve been given the opportunity to work on some really interesting air quality problems with some people who really know their science. So I pick up some more knowledge about aerosols and health, they get exposed to new ways of analysing data, and we get to present our interesting results to the world with robust and novel analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[1] Andrew Gelman. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stat.columbia.edu/~gelman/research/published/AOS259.pdf&#34;&gt;Analysis of variance - why it is more important than ever&lt;/a&gt;. Annals of Statistics, 33:1-53, 2005.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[2] Lloyd., S. P. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.nyu.edu/~roweis/csc2515-2006/readings/lloyd57.pdf&#34;&gt;Least squares quantization in PCM&lt;/a&gt;. IEEE Transactions on Information Theory 28 (2): 129-137, 1982.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[3] Darren Wraith, Clair Alston, Kerrie Mengersen, Tareq Hussein. &lt;a href=&#34;http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/env.1020/abstract&#34;&gt;Bayesian mixture model estimation of aerosol particle size distributions&lt;/a&gt;. Environmetrics 22 (1)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[4] Brian Kulis, Michael I. Jordan. &lt;a href=&#34;http://arxiv.org/abs/1111.0352&#34;&gt;Revisiting k-means: New Algorithms via Bayesian Nonparametrics&lt;/a&gt;. ICML 2012.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[5] Lauren A. Hannah, David M. Blei, Warren B. Powell. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.princeton.edu/~blei/papers/HannahBleiPowell2011.pdf&#34;&gt;Dirichlet Process Mixtures of Generalized Linear Models&lt;/a&gt;. Journal of Machine Learning Research 1: 1-33, 2011.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[6] Thomas L. Griffiths, Zoubin Ghahramani. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gatsby.ucl.ac.uk/~zoubin/papers/ibp-nips05.pdf&#34;&gt;Inﬁnite Latent Feature Models and the Indian Buffet Process&lt;/a&gt;. Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems 18, 2005.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[7] S. Clifford, S. Low Choy, T. Hussein, K. Mengersen, L. Morawska, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1352231011004766&#34;&gt;Using the Generalised Additive Model to model the particle number count of ultrafine particles&lt;/a&gt;, Atmospheric Environment 45 (32): 5934-5945, 2011.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[8] S. Clifford, B. Mølgaard, S. Low Choy, J. Corander, K. Hämeri, K. Mengersen, L. Morawska, Bayesian semi-parametric forecasting of particle number concentration: penalised splines and autoregressive errors, in prep, 2012. &lt;a href=&#34;http://arxiv.org/abs/1207.0558&#34;&gt;arXiv&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[9] Banerjee, S.; Gelfand, A. E.; Finley, A. &amp;amp; Sang, H. &lt;a href=&#34;http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/j.1467-9868.2008.00663.x/abstract&#34;&gt;Gaussian predictive process models for large spatial data sets&lt;/a&gt;. Journal of the Royal Statistical Society B 70: 825-848, 2008.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[10] Emily Fox and David Dunson. &lt;a href=&#34;http://arxiv.org/abs/1101.2017&#34;&gt;Bayesian Nonparametric Covariance Regression&lt;/a&gt;, 2011.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[11] Blangiardo, M.; Hansell, A. &amp;amp; Richardson, S. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1352231010008642&#34;&gt;A Bayesian model of time activity data to investigate health effect of air pollution in time series studies&lt;/a&gt;. Atmospheric Environment, 45: 379 - 386, 2011.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Healthy Buildings</title>
      <link>/./2012/07/09/healthy-buildings/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Jul 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/07/09/healthy-buildings/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am taking a break from the final session of the day to catch up on some thesis related emails. Figured I might as well write up what’s happened so far. The welcome reception at GoMA last night was quite good. Dr Bruce Flegg, Minister for Housing and Public Works, gave a good speech welcoming us all and stressing the importance of what we do. I was very impressed with how across the topic Flegg seemed to be. Dr Flegg has a background as a GP and is all too aware of the problems associated with unhealthy workplaces with things like mesothelioma and asbestosis. He has seen people who have developed health issues associated with accidental environmental exposure (so not people installing these materials like Bernie Banton). Flegg also spoke about the need to ensure that public housing stock, particularly in our indigenous communities, are of a high quality in terms of their energy efficiency but also in the way they promote health and are appropriate to the communities and regions in which they’re built. At the opening I also got to chat with Susan Savage, the Assistant Dean of Teaching and Learning in the new Science and Engineering Faculty at QUT. We discussed changes to the first year Bachelor of Science program that sound very promising. A common first semester will expose students to what science is and how it is done before students choose a major in their second semester. Mathematics will be embedded in each subject to make sure that our students continue to be exposed to it rather than doing a single Data Analysis unit and then thinking that they’ll never have to do statistics again. The opening plenary symposium, “Balance of Power”, was a discussion by two international speakers about the issue of a compromise between energy efficient buildings and healthy buildings. Professor Jiang Yi from Tsinghua University spoke about the issues of growing energy demand in the search for thermal comfort and presented some very interesting case studies where Chinese buildings have been built to maximise the availability of natural ventilation and light while still providing a very high quality of thermal comfort for the occupants. His message was that a combination of decentralised air conditioning systems that don’t work against each other can augment a default system of natural ventilation (with office windows which can be opened, for a start) to drastically cut our energy usage and ensure a ready supply of fresh air. The second speaker, Philippa Howden-Chapman discussed the problems faced in the New Zealand housing stock. New Zealand is a first world country but most of the public housing stock was built around World War II, prior to the first global oil shock, and is characterised by poor insulation and unflued gas heaters (often LPG). As a result, people in public housing are facing the choice of “heat or eat”. And even if they can manage to heat themselves, NO2 levels in the home tend to be three times higher than in homes without an LPG heater. Her group has done a lot of work to intervene in the worst affected homes and improve thermal comfort, health and energy efficiency. New Zealand has the lowest per capita energy use in the OECD despite being so damn cold. But heating an uninsulated house can be very expensive. The big finding is that if the government spends the money retrofitting homes they save a lot in terms of public pharmaceutical provision, hospital visits and lost productivity and education. An econometric analysis showed a 3.9:1 return on investment, with the investment in a house paying for itself if a single hospital visit in that house can be avoided. I spent the parallel sessions this morning doing AV support for two sessions. The venue has done a great job making it as easy as possible for presenters so the most I had to do was look for two missing speakers and walk people through how to use the pointer. The first session I attended was all about ventilation and there were some very interesting presentations about filtering incoming air and how being a bit clever about our behaviour in the home can lead to much better air quality. The second session focussed on regional solutions and included three talks about stoves in the developing world. A lot of poorer regions such as rural Kenya and Andean Peru rely on the use of solid fuels such as dung and the homes typically do not have very good ventilation. Some new stove designs were developed with community feedback in order to arrive at a design which was both energy efficient and didn’t depart from the cultural aesthetic of the typical oven design. Other considerations included the cost to the end user, provision of local jobs in assembling and maintaining the ovens and ensuring that the indoor air quality was improved beyond the energy efficiency gains. One of the more novel approaches for this was to use a thermoelectric device that could power an air blower with waste heat from the oven. This meant that particulate matter and incomplete combustion byproducts (CO mainly) were removed much quicker. Excess energy from these thermoelectric devices can be used to charge mobile phones (and something like 40% of homes in rural Kenya have mobile phones!). Some very inspiring work, showing that science can have a real impact in the developing world. I’ve also caught up with the two other students in my plenary session, Joana and Mengyan. The three of us will be meeting with our session chairs on Thursday morning (QUT SEF Dean Martin Betts and UC Berkeley Professor William Nazaroff) to discuss the session but today’s chat was a bit of getting to know each other and discussing what Brisbane’s like. Joana was very interested in what sort of Australian foods she could take back to Portugal for her friends. Vegemite, Tim Tams and Iced Vovos. The conference is going well overall. The QUT Events team and the Brisbane Convention and Exhibition Centre staff have done an amazing job making sure everything’s as clear as possible. It’s a great venue (the new wing of the BCEC) and the conference is bringing together people from 40 countries, be they academics, students, consultants, industry practitioners or vendors. There are 160ish students in attendance (many of whom I’ll meet tomorrow night at the student event) and I’ve heard that something like three quarters of attendees are from overseas. I’m looking forward to the next few days.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Two papers submitted</title>
      <link>/./2012/07/06/two-papers-submitted/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jul 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/07/06/two-papers-submitted/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the last two weeks I’ve sent two papers to Annals of Applied Statistics and uploaded them to the arXiv. This fulfills the minimum publication requirements for a PhD by publication at QUT. So it’s a milestone on the way to completion. Now I just have to sort out a fourth paper as backup, give two presentations at next week’s conference, organise a final seminar session, compile all my work into a thesis and get it to my supervisors. On top of my immediate thesis work on spatio-temporal modelling, I’ve got a paper for Healthy Buildings on methods for analysing the UPTECH survey data that’ll get published, a paper on which I’m coauthor (particle losses in a thermodenuder system) that’s almost finished and the microbiology paper I wrote about previously. Busy.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A few things that warrant an update</title>
      <link>/./2012/07/04/a-few-things-that-warrant-an-update/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jul 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/07/04/a-few-things-that-warrant-an-update/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Finnish paper is pretty much ready for submission to Annals of Applied Stats. I’ve updated my publications page to include a link to the preprint on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://arxiv.org/abs/1207.0558&#34;&gt;arXiv&lt;/a&gt;. I will update my CV soon and I’ll add my posters and slides to the publications page. The Higgs boson - what’s the deal with that? &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.northcountrypublicradio.org/news/npr/156221787/cern-discovers-a-new-particle-likely-the-higgs-boson&#34;&gt;NPR has a good article on it&lt;/a&gt;. I spent the evening watching the Higgs announcements at uni and even though I thought the CERN slides were pretty cluttered and didn’t like the layout, nothing had prepared me for the ATLAS slides. Bad colour schemes (if you can call them that) and Comic Sans MS? Yuk. You don’t make science accessible by making people think “Hey. That looks like &lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt; could have designed that. Scientists aren’t so different to me after all!” Some clearly presented slides that weren’t stuffed full of text and images are, in my opinion, the key to a good scientific presentation. 1 slide per minute, no more than 5-6 lines with no more than 5-6 words per line. The slides should touch on the key points so people can, at a glance, get a good idea of what’s going on. The talk that accompanies the slides is what conveys the rest of the information in more natural language. There was a lot of great science presented tonight, but it wasn’t presented well. David Spiegelhalter &lt;a href=&#34;http://understandinguncertainty.org/higgs-it-one-sided-or-two-sided&#34;&gt;explains&lt;/a&gt; the five sigma significance of the ATLAS/CERN results. P-values and confidence intervals are two things where I think frequentist probability stops being conceptually simpler than Bayesian statistics and becomes about questions like “What is the probability of observing the data I have seen given that I have this model and these parameter estimates?” and “If I did an infinite number of trials how many times would I expect this interval for my sample mean to cover the true mean?” and “Something something agriculture”. &lt;a href=&#34;http://hb2012.org/&#34;&gt;Healthy Buildings&lt;/a&gt; is coming up next week. It’s all hands on deck at ILAQH while we put the finishing touches on the program and sort out the behind the scenes stuff. It’s going to be great. I’ll be giving two talks; the first is about how we can use the Dirichlet process for clustering in health survey data and the second is about the need for better statistics in science. ISBA 2012 was a heap of fun and there were lots of good talks. I find meeting other statisticians very inspiring. I will try to write a wrap-up when HB 2012 is over. For now, you can enjoy &lt;a href=&#34;http://xianblog.wordpress.com/2012/06/27/isba-2012-guest-post/&#34;&gt;my preliminary thoughts&lt;/a&gt; on Xian’s ’Og.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A few observations on Kyoto so far</title>
      <link>/./2012/06/25/a-few-observations-on-kyoto-so-far/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jun 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/06/25/a-few-observations-on-kyoto-so-far/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve been here roughly 24 hours and thought I might jot down a few things I’ve noticed about Kyoto, at least the parts I’ve been to. It’s a very human scale city. A lot of the photos I’ve seen of Tokyo made me think that urban Japan is this sprawling metropolis of high rise buildings, neon lights, etc. Kyoto is not like that at all. Most of the buildings I’ve seen in the downtown area are perhaps four stories tall. You can see the mountains by looking down the street. There are not multiple lane highways running through the CBD, most streets near the central JR station are one lane in each direction, maybe two at the intersection. A few of the bigger streets may be three or four lanes in each direction but they aren’t clogged full of traffic and nor are they speedways. Contrast this to Brisbane where almost every street downtown is a four lane one way street with on-street parking on each side except in peak hour where all four lanes are on street parking because traffic slows to about 10km/hr. There is a huge bike culture. It seems to be the easiest way to get around when making short trips. No one locks their bikes up. You just pop up the kick stand and go into the store for a few minutes. There are bike lanes at intersections for crossing and people ride on the road and the footpaths, and down the arcades in some places. There appear to be no helmet laws. Bins are as rare as hen’s teeth yet the city doesn’t have a litter problem. Every vending machine has recycling bins next to it and people eat their food at the shops where they buy it, even if it’s a pokey little hole in the wall takeaway dumpling place in an arcade. People don’t walk around eating and drinking like they do in Australia. You sit down, eat your takeaway meal, dump the rubbish in the bin and then off you go. I must have spent ten minutes walking around with an empty takoyaki tray before deciding to walk into a Starbucks, dump by garbage, buy an iced tea, drink it quickly, dump the rubbish and leave. The markets are wonderful. I spent the late morning walking around downtown with two other QUT ISBA attendees. We went to a few arcades where almost every shop seemed to be selling fresh fish, fermented vegetables, tofu, fried takeaway, dried beans, etc. The smells! Like nothing you get in Brisbane markets (I’m thinking Brisbane Square). We stopped for some takoyaki (octopus croquettes, basically) and I got a tempura lotus root on a stick. Not my usual fare but it’s not the sort of thing you see all that often in Brisbane so I decided I’d have a go. I couldn’t bring myself to eat the boiled baby octopus on a skewer, though; too Lovecraftian. All in all, Kyoto appears to be a great little town with a fantastic public transport system, good food, friendly people all at a scale that’s not completely overwhelming. I would consider living here if there was a good postdoc position. I’d have to learn much more Japanese than “Arigato” and “Ohaio gozaimasu”.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Wald is not enough</title>
      <link>/./2012/06/25/the-wald-is-not-enough/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jun 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/06/25/the-wald-is-not-enough/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I’m working on a talk I’m presenting at Healthy Buildings 2012 while I do some travel to ISBA. My supervisor, who is president of the Healthy Buildings conference this year, saw &lt;a href=&#34;http://samclifford.info/2012/06/01/statistics-not-just-for-statisticians/&#34;&gt;a blog post of mine&lt;/a&gt; and thought that it would make a good presentation for the student plenary session. The basic point of the talk is that the quality of scientific research is greatly improved by ensuring that appropriate statistical analysis is performed and presented clearly. There have been so many papers and presentations I’ve seen where the authors just stop at descriptive statistics of their data and draw inferences just from describing the data. If we’re lucky they’ll do a t-test or ANOVA. If we’re not, they’ll just calculate summary statistics and perhaps a correlation between the response and the covariates rather than doing any statistical modelling. The problem isn’t restricted to indoor air quality and climate, the focus of this conference, though. &lt;a href=&#34;http://conidialcoleopticide.wordpress.com/&#34;&gt;A friend of mine&lt;/a&gt; has come across the same issue in her literature review for using microbes to control insect pests. There are some groups doing some amazing scientific work with robust statistics, such as Hugh Possingham’s group at UQ who look at applying econometric principles to conservation (think triage for species rather than patients). At the risk of spoiling the ending of my talk, being “the statistician” in my group has given me the opportunity to work on some interesting aerosol science problems such as particle loss in instrumentation, the multi-modality of SMPS data and how it affects automatic processing, microbiology populations in classrooms, the fate of non-background ions and determining exposure measures from personal samplers and monitoring equipment that have different time steps. In turn, I have introduced the researchers I’m working with to new statistical techniques (often with R code) which they can adapt and use in future work. Every group needs a statistician in it, but not just to be handed the data to analyse and used as a black box where data goes in and analysis comes out. For starters, the statistician needs to know what the data actually describe. But the statistician should be there to build the skill set of the group. We can’t expect that every scientist has PhD level statistical skills but the scientist needs to be comfortable going beyond ANOVA to investigate what’s happening in their experimental or observational data. P.S. the title for this talk was inspired by a brief conversation with my ISBA room-mate about how great statistics-based puns are.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Just a few quick thoughts</title>
      <link>/./2012/06/19/just-a-few-quick-thoughts/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Jun 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/06/19/just-a-few-quick-thoughts/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I’m setting up a laptop to take to ISBA with me as I have lots of thesis work to do. I must say, I’m really impressed with GitHub for Windows in regards to how simple it is to set up. It’s a matter of installing the program itself, then entering your github details. Cloning your GitHub repositories to your local machine is as simple as pressing a button. I haven’t had to faff about with ssh, pageant, etc. Now I just have to finish setting up remote INLA (which will require faffing about with ssh), installing LaTeX and figuring out if I can use X forwarding without X-Win. I also have to finish my ISBA poster and organise for it to be printed. Then there’s the two talks I am giving at Healthy Buildings 2012 which need writing and the Student Program work. I leave for Japan on Sunday. I should probably look at train travel from Osaka to Kyoto, find my travel money card, passport, etc. I uploaded a paper to arXiv yesterday. I’ll post about it here when it appears.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Christian Robert coming to Australia</title>
      <link>/./2012/03/20/christian-robert-coming-to-australia/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Mar 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/03/20/christian-robert-coming-to-australia/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One statistician whose blog I follow, Christian Robert (silent &lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt;), is &lt;a href=&#34;http://xianblog.wordpress.com/2012/03/20/amsi-lecturer/&#34;&gt;coming to Australia&lt;/a&gt; later in the year. Far from being just a blogging statistician, Robert is Professor of Statistics at the University of Paris Dauphine and does a lot of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ceremade.dauphine.fr/~xian/research.html&#34;&gt;interesting research&lt;/a&gt; in a variety of fields related to statistical modelling, statistical theory and computation. Some of Robert’s most recent work includes Approximate Bayesian Computation, on which some of Tony Pettitt’s students and post-docs at QUT (where Robert is an Adjunct Professor, and I wonder how long he’ll stick around here) are working. Robert will be speaking at the Australian Statistics Conference and then doing a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amsi.org.au/research-a-higher-education/rhenews/828-prof-christian-robert-lecture-tour&#34;&gt;speaking tour&lt;/a&gt; for the Australian Mathematical Sciences Institute. I’ll be going along when he’s in Brisbane but will miss him at ASC2012. Robert will be speaking on the Monday prior to the main ISBA 2012 conference and will cover advances and questions in ABC, so I still might get the chance to see him and talk to him before his speaking tour.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ISBA 2012 update</title>
      <link>/./2012/03/13/isba-2012-update/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Mar 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/03/13/isba-2012-update/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I got a very exciting email this morning as I was getting my morning coffee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dear Sam Clifford, We are very pleased to inform you that you have been selected as a recipient of a Junior Travel Award for attending the ISBA 2012 World Meeting! The amount of the Award is $300 (in US dollars) and is provided by funds from the Japanese Ministry of Education, Science, Sports, Culture and Technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;US$300 will pay for most of the conference registration if I register early as a PhD student. I’m drafting a budget now to check how much I’ll have to pay for accommodation, flights, etc. and will check how much money’s left in my IHBI student allocation and check if the new Science and Engineering Faculty will chip in a bit to help send me overseas. This is really thrilling news. I will get a chance to present my statistics work to statisticians, catch up with some of the people I met at the 8th Bayesian Nonparametrics workshop, meet some more early career statisticians, and find some academics working on similar projects who might be looking for postdocs in a year and a bit. My abstract is available &lt;a href=&#34;http://bayesian.org/node/2915&#34;&gt;online&lt;/a&gt; if you’re interested in Bayesian spatio-temporal modelling of data from a split panel design. I’ve got an old friend in Osaka who I should really catch up with. Osaka’s the nearest international airport to Kyoto and it’s an hour on the train. There’s a weekend before the conference starts, so I can probably afford to organise to see him and his wife prior to the conference.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Non-parametrics reading group</title>
      <link>/./2012/03/01/non-parametrics-reading-group/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Mar 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/03/01/non-parametrics-reading-group/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;At the &lt;a href=&#34;http://bnpworkshop.org/&#34;&gt;8th Bayesian Non-parametrics workshop&lt;/a&gt; in Veracruz, Mexico, last year I met a very enthusiastic grad student from UC Berkeley, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stat.berkeley.edu/~tab/&#34;&gt;Tamara Broderick&lt;/a&gt;. I spent a lot of time hanging out with Tamara and a bunch of the other PhD students attending the conference and I got to know about the reading group that she’d set up within the UC Berkeley Statistics Graduate Student Association (of which she is co-president). Tam’s reading group, “Classics of NP Bayes”, are working their way through a lot of the foundational papers of Bayesian non-parametric statistics, the papers that are always cited but seldom read. Inspired by this and hungry for more knowledge about NP Bayes (my only real experience at the time being semi-parametric regression with splines) I asked around the Bayesian stats group at QUT if anyone was interested in setting up a similar group here. In August 2011 the QUT NP Bayes reading group held its first meeting to decide a structure, meeting frequency, and discuss what kind of papers we wanted to read. Six or seven months later we have made our way through a number of papers, theoretical and applied, and learned quite a lot along the way. This morning I will be giving a presentation to the Bayesian stats group about our progress and writing the slides has really made me realise just how far we’ve all come together. Our little group consists mostly of PhD students, with backgrounds as varied as applied stats, computational maths, econometrics, environmental statistics, computer science, and we now have an electrical engineer from outside the School of Mathematics joining us to get more of a background in the techniques he’s using (Latent Dirichlet Allocation and Hierarchical Dirichlet Processes). We’ve covered measure theory, the Poisson process (as a completely random measure), the Dirichlet process, infinite mixture models and density estimation, the Polya urn formulation of the DP, MCMC methods for DP models, the Gaussian process and its relationship with GMRFs, non-parametric covariance regression and will spend our next few meetings on the Chinese Restaurant and Indian Buffet processes. I’m really glad with the way things have turned out, and if you’re interested in reading more about the topics we’ve covered you can check out the &lt;a href=&#34;http://samcliffordinfo.files.wordpress.com/2012/03/npbayes.pdf&#34;&gt;NP Bayes review slides&lt;/a&gt; or our &lt;a href=&#34;https://wiki.qut.edu.au/display/npbayes/Home&#34;&gt;wiki&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ISBA 2012</title>
      <link>/./2012/02/29/isba-2012/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Feb 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/02/29/isba-2012/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve just submitted a poster abstract and travel support grant application for the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www2.e.u-tokyo.ac.jp/~isba2012/&#34;&gt;ISBA 2012&lt;/a&gt; World Meeting, “Bayesian spatio-temporal modelling of ultrafine particle number concentration from a panel design” and is a nice overview of the modelling involved in the UPTECH project that we’re running at ILAQH. It’s based on the second paper that will comprise my PhD (still in prep but coming along well) and discusses quantifying temporal trends at multiple sites. I’ve had a few breakthroughs with the code recently and wish that I had’ve had them towards the end of last year so I could submit an abstract for a paper. The travel support grant for ISBA required an extended abstract and I think it’d make a good presented paper but contributed session proposals closed a &lt;em&gt;long&lt;/em&gt; time ago. I’d love to go to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sapmea.asn.au/conventions/asc2012/index.html&#34;&gt;ASC 2012&lt;/a&gt; and present this stuff there but &lt;a href=&#34;http://hb2012.org/&#34;&gt;Healthy Buildings&lt;/a&gt; is on the same week (and I’m on the Student Program Committee).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
