<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
      <title>Cube on Sam Clifford </title>
    <link>/./tags/cube/</link>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
    <updated>2013-08-09 00:00:00 &#43;0000 UTC</updated>
    
    <item>
      <title>Conference posters and an accepted paper</title>
      <link>/./2013/08/09/conference-posters-and-an-accepted-paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Aug 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2013/08/09/conference-posters-and-an-accepted-paper/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Thomas Lumley &lt;a href=&#34;http://notstatschat.tumblr.com/post/57747270796/speed-sessions-at-jsm-2013&#34;&gt;has some thoughts&lt;/a&gt; on poster sessions at JSM 2013. Healthy Buildings 2012 had something I hadn’t seen before - poster presenters were given two minutes at the end of the technical session most relevant to their poster to describe the work they are presenting in the poster session immediately after the talk slot. This gave poster presenters a small taste of presenting at a conference without them needing to prepare a full talk. QUT’s Nano and Molecular Sciences discipline had a poster session during its one day symposium a few months ago and the posters were run off &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thecube.qut.edu.au/&#34;&gt;The Cube&lt;/a&gt;, which allowed people to zoom and rotate a static image of their poster (PDF preferred). Our group will have a few posters at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://eac2013.cz/&#34;&gt;European Aerosol Conference&lt;/a&gt; in a few weeks. Mandana Mazaheri and I have been discussing the issues of transporting posters back and forth internationally, including whether or not to print on cloth and the unwieldy nature of poster tubes. I am a big fan of mailing your poster home once it’s presented but a cloth poster can be folded up and put in your luggage and you can just give it a quick iron before presenting it. I’ve also seen way too many posters that are too busy and have gradient backgrounds. Hopefully by teaching SEB113 students about the principles of good visualisation of data QUT can produce graduates who know not to make ugly posters. &lt;a href=&#34;http://pubs.acs.org/doi/abs/10.1021/es4023706&#34;&gt;Our endotoxin paper got accepted in Environmental Science &amp;amp; Technology&lt;/a&gt; after a frantic couple of days of finalising amendments and responses to reviewer comments. This paper gave me a much better understanding of Bayesian hierarchical linear models and I’m very happy with how the paper turned out. The next step is to resubmit our fungus paper, which includes similar modelling but also uses a Multinomial model with Dirichlet prior to look at the proportions of different fungal genera across the UPTECH schools. There’s yet another paper looking at chemicals in floor dust which we’re also finalising that uses a similar methodology to the fungus paper but has its own subtleties due to some chemicals not being present across all schools.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>BRAG for 2013</title>
      <link>/./2013/02/07/brag-for-2013/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Feb 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2013/02/07/brag-for-2013/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The fornightly meetings for my stats group, BRAG, started up again two weeks ago and I’ve put my hand up to chair the meetings. I totally flubbed it this morning by forgetting we’d switched the start times to 10.30 instead of 11. Today’s meeting was less of a formal meeting and more of an exploration of QUT“s”&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thecube.qut.edu.au/&#34;&gt;The Cube&lt;/a&gt;“, a new resource provided in the Science and Engineering Faculty’s new building. [caption id=“attachment_781” align=“aligncenter” width=“300”][&lt;img src=&#34;cubit1.jpg?w=300&#34; alt=&#34;CubIT, a unique system at the Cube that allows the general public to collaborate with and access research content shared by QUT’s students and academics. Photo copyright QUT.&#34; /&gt;](&lt;a href=&#34;http://samcliffordinfo.files.wordpress.com/2013/02/cubit1.jpg&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;http://samcliffordinfo.files.wordpress.com/2013/02/cubit1.jpg&lt;/a&gt;) CubIT, a unique system at the Cube that allows the general public to collaborate with and access research content shared by QUT’s students and academics. Photo copyright QUT.[/caption] Marcus Rittenbruch showed us a bit about what CubIT is, how it works and what the plans are for the future. There are a bunch of touch screens that the public can interact with as part of The Cube, and CubIT is the system that allows you to use it. If you’re a QUT student or staff member you can &lt;a href=&#34;http://cubit.thecube.qut.edu.au/users/sign_in&#34;&gt;register an account&lt;/a&gt; and upload media (photos, text notes, video) through either the mobile web interface or the iPhone app. Then you swipe in using the card readers at the bottom of the screens and move your media around the screens, including dragging to the top bar so you can make a slideshow on the large non-touch screen. There are plans to include PDF and HTML support so you can run through presentation slides and refer to web pages when necessary. I think that’d be a pretty neat way to give a presentation. There’s a booking system which is yet to be made available online but when that’s up and running it’d be an interesting way to show potential collaborators what we can do. Over the next few meetings in BRAG we’ll be presenting on visualisation, similar to the computational talks that featured in the second half of last year. While not strictly Bayesian in nature, the talks will give examples of how to visualise different types of data and methods of analysis. I’ve put my hand up with Sama Low Choy to talk about some of the guiding principles of data visualisation that Tufte came up with. I know they’ve certainly helped when I’ve been writing papers and hopefully we can come up with a nice little talk that discusses the principles and gives some examples of good and bad graphs and discuss how we can apply the principles to make the graphs better. I’m very interested to see how others approach visualisation, particularly the common issues we have such as parameter summaries and then the specific issues such as visualising mixtures, high dimensional data, spatial information, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
