<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
      <title>Arxiv on Sam Clifford </title>
    <link>/./tags/arxiv/</link>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
    <updated>2012-10-03 00:00:00 &#43;0000 UTC</updated>
    
    <item>
      <title>New paper from Trondheim&#39;s INLA group (arXiv)</title>
      <link>/./2012/10/03/new-paper-from-trondheims-inla-group-arxiv/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Oct 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/10/03/new-paper-from-trondheims-inla-group-arxiv/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://arxiv.org/abs/1210.0333&#34;&gt;Martins, Simpson, Lindgren and Rue&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The INLA approach for approximate Bayesian inference for latent Gaussian models has been shown to give fast and accurate estimates of posterior marginals and also to be a valuable tool in practice via the R-package R-INLA. In this paper we formalize new developments in the R-INLA package and show how these features greatly extend the scope of models that can be analyzed by this interface. We also discuss the current default method in R-INLA to approximate posterior marginals of the hyperparameters using only a modest number of evaluations of the joint posterior distribution of the hyperparameters, without any need for numerical integration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m using R-INLA for two UPTECH papers at the moment and I’m really interested in the replication functionality in 3.2 and the Kronecker functionality in 3.6, which seems to be a more “official” version of the work I’ve been doing rolling my own precision matrices for use with the generic0 model class. R-INLA is definitely a worthwhile piece of software to learn to use and the stochastic PDE model for spatial inference is one of the coolest things I’ve seen in terms of spatial modelling. I wonder if the Kronecker stuff in 3.6 will let me define a separable product of a stochastic PDE model and a model for the time series component.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Resubmission of Finnish paper</title>
      <link>/./2012/08/08/resubmission-of-finnish-paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Aug 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/08/08/resubmission-of-finnish-paper/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve spent a lot of my time since Healthy Buildings finished revising the semi-parametric forecasting paper. We had submitted to Annals of Applied Statistics but it was rejected. We got some very useful comments back from the reviewer, though, and I think it’s a much stronger paper now. The reviewer encouraged us to rewrite the paper with a focus on the methodology rather than the application and submit it to a more theoretical journal. I have just submitted it to &lt;a href=&#34;http://ba.stat.cmu.edu/&#34;&gt;Bayesian Analysis&lt;/a&gt; (IF: 1.650), the official journal of &lt;a href=&#34;http://bayesian.org&#34;&gt;ISBA&lt;/a&gt;, and uploaded the preprint to arXiv (where it will replace the &lt;a href=&#34;http://arxiv.org/abs/1207.0558&#34;&gt;current version&lt;/a&gt; in the next 24 hours). As an Open Access journal with a well-written LaTeX document class, Bayesian Analysis is a journal I can get behind. Some very good papers have appeared there and as Bayesian statistics continues to grow as a field (and ISBA as a society) I think we can expect to see BA really take off as a journal. So much of modern statistics is algorithms rather than proofs and making these available to people, particularly people who aren’t academics, with freely available, peer reviewed papers will help improve the statistical capabilities of modern science.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Two papers submitted</title>
      <link>/./2012/07/06/two-papers-submitted/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jul 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/07/06/two-papers-submitted/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the last two weeks I’ve sent two papers to Annals of Applied Statistics and uploaded them to the arXiv. This fulfills the minimum publication requirements for a PhD by publication at QUT. So it’s a milestone on the way to completion. Now I just have to sort out a fourth paper as backup, give two presentations at next week’s conference, organise a final seminar session, compile all my work into a thesis and get it to my supervisors. On top of my immediate thesis work on spatio-temporal modelling, I’ve got a paper for Healthy Buildings on methods for analysing the UPTECH survey data that’ll get published, a paper on which I’m coauthor (particle losses in a thermodenuder system) that’s almost finished and the microbiology paper I wrote about previously. Busy.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A few things that warrant an update</title>
      <link>/./2012/07/04/a-few-things-that-warrant-an-update/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jul 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/07/04/a-few-things-that-warrant-an-update/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Finnish paper is pretty much ready for submission to Annals of Applied Stats. I’ve updated my publications page to include a link to the preprint on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://arxiv.org/abs/1207.0558&#34;&gt;arXiv&lt;/a&gt;. I will update my CV soon and I’ll add my posters and slides to the publications page. The Higgs boson - what’s the deal with that? &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.northcountrypublicradio.org/news/npr/156221787/cern-discovers-a-new-particle-likely-the-higgs-boson&#34;&gt;NPR has a good article on it&lt;/a&gt;. I spent the evening watching the Higgs announcements at uni and even though I thought the CERN slides were pretty cluttered and didn’t like the layout, nothing had prepared me for the ATLAS slides. Bad colour schemes (if you can call them that) and Comic Sans MS? Yuk. You don’t make science accessible by making people think “Hey. That looks like &lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt; could have designed that. Scientists aren’t so different to me after all!” Some clearly presented slides that weren’t stuffed full of text and images are, in my opinion, the key to a good scientific presentation. 1 slide per minute, no more than 5-6 lines with no more than 5-6 words per line. The slides should touch on the key points so people can, at a glance, get a good idea of what’s going on. The talk that accompanies the slides is what conveys the rest of the information in more natural language. There was a lot of great science presented tonight, but it wasn’t presented well. David Spiegelhalter &lt;a href=&#34;http://understandinguncertainty.org/higgs-it-one-sided-or-two-sided&#34;&gt;explains&lt;/a&gt; the five sigma significance of the ATLAS/CERN results. P-values and confidence intervals are two things where I think frequentist probability stops being conceptually simpler than Bayesian statistics and becomes about questions like “What is the probability of observing the data I have seen given that I have this model and these parameter estimates?” and “If I did an infinite number of trials how many times would I expect this interval for my sample mean to cover the true mean?” and “Something something agriculture”. &lt;a href=&#34;http://hb2012.org/&#34;&gt;Healthy Buildings&lt;/a&gt; is coming up next week. It’s all hands on deck at ILAQH while we put the finishing touches on the program and sort out the behind the scenes stuff. It’s going to be great. I’ll be giving two talks; the first is about how we can use the Dirichlet process for clustering in health survey data and the second is about the need for better statistics in science. ISBA 2012 was a heap of fun and there were lots of good talks. I find meeting other statisticians very inspiring. I will try to write a wrap-up when HB 2012 is over. For now, you can enjoy &lt;a href=&#34;http://xianblog.wordpress.com/2012/06/27/isba-2012-guest-post/&#34;&gt;my preliminary thoughts&lt;/a&gt; on Xian’s ’Og.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>First arXived paper</title>
      <link>/./2012/06/19/first-arxived-paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Jun 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/06/19/first-arxived-paper/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Given that I’ve had to submit a manuscript for ISBA 2012 I figured I should put it on arXiv just in case anything happens. It’d also be good to point people to it at the conference to get a better idea from the poster that I’m presenting. I’ve put a link to it on my &lt;a href=&#34;http://samclifford.info/publications/&#34; title=&#34;Publications&#34;&gt;publications&lt;/a&gt; page, but the direct link is &lt;a href=&#34;http://arxiv.org/abs/1206.3833&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to save you a click. I found the arXiv submission process very easy to use and am very impressed with its LaTeX processing.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Just a few quick thoughts</title>
      <link>/./2012/06/19/just-a-few-quick-thoughts/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Jun 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/06/19/just-a-few-quick-thoughts/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I’m setting up a laptop to take to ISBA with me as I have lots of thesis work to do. I must say, I’m really impressed with GitHub for Windows in regards to how simple it is to set up. It’s a matter of installing the program itself, then entering your github details. Cloning your GitHub repositories to your local machine is as simple as pressing a button. I haven’t had to faff about with ssh, pageant, etc. Now I just have to finish setting up remote INLA (which will require faffing about with ssh), installing LaTeX and figuring out if I can use X forwarding without X-Win. I also have to finish my ISBA poster and organise for it to be printed. Then there’s the two talks I am giving at Healthy Buildings 2012 which need writing and the Student Program work. I leave for Japan on Sunday. I should probably look at train travel from Osaka to Kyoto, find my travel money card, passport, etc. I uploaded a paper to arXiv yesterday. I’ll post about it here when it appears.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Working on this Finnish paper</title>
      <link>/./2012/06/05/working-on-this-finnish-paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jun 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/06/05/working-on-this-finnish-paper/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I figured I might as well describe how git made it possible to write the code and paper for the work I’ve been doing with Bjarke, Tareq, Kaarle and Jukka. Without git, we’d probably have been emailing code back and forth to each other or using something like Dropbox which would freak out over all the little changes we make, making it impossible to both be working on the same file at once. &lt;a href=&#34;http://git-scm.com/&#34;&gt;Git&lt;/a&gt; is a distributed version control system that allows you to track revisions to your code and invite multiple collaborators to the project. I’ve talked about it &lt;a href=&#34;http://samclifford.info/tag/git/&#34;&gt;previously&lt;/a&gt; but basically it’s this great system where you can work on a project with multiple people, making your changes, committing them on your local machine to save them. Once you are happy with the changes you’ve made and they don’t break anything, you can push the changes to the shared repository where all the other members of the project have access to them. If there’s a conflict, git lets you know and you can fix it up then re-commit and push. There are tools for reverting changes, making new branches, merging branches, etc. June 13 2011. It’s still three weeks before I’m due to arrive in Finland. I upload the code from the book chapter on Bayesian Splines that I’ve been writing for BRAG. Bjarke and I spend a bit of time emailing back and forth about how splines work, as he hasn’t used them in a regression framework before. Bjarke has sent me a copy of the draft of his paper on a GLM with autoregressive residuals. I’ve still got the 8BNP workshop to attend before arriving in Finland. July 5 2011. I arrive in Finland and meet Tareq and Bjarke for a meeting. We take a copious amount of notes during a long discussion where we set out what we want to achieve long term and what we want to have finished by the time I leave. The aim is to at least have some working code that combines my splines with Bjarke’s code that does autoregressive residuals. July 6 2011. Bjarke’s code is added to the git repository and we get to work understanding what the other person has written. We’re both still getting to grips with how git works and end up accidentally making new branches. I spend most of my time annotating code so that I know where to look when things inevitably go wrong. Time is spent ensuring we have ways of visualising our results so we know if things are going totally wrong. July 7-8 2011. We spend the next few days attempting to stitch the code together. Bjarke doesn’t use Google Chat or Facebook so there’s a little email correspondence at this time but it’s mostly office conversations. July 9-10 2011. No work happens here as Bjarke and I are holidaying with his in-laws for the weekend at a summer cottage near Lappeenranta (near the Russian border). July 11-16 2011. This is the most creative and chaotic period of working on the paper. Notes are made on A4 paper, transcribed as notes in a text file on git when they are worth following up and abandoned when they don’t lead anywhere. We start really getting to grips with multivariate splines, Metropolis-within-Gibbs, testing out new ideas, making new branches, merging them when they work, deleting them when they don’t, scribbling maths out on pieces of paper and running up and down the corridors whenever there’s a breakthrough. July 19-31 2011. I return to Australia and we spend some time writing about what we managed to get done while I was overseas. We’re back to one branch and are largely discussing the methodology and making sure plotting works. August, September 2011. I continue making changes to the way autoregressive residuals are handled, Bjarke codes up some diagnostics and begins examining a wide range of model specifications for the air quality data we’re working with in order to come up with a way of illustrating how what we’ve done is so cool. October, November 2011. Some changes are made to the way the penalties are handled, the code becomes more functional and most of the focus is on plotting, diagnostics and model choice. Plots are saved as PDF files using &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mathworks.com/matlabcentral/fileexchange/23629&#34;&gt;export_fig.m&lt;/a&gt; within our script and are brought under the control of git so that we can replace one set of results with another in a single commit. December 2011. Some radical changes are made to the way the autoregressive error structure is passed to the model, making it more flexible. These changes are contained in a separate branch so that Bjarke can continue working on his model comparison knowing that his code will continue to run. He checks it out and offers feedback. January 2012. A lot of work is done on making sure the paper explains what’s going on. A few more features are introduced and the code is commented heavily. February-April 2012. Bjarke spends a lot of time making sure the scripts to call the model fitting, forecasting and diagnostics work properly. May 2012. A draft paper is sent around for feedback, some changes to the description of the method are recommended, as are a few different model specifications. Development on the code itself has stopped but the diagnostics, plotting and inference continues. Much of the work is now happening on QUT’s supercomputer as competing models are tested. Writing about the autoregressive errors is filled out a bit to ensure that the forecasting is highlighted. June 2012. The paper is almost finished. We’re waiting on feedback from a co-author who has been quite sick. There have been some large rewrites based on Kerrie’s feedback, mostly to change the order so that it’s a punchier article which highlights the novelty of the method rather than me just talking about how cool splines are. Support is being canvassed among the authors for uploading the draft to arXiv and releasing the code once the paper is published. And that’s where we stand at the moment. Hopefully I can make the git repository public and you can have a look at what’s happened and where we’ve come from with this. It might need a bit of pruning first to make sure that no data that shouldn’t be publicly available isn’t accidentally made public. There’s a minimal working example in the code where we simulate some data, so hopefully that’s enough to demonstrate what we’ve done. There are some really neat ways of visualising the work done on GitHub, including a network diagram of the committed changes and branches, contributions of each person over time, when commits occur most frequently, what (programming) languages the project uses and how frequent additions and deletions occur (and therefore the growth rate of the project). I hope this sheds some light on the process that’s been used. GitHub was basically a way for the QUT and Helsinki groups to collaborate, with Bjarke and I acting as the conduits for reviews and comments. Git allowed us to write a whole bunch of code together, following up all sorts of crazy ideas without getting in each others’ way. The paper was written as we went and is subject to the same version control (after all, LaTeX is code too). I have found it a really great way of working. I’d like to see how it goes with a few more people programming and whether I can work with a few other people to try to make the changes to the paper directly via git rather me making the changes based on notes scribbled on a printed copy. P.S. Wow, I can’t believe it’s been nearly a year since we started working on this. Well, I can, as we had a few delays where it turned out we needed to rewrite large chunks of code and the paper. P.P.S. I just managed to merge the development branch with the modified way of dealing with the residuals back into the master branch without there being any conflicts. I didn’t expect conflicts but it’s nice to know that everything’s back in the master branch. Below is an image of the commit history. It doesn’t show the number of changes in each commit, but given that commits occur when an idea has been tested or a section written, it’s a good indication of a parcel of working being done. &lt;a href=&#34;commits.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://samcliffordinfo.files.wordpress.com/2012/06/commits.png&#34; title=&#34;commits&#34; alt=&#34;Committed changes for the Finnish paper&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; For interest’s sake &lt;a href=&#34;https://maps.google.com/maps/ms?msid=205578669134200940456.0004a7be06572cca98eec&amp;amp;msa=0&#34;&gt;here’s a map of my time in Finland&lt;/a&gt;. I haven’t got the exact location of the summer cottage but it’s near Taipalsaari. Here’s &lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/photos/106543548808921798128/albums/5637271904465537361?authkey=CIOgldL52du6vAE&#34;&gt;my collection of photos from my time in Finland&lt;/a&gt;. I had originally uploaded them to Facebook and given detailed captions but the move to Google Plus ended up removing the captions. Leave a comment on them asking a question if you want to know more.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gelman and Robert</title>
      <link>/./2012/05/25/gelman-and-robert/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 May 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/05/25/gelman-and-robert/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Kerrie Mengersen, one of my supervisors, is visiting some colleagues in France at the moment. It appears that one of the outputs of this visit is a discussion paper, “In praise of the referee”, written with Nicolas Chopin, Andrew Gelman and Christian Robert (&lt;a href=&#34;http://arxiv.org/abs/1205.4304&#34;&gt;arXiv&lt;/a&gt;). There’s been a lot of discussion recently about the role of journals, publishers and reviewers in academic publishing ranging from defending the &lt;em&gt;status quo&lt;/em&gt; to totally overhauling the system by shedding paper journals and moving everything online to a distributed network of institutional ePrints repositories. The paper by Chopin et al. makes two recommendations after a lengthy discussion about where we find ourselves&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Post-publication peer review with comment threads on arXiv and/or a filtering service where instead of acting as reviewers, editorial boards pick out worthwhile new research as a list of recommended reading.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A reviewer commons where academics are taught how to review and the reviewer reports (and their names) are published alongside the article.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article is worth a read. I figured I’d also share an old Gelman blog post that he’s recently linked to, “&lt;a href=&#34;http://andrewgelman.com/2009/07/advice_on_writi/&#34;&gt;Advice on writing research articles&lt;/a&gt;”. The seven pieces of general advice are well worth remembering. It’s basically “Start with your conclusions and work backwards towards your methods”. Christian Robert has &lt;a href=&#34;http://xianblog.wordpress.com/2012/05/25/xian-australian-tour-2012/&#34;&gt;published the dates for his Australian tour&lt;/a&gt;. I’m not particularly interested in ABC but the talk on Rao-Blackwellisation looks interesting. Anyone who’s interested in learning a bit about what Bayesian simulation is, without necessarily having a statistics background, would do well to attend the public talk entitled “Simulation as a universal tool for statistics”, which you could probably consider as a popular science talk.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Open access and my next paper</title>
      <link>/./2012/04/19/open-access-and-my-next-paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Apr 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/04/19/open-access-and-my-next-paper/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I got some substantial feedback from one of my supervisors earlier in the week and I’ve been chopping and changing this paper to ensure that the results section is more than just “Look at these graphs. They are graphs.” and that the introduction actually introduces the problem before leaping into how we propose to solve it. Another one of my supervisors will always pick me up on my use of informal language. I tend to write as if I’m explaining how I went about solving a problem, which is very well suited to tutorials, blogging and the &lt;a href=&#34;https://wiki.qut.edu.au/display/npbayes/home&#34;&gt;NP Bayes Wiki&lt;/a&gt; (the reading group is currently on hiatus) but less well suited to academic papers which will be sent to peer reviewed journals. I need to keep working on my formal scientific writing. Part of that probably means reading more academic papers from start to finish rather than skimming them for the information that I need. It probably also doesn’t help that most of the methodological stuff that I’m writing is drawn from the documentation and FAQs of an R package as well as personal communication with the authors of said package (said package is &lt;a href=&#34;www.r-inla.org&#34;&gt;R-INLA&lt;/a&gt;). I’ve got three papers on the go at the moment, so it’s going to be important that I can pick the low-hanging fruit of avoiding informal language so that my supervisors can concentrate on the actual work when giving me feedback. I’ve recently been spending a fair amount of time thinking about, and discussing with some colleagues, the issues of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://thecostofknowledge.com/&#34;&gt;Elsevier boycott&lt;/a&gt;, open access publishing and the use of preprint repositories like &lt;a href=&#34;http://arxiv.org/&#34;&gt;arXiv&lt;/a&gt;. QUT supports open access to some extent by running an &lt;a href=&#34;http://eprints.qut.edu.au/&#34;&gt;ePrints&lt;/a&gt; repository, where university researchers are encouraged to deposit a preprint of their work (not the version published by the journal), and &lt;a href=&#34;http://libguides.library.qut.edu.au/content.php?pid=84068&amp;amp;sid=624559&#34;&gt;subscribing to, or taking out membership with&lt;/a&gt;, a few open access journals. Some of these are quite highly regarded, particularly publications by the Public Library of Science, such as &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.plosone.org/home.action&#34;&gt;PLoS ONE&lt;/a&gt;. The bulk of our papers at ILAQH end up in Elsevier’s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.journals.elsevier.com/atmospheric-environment/&#34;&gt;Atmospheric Environment&lt;/a&gt;, quite a respectable journal, but I feel uncomfortable propping up a business with such a coercive business model that allows them to operate at a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2012/02/14/science/researchers-boycott-elsevier-journal-publisher.html?_r=1&#34;&gt;profit level of 36&lt;/a&gt;%. Sure, Adam Smith tells us that the baker is a baker not out of a love of bread but out of a desire to earn money with which to live, but we don’t have to accept the terms of business of one large company. I’m particularly interested in journals where the authors retain the copyright (or in the case of QUT, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mopp.qut.edu.au/D/D_03_01.jsp#D_03_01.05.mdoc&#34;&gt;the authors’ institution&lt;/a&gt;). I’m also a fan of journals which are innovating in the modern publishing environment, such as the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amstat.org&#34;&gt;American Statistical Association&lt;/a&gt;’s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jstatsoft.org/&#34;&gt;Journal of Statistical Software&lt;/a&gt; which is not only open access but publishes each article as its own issue of the journal, increasing the frequency of publication to a point where when an article’s reviewed it’s published straight away. I don’t like Elsevier’s business model and would be happy to look at publishing in high quality open access journals where the authors don’t have to sign away their copyright to the publishers. After all, it’s not the journals funding or doing the work. I believe granting the publishers a time-limited exclusive license to publish would be a far better model. There are other journals with a similar level of credibility and respect that don’t require authors to sign over copyright, don’t coerce libraries into taking big packages with unwanted journals bundled in and don’t freeze the person in the street out of reading the results of publicly funded research (a lot of research in Australia is funded by the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.arc.gov.au/&#34;&gt;Australian Research Council&lt;/a&gt;, a government funding body). I don’t think Elsevier are evil, but they have a terrible business model in terms of disseminating high quality research to the public in an affordable manner. There are others out there doing a better job and researchers should support them.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
