<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
      <title>Edward Tufte on Sam Clifford </title>
    <link>/./tags/edward-tufte/</link>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
    <updated>2013-09-10 00:00:00 &#43;0000 UTC</updated>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using ggplot2 in SEB113</title>
      <link>/./2013/09/10/using-ggplot2-in-seb113/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Sep 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2013/09/10/using-ggplot2-in-seb113/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the big pieces of feedback we got during last semester’s SEB113 class was that the programming was difficult to understand and reproduce. While the subject is not a programming subject, we do use R quite heavily for all of the data analysis. Maths B isn’t a pre-requisite for SEB113 and I’d wager that even fewer of the students entering the ST01 Bachelor of Science program have taken senior IPT/ICT subjects at their high schools than have taken Maths B. This semester we introduced R in the very first lecture and gave it a bit of a context. This means that students are aware from the get-go that they will be learning statistics through data analysis on a computer. The lectorials introduce the concepts and provide code for the resulting plots and analysis, the computer labs show how to do that particular form of analysis in R and then the collaborative workshops reinforce the labs by getting groups to work through the analysis of some problem using the statistical concepts and code that they’ve learned that week. One of the biggest stumbling blocks last semester was the inconsistency in the way visualisation was done in R. We used a combination of base graphics, trellis graphics in the lattice package, heatmaps and dendrograms from other packages and had to turn to yet another package to get colorbars for the heatmaps. Part of the fine-tuning this semester has been employing someone (who also does the labs) to rewrite the graphics in the labs in terms of Hadley Wickham’s &lt;a href=&#34;http://ggplot2.org/&#34;&gt;ggplot2&lt;/a&gt; library. This brings consistency to the graphical aspect of the unit and the plot geometries are named explicitly so that it’s clear what style of plot you’ll be generating. I was quite sceptical of ggplot2 when I first saw it, as the only exposure I had to it was the default options for a scatterplot with points. Sure, that’s pretty boring, but the fact that you can make a faceted grid (or wrap it using facet_wrap instead of facet_grid) means that investigating the use of small multiples is so much easier. Small multiples is a visualisation technique developed by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.edwardtufte.com/tufte/&#34;&gt;Edward Tufte&lt;/a&gt; to allow the reader to see how the relationship between two variables changes as you also vary one or two other (categorical) covariates. Doing this in lattice required specifying a formula, similar to the way you specify a model in lm, but lattice is so different from the base graphics that you lose consistency. I’m touching up this week’s workshop at the moment and I’m really noticing where the graphics code has been greatly simplified by access to a grammar of graphics for a powerful set of plotting routines. The &lt;a href=&#34;http://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/GGally/index.html&#34;&gt;GGally&lt;/a&gt; pacakge provides things like ggpairs, which does what pairs does in the base graphics but gives you the correlation above the diagonal and the scatterplots below the diagonal. This makes for more informative graphs with the beauty of the ggplot style. As far as I can tell we’re hearing fewer complaints about the programming and the visualisation is happening much quicker in the workshops this semester as ggplot2’s documentation is amazing and it’s often a choice of geometry (and changing one or two options) rather than a choice of library (and changing the entire approach to the coding). The use of ggplot2 has made teaching visualisation much simpler and we’re now getting through the workshops quite quickly because the visualisation is no longer a huge stumbling block.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Presenting data and mathematical ideas</title>
      <link>/./2012/12/15/presenting-data-and-mathematical-ideas/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Dec 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/12/15/presenting-data-and-mathematical-ideas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I was hanging out with some friends the other night and the topic of conversation turned to an infographic that one of the guys was working on for a friend of his, &lt;a href=&#34;http://onceround.com/2012/12/11/red-dwarf-smeg-count/&#34;&gt;the number of times the word “smeg” (or a variant) appears in each episode&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0094535/&#34;&gt;Red Dwarf&lt;/a&gt; (made in &lt;a href=&#34;http://processing.org/&#34;&gt;Processing&lt;/a&gt;). We got chatting about data visualisation and ended up talking about Edward Tufte and his approach to the various aspects of using data to show information. Apparently his brother have him a copy of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.edwardtufte.com/tufte/books_vdqi&#34;&gt;Tufte’s book&lt;/a&gt; last year and he was kind enough to loan it to me. &lt;a href=&#34;http://staff.qut.edu.au/staff/lowchoy/&#34;&gt;One of my supervisors&lt;/a&gt; is a huge fan of Tufte’s approach and it’s worn off on me. Throughout my thesis I’ve moved away from giant scatter plots of the data to summary plots that don’t use more “ink” than is necessary to show the information. An example he gives in the book is the boxplot, which typically contains a lot of redundant information. The image below shows Tufte’s stripped down boxplot and the default R boxplot for the same data. In the more traditional boxplot, the maximum of the data (within 1.5 IQR) is represented by the end of the whisker as well as a hinge. The hinge isn’t necessary and neither is the box which marks the 25th and 75th percentiles as the other end of the whisker represents these. With no box, there’s no need for a horizontal stripe for the median, so it can be represented as a dot.&lt;a href=&#34;http://samcliffordinfo.files.wordpress.com/2012/12/boxplots.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;boxplots.png?w=300&#34; alt=&#34;boxplots&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; There are some plots in my thesis papers of which I’m quite proud and I will upload some of them here once the papers are finalised. My Tufte-mad supervisor has even commented on how my plots have become quite minimalist, something she attributes to the 2000s/10s despite Tufte’s work dating back to the 1970s. I’ve noticed that the R packages I’ve tended to use (&lt;a href=&#34;http://r-inla.org/&#34;&gt;R-INLA&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/mgcv/index.html&#34;&gt;mgcv&lt;/a&gt;) have quite simple graphics. While there are some fantastic plotting packages such as &lt;a href=&#34;http://ggplot2.org/&#34;&gt;ggplot2&lt;/a&gt; that make it quite easy to produce very pretty graphics, I feel far more familiar mucking around with the base graphics system to add points, lines and polygons to a blank plot. If you take the approach that Tufte does, that the ink on the page should represent data, and that there should be no extraneous elements to your plot (such as cross-hatching a barplot or colour where it doesn’t convey information) then it’s not hard to shy away from packages that do a lot of very nice, but ultimately data-poor, plotting. But graphs on the printed page are not the only way to represent data or mathematical or statistical concepts. The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jK7xPo1YXzY&#34;&gt;Museum of Mathematics&lt;/a&gt; in New York looks to have a lot of really cool displays of a wide range of mathematical concepts, for example. My Advanced Calculus lecturer, Dr Jack Wrigley, had a background in education and often used props in class to illustrate ideas, such as holding pieces of paper against a balloon to give us a visual representation of a tangent and normal surfaces. I don’t often have props when doing improvised theatre but academic presentation is, at the end of the day, just another type of performance. Part of the work I’ve been doing on modelling temporal trends from split panel design data involves modelling penalised random walks where the random walk is on a torus that represents a joint term for the hour of the day and the day of the week. This “hour of the week” term has 168 unique values, but we want to smooth both in the day to day and hour to hour direction, rather than just looking at the circle formed by gluing Saturday 11pm to Midnight and then Sunday 1am. Some people might be very good at visualising Markov random fields through their precision matrix but there will be many people in my PhD final seminar audience who are not postgraduate level statisticians. For the purpose of explaining one of the key ideas in my thesis, I am considering bringing an inflatable pool ring and a marker in order to draw the smoothing directions on the torus that represents the product of two circular spaces. If this doesn’t make up for the conceded pass I got in Jack Wrigley’s class I have no idea what will.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
