<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
      <title>Isba on Sam Clifford </title>
    <link>/./tags/isba/</link>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
    <updated>2012-08-30 00:00:00 &#43;0000 UTC</updated>
    
    <item>
      <title>Unfinnished business</title>
      <link>/./2012/08/30/unfinnished-business/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Aug 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/08/30/unfinnished-business/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve just heard from Kerrie Mengersen that the Finnish paper got rejected by BA for not being novel enough to publish there. So now I’m in a situation where I’ve got a paper which is too methodological for an applied stats journal (and far too methodological for an atmospheric science journal) and not a novel enough methodology for a journal as theoretical as BA. If BA don’t think it’s novel enough and it’s not the first time this data’s been published we’ll struggle to get it into something like &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rss.org.uk/site/cms/contentviewarticle.asp?article=876&#34;&gt;JRSS B&lt;/a&gt; (IF: 3.645), &lt;a href=&#34;http://rsif.royalsocietypublishing.org/&#34;&gt;JRS: Interface&lt;/a&gt; (IF: 4.402) or &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.plosone.org&#34;&gt;PLoS One&lt;/a&gt; (IF: 4.092). Our options, then, seem to be trying an Elsevier journal like &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.journals.elsevier.com/environmental-modelling-and-software/&#34;&gt;EMS&lt;/a&gt; (IF: 3.114) or &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.journals.elsevier.com/computational-statistics-and-data-analysis/&#34;&gt;CSDA&lt;/a&gt; (IF: 1.028), which I’m not keen to do, somewhere like &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jstatsoft.org&#34;&gt;JSS&lt;/a&gt; (IF: 2.647) or a more applied journal like &lt;a href=&#34;http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/journal/10.1111/(ISSN)1467-9876&#34;&gt;JRSS C&lt;/a&gt; (IF: 0.828, which is quite low). I’d like to put this in a statistics journal because I want to have a career as a statistician rather than just someone who can only work in aerosols. That’s one of the reasons I’m not keen to publish this somewhere like Atmospheric Environment (where both my article and Bjarke’s, the bases of this work, were published). I’m really kicking myself now for not submitting an abstract for this as a contributed talk at ISBA. I would’ve got a BA article out of it. In happier news, I gave a presentation with two other PhD students to BRAG this morning where we talked about INLA. It went well and I think we’ve convinced a few of the others that INLA is pretty cool and worth using. Edit: and I’m getting a lot of mileage out of the Finnish/finish pun.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Summary of the last week&#39;s Christian Robert visit</title>
      <link>/./2012/08/24/summary-of-the-last-weeks-christian-robert-visit/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Aug 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/08/24/summary-of-the-last-weeks-christian-robert-visit/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I didn’t have any one on one meetings with Professor Robert but he did address two of my stats research group’s meetings and gave two seminars as part of his AMSI talk. In addition to this, there was a few hours one afternoon where QUT statisticians presented some of the Bayesian computation that is worked on here. Christian’s first talk to BRAG focused on model choice and comparison and &lt;a href=&#34;http://samclifford.info/2012/08/16/a-few-things-from-today/&#34;&gt;I wrote about it last week&lt;/a&gt;. The second talk to BRAG (&lt;a href=&#34;http://storify.com/samclifford/christian-robert-s-second-brag-talk&#34;&gt;Storify&lt;/a&gt;) was to finish off the themes on improving MCMC methods that he mentioned. We picked up where we left off, with a discussion of simulated tempering. The choice of &lt;em&gt;α&lt;/em&gt; is probably the key concept here, and Christian recommends choosing a scale based on the number of data points (if π&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt; is the original likelihood, try using π = π&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1/&lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; for &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; data points). Allowing &lt;em&gt;α&lt;/em&gt; to take multiple values (or even have a distribution) means that we now have a space of target posteriors. By moving around in this space of posteriors we are less likely to end up with sticky Markov chains because a sharply peaked posterior in one posterior will likely not be as sharply peaked in another posterior. Robert gave a reference to a paper by Radford Neal which deals with tempering [1]. Another way to ensure movement throughout the posterior space is to either subsample the data or to perturb the data with a small amount of noise. These will again change the posterior (ever so slightly) and help exploration of the space to find the modes. A change of variable is another way to flatten out the posterior. Parallel computation is another option; running the same model with different starting values and using the posterior density (a one dimensional value for each simulation) to get a sense of what the maximum value of the posterior might be. Low density models can be dropped in this way as they are not near the global mode of the posterior. I find this approach quite interesting and if I had a bit more time I’d try implementing it. Some exploration of low density modes is burn-in, but if the exploration is trapped at a local mode (and tempering, etc. aren’t getting it out of there) then perhaps it ought to be dropped. Robert then went on to talk about using auxiliary variables to create joint densities where we can move along level sets of the posterior to get large jumps in the parameter of interest. This is probably where I got lost, but I did manage to get that there’s a paper by Girolami and Calderhead [2] where this is formalised as Langevin and Hamiltonian Monte Carlo. Some of the members of BRAG will be presenting LMC/HMC at a future meeting and I look forward to it. It’s always interesting to find out that so much Bayesian computation started out as a branch of physics (the Metropolis(-Hastings) algorithm as a solution for the Ising/Potts model, for example). I’ve used Storify to publish my notes from the two AMSI sessions (&lt;a href=&#34;http://samclifford.info/2012/08/21/christian-roberts-talk-on-simulation/&#34; title=&#34;Christian Robert&amp;#39;s talk on simulation&#34;&gt;simulation&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://samclifford.info/2012/08/22/christian-roberts-talk-on-abc-for-model-choice-and-open-floor-on-bayesian-computation-2/&#34; title=&#34;Christian Robert&amp;#39;s talk on ABC for Model Choice and open floor on Bayesian computation&#34;&gt;ABC for model choice&lt;/a&gt;) that were part of Christian’s tour. I missed the one at UQ about Rao-Blackwellisation, unfortunately. Some of his slides from his talks are available online at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.slideshare.net/xianblog/presentations&#34;&gt;Slideshare&lt;/a&gt;. The open floor after the ABC talk was quite good as it gave me a chance to see what people are working on. While I have seen a few pyMCMC talks before there seems to be quite a lot of energy from Chris Strickland and Clair Alston for the development of new models in the pyMCMC framework. I’ve previously spoken with Chris about how to go about using it for spline models and spatial modelling and I hope that once I finish my PhD I’ve got some time to check out pyMCMC in greater depth. If you want to have a look, you can clone it from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://bitbucket.org/christophermarkstrickland/pymcmc/&#34;&gt;git repository on bitbucket&lt;/a&gt;. It was also interesting to see the work Ewan Cameron and Tony Pettitt have been doing on ABC for astronomical data (evolution of galaxies, etc.) and the work of Chris Drovandi, James McGree, Liz Ryan and others on using Sequential Monte Carlo with ABC for adaptive clinical study design. All in all a good week of seminars with lots of interesting ideas. &lt;a href=&#34;http://bayesian.org/forums/conferences/3606&#34;&gt;Bayes on the Beach 2012&lt;/a&gt; is &lt;a href=&#34;http://bragqut.wordpress.com/beachbayes2012/&#34;&gt;coming up&lt;/a&gt;. This is one of my favourite events of the year because it’s a chance to get away from uni with a bunch of statisticians and discuss some interesting problems and do little workshops. The beach is also quite a nice part of it and there’s usually some sort of games night (last year I contributed a game which is basically Chinese Whispers mixed with Pictionary and we all had a lot of fun trying to figure out what was going on). It’s also a really good chance for early PhD students to present a poster in a very friendly environment so they can get used to talking to others about their work. I’ve also managed to land myself on the list of presenters for the School of Mathematical Sciences’ “Postgrad Day”. While not a member of the school, two of my supervisors are and I’ve been working on statistical methods during my PhD. I will present the work I’ve been doing with my Finnish collaborators in a 20 minute slot. This will be a sort of practice run for my final seminar and is what I should have submitted to ISBA 2012 (but when abstracts closed we weren’t nearly ready enough). It’ll be good to have an audience of mathematicians and statisticians, because I always feel awkward explaining statistical research to aerosol scientists, chemists, physicists and microbiologists. Perhaps I need to focus a bit more on pitching a particular aspect of my work to the audience I’ve got. [1] [Neal, R. M., (1996) “Sampling from Multimodal Distributions using Tempered Transitions”, &lt;em&gt;Statistics and Computing&lt;/em&gt; 6, pp. 353-366](&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.springerlink.com/content/x6417mm4h7845735/&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;http://www.springerlink.com/content/x6417mm4h7845735/&lt;/a&gt;). [2] [Girolami, M., and Calderhead, B., (2011) “Riemann manifold Langevin and Hamiltonian Monte Carlo methods”, &lt;em&gt;Journal of the Royal Statistical Society - Series B&lt;/em&gt; 73(2), pp. 1-37.](&lt;a href=&#34;http://people.stat.sfu.ca/~cao/Research/GirolamiCalderhead.pdf&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;http://people.stat.sfu.ca/~cao/Research/GirolamiCalderhead.pdf&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A few things that warrant an update</title>
      <link>/./2012/07/04/a-few-things-that-warrant-an-update/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jul 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/07/04/a-few-things-that-warrant-an-update/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Finnish paper is pretty much ready for submission to Annals of Applied Stats. I’ve updated my publications page to include a link to the preprint on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://arxiv.org/abs/1207.0558&#34;&gt;arXiv&lt;/a&gt;. I will update my CV soon and I’ll add my posters and slides to the publications page. The Higgs boson - what’s the deal with that? &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.northcountrypublicradio.org/news/npr/156221787/cern-discovers-a-new-particle-likely-the-higgs-boson&#34;&gt;NPR has a good article on it&lt;/a&gt;. I spent the evening watching the Higgs announcements at uni and even though I thought the CERN slides were pretty cluttered and didn’t like the layout, nothing had prepared me for the ATLAS slides. Bad colour schemes (if you can call them that) and Comic Sans MS? Yuk. You don’t make science accessible by making people think “Hey. That looks like &lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt; could have designed that. Scientists aren’t so different to me after all!” Some clearly presented slides that weren’t stuffed full of text and images are, in my opinion, the key to a good scientific presentation. 1 slide per minute, no more than 5-6 lines with no more than 5-6 words per line. The slides should touch on the key points so people can, at a glance, get a good idea of what’s going on. The talk that accompanies the slides is what conveys the rest of the information in more natural language. There was a lot of great science presented tonight, but it wasn’t presented well. David Spiegelhalter &lt;a href=&#34;http://understandinguncertainty.org/higgs-it-one-sided-or-two-sided&#34;&gt;explains&lt;/a&gt; the five sigma significance of the ATLAS/CERN results. P-values and confidence intervals are two things where I think frequentist probability stops being conceptually simpler than Bayesian statistics and becomes about questions like “What is the probability of observing the data I have seen given that I have this model and these parameter estimates?” and “If I did an infinite number of trials how many times would I expect this interval for my sample mean to cover the true mean?” and “Something something agriculture”. &lt;a href=&#34;http://hb2012.org/&#34;&gt;Healthy Buildings&lt;/a&gt; is coming up next week. It’s all hands on deck at ILAQH while we put the finishing touches on the program and sort out the behind the scenes stuff. It’s going to be great. I’ll be giving two talks; the first is about how we can use the Dirichlet process for clustering in health survey data and the second is about the need for better statistics in science. ISBA 2012 was a heap of fun and there were lots of good talks. I find meeting other statisticians very inspiring. I will try to write a wrap-up when HB 2012 is over. For now, you can enjoy &lt;a href=&#34;http://xianblog.wordpress.com/2012/06/27/isba-2012-guest-post/&#34;&gt;my preliminary thoughts&lt;/a&gt; on Xian’s ’Og.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ISBA 2012 - A few thoughts</title>
      <link>/./2012/06/27/isba-2012---a-few-thoughts/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Jun 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/06/27/isba-2012---a-few-thoughts/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Christian Robert asked for some guest bloggers for ISBA 2012 and &lt;a href=&#34;http://xianblog.wordpress.com/2012/06/27/isba-2012-guest-post/&#34;&gt;today his ’og features my thoughts&lt;/a&gt; as of this morning’s coffee break. There have been some really amazing talks in the sessions I’ve gone to, mostly in the NP Bayes talks. My poster went well, I had a good discussion with Daniel Williamson about some of the shortfalls of P-spline models when smoothing temporal data. Hopefully I convinced him that my use of AR residuals means I’m not modelling noise with a highly oscillatory spline. I don’t think I can convince him of the validity of using an informative Gamma(1,b) prior for the smoothing parameter as he’s quite firmly in the subjective priors camp. Perhaps he and Sama should have a meeting. I still haven’t been able to find Jukka Corander, he didn’t seem to be at the poster session where three of his students were presenting. Perhaps I just haven’t spotted him because we’ve only met once before and that was a year ago.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A few observations on Kyoto so far</title>
      <link>/./2012/06/25/a-few-observations-on-kyoto-so-far/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jun 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/06/25/a-few-observations-on-kyoto-so-far/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve been here roughly 24 hours and thought I might jot down a few things I’ve noticed about Kyoto, at least the parts I’ve been to. It’s a very human scale city. A lot of the photos I’ve seen of Tokyo made me think that urban Japan is this sprawling metropolis of high rise buildings, neon lights, etc. Kyoto is not like that at all. Most of the buildings I’ve seen in the downtown area are perhaps four stories tall. You can see the mountains by looking down the street. There are not multiple lane highways running through the CBD, most streets near the central JR station are one lane in each direction, maybe two at the intersection. A few of the bigger streets may be three or four lanes in each direction but they aren’t clogged full of traffic and nor are they speedways. Contrast this to Brisbane where almost every street downtown is a four lane one way street with on-street parking on each side except in peak hour where all four lanes are on street parking because traffic slows to about 10km/hr. There is a huge bike culture. It seems to be the easiest way to get around when making short trips. No one locks their bikes up. You just pop up the kick stand and go into the store for a few minutes. There are bike lanes at intersections for crossing and people ride on the road and the footpaths, and down the arcades in some places. There appear to be no helmet laws. Bins are as rare as hen’s teeth yet the city doesn’t have a litter problem. Every vending machine has recycling bins next to it and people eat their food at the shops where they buy it, even if it’s a pokey little hole in the wall takeaway dumpling place in an arcade. People don’t walk around eating and drinking like they do in Australia. You sit down, eat your takeaway meal, dump the rubbish in the bin and then off you go. I must have spent ten minutes walking around with an empty takoyaki tray before deciding to walk into a Starbucks, dump by garbage, buy an iced tea, drink it quickly, dump the rubbish and leave. The markets are wonderful. I spent the late morning walking around downtown with two other QUT ISBA attendees. We went to a few arcades where almost every shop seemed to be selling fresh fish, fermented vegetables, tofu, fried takeaway, dried beans, etc. The smells! Like nothing you get in Brisbane markets (I’m thinking Brisbane Square). We stopped for some takoyaki (octopus croquettes, basically) and I got a tempura lotus root on a stick. Not my usual fare but it’s not the sort of thing you see all that often in Brisbane so I decided I’d have a go. I couldn’t bring myself to eat the boiled baby octopus on a skewer, though; too Lovecraftian. All in all, Kyoto appears to be a great little town with a fantastic public transport system, good food, friendly people all at a scale that’s not completely overwhelming. I would consider living here if there was a good postdoc position. I’d have to learn much more Japanese than “Arigato” and “Ohaio gozaimasu”.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Wald is not enough</title>
      <link>/./2012/06/25/the-wald-is-not-enough/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jun 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/06/25/the-wald-is-not-enough/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I’m working on a talk I’m presenting at Healthy Buildings 2012 while I do some travel to ISBA. My supervisor, who is president of the Healthy Buildings conference this year, saw &lt;a href=&#34;http://samclifford.info/2012/06/01/statistics-not-just-for-statisticians/&#34;&gt;a blog post of mine&lt;/a&gt; and thought that it would make a good presentation for the student plenary session. The basic point of the talk is that the quality of scientific research is greatly improved by ensuring that appropriate statistical analysis is performed and presented clearly. There have been so many papers and presentations I’ve seen where the authors just stop at descriptive statistics of their data and draw inferences just from describing the data. If we’re lucky they’ll do a t-test or ANOVA. If we’re not, they’ll just calculate summary statistics and perhaps a correlation between the response and the covariates rather than doing any statistical modelling. The problem isn’t restricted to indoor air quality and climate, the focus of this conference, though. &lt;a href=&#34;http://conidialcoleopticide.wordpress.com/&#34;&gt;A friend of mine&lt;/a&gt; has come across the same issue in her literature review for using microbes to control insect pests. There are some groups doing some amazing scientific work with robust statistics, such as Hugh Possingham’s group at UQ who look at applying econometric principles to conservation (think triage for species rather than patients). At the risk of spoiling the ending of my talk, being “the statistician” in my group has given me the opportunity to work on some interesting aerosol science problems such as particle loss in instrumentation, the multi-modality of SMPS data and how it affects automatic processing, microbiology populations in classrooms, the fate of non-background ions and determining exposure measures from personal samplers and monitoring equipment that have different time steps. In turn, I have introduced the researchers I’m working with to new statistical techniques (often with R code) which they can adapt and use in future work. Every group needs a statistician in it, but not just to be handed the data to analyse and used as a black box where data goes in and analysis comes out. For starters, the statistician needs to know what the data actually describe. But the statistician should be there to build the skill set of the group. We can’t expect that every scientist has PhD level statistical skills but the scientist needs to be comfortable going beyond ANOVA to investigate what’s happening in their experimental or observational data. P.S. the title for this talk was inspired by a brief conversation with my ISBA room-mate about how great statistics-based puns are.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>First arXived paper</title>
      <link>/./2012/06/19/first-arxived-paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Jun 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/06/19/first-arxived-paper/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Given that I’ve had to submit a manuscript for ISBA 2012 I figured I should put it on arXiv just in case anything happens. It’d also be good to point people to it at the conference to get a better idea from the poster that I’m presenting. I’ve put a link to it on my &lt;a href=&#34;http://samclifford.info/publications/&#34; title=&#34;Publications&#34;&gt;publications&lt;/a&gt; page, but the direct link is &lt;a href=&#34;http://arxiv.org/abs/1206.3833&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to save you a click. I found the arXiv submission process very easy to use and am very impressed with its LaTeX processing.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ISBA update - logistics</title>
      <link>/./2012/05/10/isba-update---logistics/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 May 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/05/10/isba-update---logistics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This morning I booked my flights to Osaka ($670 return, a very good deal) and am in the process of organising accommodation with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stat.berkeley.edu/~tab/&#34;&gt;Tamara Broderick&lt;/a&gt;. I’m getting excited about catching up with the various people that I met at the BNP conference last year and it’s even more exciting to see their names on the list of people giving talks. Tamara will be talking about Beta processes and Sergio Bacallado is giving a talk alongside Sonia Petrone and Yee Whye Teh, two of the big names in Bayesian non-parametrics. A few QUT people are talking as well. Nicole White and Susanna Cramb will be talking about spatio-temporal disease modelling. One of my supervisors, Sama Low Choy, will be talking about combining subjective priors (expert elicitation) and another, Kerrie Mengersen, is organising that session and co-author on a few papers that are being presented by people in her BRAG group, as well as posters (such as mine). I’m also looking forward to seeing presentations on INLA, spatial modelling, non-parametric estimation and environmental modelling.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A mostly Fin(n)ish[ed] paper</title>
      <link>/./2012/05/09/a-mostly-finnished-paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 May 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/05/09/a-mostly-finnished-paper/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The paper I started with some collaborators in Finland (&lt;a href=&#34;https://tuhat.halvi.helsinki.fi/portal/en/persons/bjarke-moelgaard(74a8081d-a379-4e4b-9aff-e9b85bc98c78)/publications.html&#34;&gt;Bjarke Mølgaard&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rni.helsinki.fi/~jic/&#34;&gt;Jukka Corander&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.atm.helsinki.fi/~khameri/&#34;&gt;Kaarle Hämeri&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://tuhat.halvi.helsinki.fi/portal/en/persons/tareq-hussein(3aacf8e7-f431-41b0-9303-1abaf1897bf7)/publications.html?page=5&amp;amp;rendering=vancouver&#34;&gt;Tareq Hussein&lt;/a&gt;) almost a year ago is nearly done. It’s been nearly done a few times, but now all that remains is to do a little bit of model choice regarding the separability of the effects of meteorology on ultrafine particle number concentration. We’ve been using git to send the paper and code back and forth (well, Bjarke and I have) and I’ve found that to be a really simple way of collaboratively writing code and a paper. To see the changes made, one need only look at the commit details. Much nicer than using tracked changes in Word and emailing a bunch of versions of the same file back and forth and trying to do complicated merges of changes. I am really looking forward to submitting this paper, as it’s probably the most methodological work I’ll get out of my PhD (the other papers are largely applications of some novel techniques to the UPTECH project’s data). It’s quite a nice blending of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://tuhat.halvi.helsinki.fi/portal/en/publications/forecasting-sizefra(9c6ae07d-af34-4909-a4f9-d758bc7a4795).html&#34;&gt;work done by the Finnish authors previously&lt;/a&gt; [1] as part of Bjarke’s PhD and some of the ideas in my first paper [2]. While I don’t know that it will totally revolutionise atmospheric modelling (in the way that I’m sure we all hope it will), it’s quite a nice technique that increases the flexibility of the Generalised Additive Model and hopefully encourage anyone interested in doing Bayesian modelling with the GAM to stop using &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.uow.edu.au/~mwand/&#34;&gt;Matt Wand&lt;/a&gt;’s WinBUGS approach [3, 4]. To be clear, I find GAMs in WinBUGS particularly cumbersome to code given that WinBUGS doesn’t deal with matrix operations very well and the use of P-splines requires a lot of matrix operations. Having said that, though, Wand’s code is a nice intro to Bayesian splines where you don’t have to write your own MCMC sampler. I just think it has some limitations that are not easily overcome. I’d like to present this to a statistics conference but it wasn’t anywhere near ready enough to demonstrate at ISBA 2012 when I was submitting an abstract. [1] B. Mølgaard, T. Hussein, J. Corander, K. Hämeri, Forecasting size-fractionated particle number concentrations in the urban atmosphere, Atmospheric Environment, Volume 46, January 2012, Pages 155-163, ISSN 1352-2310, 10.1016/j.atmosenv.2011.10.004. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1352231011010491&#34;&gt;ScienceDirect&lt;/a&gt; [2] S. Clifford, S. Low Choy, T. Hussein, K. Mengersen, L. Morawska, Using the Generalised Additive Model to model the particle number count of ultrafine particles, Atmospheric Environment, Volume 45, Issue 32, October 2011, Pages 5934-5945, ISSN 1352-2310, 10.1016/j.atmosenv.2011.05.004. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1352231011004766&#34;&gt;ScienceDirect&lt;/a&gt; [3] C. M. Crainiceanu, D. Ruppert. M. P. Wand, Bayesian Analysis for Penalized Spline Regression Using WinBUGS, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jstatsoft.org/v14/i14/&#34;&gt;Journal of Statistical Software, Volume 14, Issue 14, September 2005&lt;/a&gt;. [4] J. K. Marley, M. P. Wand, Non-Standard Semiparametric Regression via BRugs, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jstatsoft.org/v37/i05&#34;&gt;Journal of Statistical Software, Volume 37, Issue 5, November 2010&lt;/a&gt;. P.S. I apologise for the awful pun, but &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Micallef_P(r)ogram(me)&#34;&gt;Shaun Micallef&lt;/a&gt; has been on my mind recently.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dear Mr Supercomputer</title>
      <link>/./2012/04/17/dear-mr-supercomputer/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Apr 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/04/17/dear-mr-supercomputer/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;After ensuring that my colleagues were pushing their results to our git repository it’s now all steam ahead on this Finnish paper. I’ve got my MATLAB code running on the QUT supercomputer right now. It’s all very exciting watching it go and not run out of memory. Hopefully I can get these results sorted, do some model comparison, plotting and then send the document around for some final drafting within the next two or three weeks (the bulk of the theory section of the paper is finished). It would’ve been nice to be able to present this work at ISBA but I think I’d rather talk about the applied paper that discusses the spatio-temporal trends from the UPTECH project.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Christian Robert coming to Australia</title>
      <link>/./2012/03/20/christian-robert-coming-to-australia/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Mar 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/03/20/christian-robert-coming-to-australia/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One statistician whose blog I follow, Christian Robert (silent &lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt;), is &lt;a href=&#34;http://xianblog.wordpress.com/2012/03/20/amsi-lecturer/&#34;&gt;coming to Australia&lt;/a&gt; later in the year. Far from being just a blogging statistician, Robert is Professor of Statistics at the University of Paris Dauphine and does a lot of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ceremade.dauphine.fr/~xian/research.html&#34;&gt;interesting research&lt;/a&gt; in a variety of fields related to statistical modelling, statistical theory and computation. Some of Robert’s most recent work includes Approximate Bayesian Computation, on which some of Tony Pettitt’s students and post-docs at QUT (where Robert is an Adjunct Professor, and I wonder how long he’ll stick around here) are working. Robert will be speaking at the Australian Statistics Conference and then doing a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amsi.org.au/research-a-higher-education/rhenews/828-prof-christian-robert-lecture-tour&#34;&gt;speaking tour&lt;/a&gt; for the Australian Mathematical Sciences Institute. I’ll be going along when he’s in Brisbane but will miss him at ASC2012. Robert will be speaking on the Monday prior to the main ISBA 2012 conference and will cover advances and questions in ABC, so I still might get the chance to see him and talk to him before his speaking tour.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ISBA 2012 update</title>
      <link>/./2012/03/13/isba-2012-update/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Mar 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/03/13/isba-2012-update/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I got a very exciting email this morning as I was getting my morning coffee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dear Sam Clifford, We are very pleased to inform you that you have been selected as a recipient of a Junior Travel Award for attending the ISBA 2012 World Meeting! The amount of the Award is $300 (in US dollars) and is provided by funds from the Japanese Ministry of Education, Science, Sports, Culture and Technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;US$300 will pay for most of the conference registration if I register early as a PhD student. I’m drafting a budget now to check how much I’ll have to pay for accommodation, flights, etc. and will check how much money’s left in my IHBI student allocation and check if the new Science and Engineering Faculty will chip in a bit to help send me overseas. This is really thrilling news. I will get a chance to present my statistics work to statisticians, catch up with some of the people I met at the 8th Bayesian Nonparametrics workshop, meet some more early career statisticians, and find some academics working on similar projects who might be looking for postdocs in a year and a bit. My abstract is available &lt;a href=&#34;http://bayesian.org/node/2915&#34;&gt;online&lt;/a&gt; if you’re interested in Bayesian spatio-temporal modelling of data from a split panel design. I’ve got an old friend in Osaka who I should really catch up with. Osaka’s the nearest international airport to Kyoto and it’s an hour on the train. There’s a weekend before the conference starts, so I can probably afford to organise to see him and his wife prior to the conference.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ISBA 2012</title>
      <link>/./2012/02/29/isba-2012/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Feb 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/02/29/isba-2012/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve just submitted a poster abstract and travel support grant application for the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www2.e.u-tokyo.ac.jp/~isba2012/&#34;&gt;ISBA 2012&lt;/a&gt; World Meeting, “Bayesian spatio-temporal modelling of ultrafine particle number concentration from a panel design” and is a nice overview of the modelling involved in the UPTECH project that we’re running at ILAQH. It’s based on the second paper that will comprise my PhD (still in prep but coming along well) and discusses quantifying temporal trends at multiple sites. I’ve had a few breakthroughs with the code recently and wish that I had’ve had them towards the end of last year so I could submit an abstract for a paper. The travel support grant for ISBA required an extended abstract and I think it’d make a good presented paper but contributed session proposals closed a &lt;em&gt;long&lt;/em&gt; time ago. I’d love to go to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sapmea.asn.au/conventions/asc2012/index.html&#34;&gt;ASC 2012&lt;/a&gt; and present this stuff there but &lt;a href=&#34;http://hb2012.org/&#34;&gt;Healthy Buildings&lt;/a&gt; is on the same week (and I’m on the Student Program Committee).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
