<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
      <title>Data Mining on Sam Clifford </title>
    <link>/./tags/data-mining/</link>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
    <updated>2012-10-16 00:00:00 &#43;0000 UTC</updated>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research position with QUT&#39;s Applied Data Mining group</title>
      <link>/./2012/10/16/research-position-with-quts-applied-data-mining-group/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Oct 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/10/16/research-position-with-quts-applied-data-mining-group/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.applieddatamining.info/&#34;&gt;Applied Data Mining group&lt;/a&gt; has an opening for a one year position as a research officer with the group, working on topics in data mining and machine learning (which appears to be a less rigorous Bayesian non-parametrics). So if you or someone you know is finishing a PhD in statistics, machine learning or computer science and knows how to do scientific computation/data mining for big data and wouldn’t mind working in lovely, subtropical Brisbane, Australia for a year, email &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:r.nayak@qut.edu.au&#34;&gt;Associate Professor Richi Nayak&lt;/a&gt; this week. Some selection criteria are under the cut. The successful application should have:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Completed the PhD (or nearly completed) with success as evidenced by publications in proceedings of important conferences and journals in the field of machine learning/ data mining;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Acquired a profound knowledge and practical experience in machine learning, data mining and information retrieval; experience with Big Data is an advantage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Good programming skills (e.g., Java, C++, MATLAB, Python);&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Experience with data mining tools such as WEKA, SAS, MSQLServer;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Excellent English language skills (written and spoken);&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Good communication skills especially for interacting with industry partners;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The capability to work independently and in a team;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
