<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
      <title>Biostatistics on Sam Clifford </title>
    <link>/./tags/biostatistics/</link>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
    <updated>2014-07-02 00:00:00 &#43;0000 UTC</updated>
    
    <item>
      <title>Posterior samples</title>
      <link>/./2014/07/02/posterior-samples/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Jul 2014 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2014/07/02/posterior-samples/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;ARC Discovery Projects have been returned to their authors, and we are putting our responses together for the rejoinders. Interesting to see that we got a comment suggesting that we use the less restrictive CC-by instead of CC-by-nc-sa as we’d suggested. We weren’t successful in our Linkage Project applications, which is disappointing as they were interesting projects (well, we thought so). Continuing to bring research funding in is an ongoing struggle for all research groups and I feel it’s only going to get harder as the new federal government’s research priorities appear to be more aligned to medical science that delivers treatments than to our group’s traditional strengths. SEB113 is pretty much completely over for the semester, with marks having been entered for almost every student. Overall I think the students did fairly well. We had some issues with the timetable this semester. Ideally, we’d like the Lecture, then all of the computer labs, then all of the workshops, so that we can introduce a statistical idea, show the code and then apply the idea and code in a group setting. Next semester, we have the lecture followed immediately by the workshops with the computer labs dotted throughout the remainder of the week. This has provided us with an opportunity to try some semi-flipped classroom ideas, where students are able/expected to do the computer lab at home at their own pace rather than watch a tutor explain it one line at a time at the front of a computer lab. I’m teaching part of a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.eventbrite.com.au/e/r-statistical-language-for-air-pollution-epidemiology-tickets-12043581677&#34;&gt;two day course&lt;/a&gt; on the use of R in air pollution epidemiology. My part will introduce Bayesian statistics with a brief overview, a discussion about prior distributions as a means of encoding &lt;em&gt;a priori&lt;/em&gt; beliefs about model parameters, and discuss the use of Bayesian hierarchical modelling (as opposed to more traditional ANOVA techniques) as a way of making the most of the data that’s been collected. The other two presenters are &lt;a href=&#34;http://researchers.uq.edu.au/researcher/2181&#34;&gt;Dr Peter Baker&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://researchers.uq.edu.au/researcher/2530&#34;&gt;Dr Yuming Guo&lt;/a&gt;. The course is being run by the CAR-CRE, who partially fund my postdoctoral fellowship. I had meant to post this back when they were doing the rounds, but there’s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.tylervigen.com/&#34;&gt;a bunch of plots&lt;/a&gt; that attempt to show that correlation isn’t causation and that spurious correlations exist in large data sets. &lt;a href=&#34;https://tom-christie.github.io/articles/correlation/&#34;&gt;Tom Christie has responded&lt;/a&gt; to this by going over the fact that correlation in time series isn’t as simple as in the case of independent, identically distributed data. One should be careful that one’s criticism of bad statistics is itself founded on good statistics.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Coursera courses on statistics</title>
      <link>/./2013/11/11/coursera-courses-on-statistics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Nov 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2013/11/11/coursera-courses-on-statistics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height:1.714285714;font-size:1rem;&#34;&gt;I was looking into Coursera courses for a colleague who wants their postgrad students to have a stronger background in statistics. These students are coming from a background of having done science but not necessarily taken any mathematics or statistics electives in a while. It’d be good for them to learn R for their data analysis, too, seeing as most other statistics packages cost money and Excel, while readily available within universities and other research laboratories, is utterly terrible for proper data analysis.&lt;/span&gt; I managed to find the following courses which look relevant to the students and perhaps might even be good for any SEB113 students seeking to consolidate their statistical knowledge. This may also be relevant for current researchers looking to refamiliarise themselves with statistics and learn a good software package while they’re at it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.coursera.org/course/biostats&#34;&gt;Mathematical Biostatistics Boot Camp 1&lt;/a&gt;. Starting November 18 2013 and running for seven weeks. This requires some knowledge of calculus but looks like a really good course. Uses R.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.coursera.org/course/compdata&#34;&gt;Computing for Data Analysis&lt;/a&gt;. Starting January 6 2014 and running for four weeks. Uses R.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.coursera.org/course/statreasoning&#34;&gt;Statistical Reasoning for Public Health: Estimation, Inference, &amp;amp; Interpretation&lt;/a&gt;. Starting January 21 2013 and running for eight weeks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.coursera.org/course/statistics&#34;&gt;Data Analysis and Statistical Inference&lt;/a&gt;. Starting February 17 2013 and running for ten weeks. Uses R.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These courses are all free and some of them provide you with a statement of accomplishment upon successful completion, which could be a useful addition to your CV if you want to show prospective employers that you’re enthusiastic about learning and applying statistics. Edit: there’s also &lt;a href=&#34;https://novoed.com/numbers-life-quantway&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; “Numbers for Life” from Novo Ed. Johns Hopkins’ Open Courseware has the following neat courses:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://ocw.jhsph.edu/index.cfm/go/viewCourse/course/introbiostats/coursePage/index/&#34;&gt;Introduction to Biostatistics&lt;/a&gt;. This is a bit like if SEB113 focussed on tests rather than models.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://ocw.jhsph.edu/index.cfm/go/viewCourse/course/BiostatisticsLectureSeries05/coursePage/index/&#34;&gt;Biostatistics Lecture Series&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height:1.714285714;font-size:1rem;&#34;&gt;. A discussion not so much about statistics but the way statistics is practised.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height:1.714285714;font-size:1rem;&#34;&gt;Methods in Biostatistics&lt;/span&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://ocw.jhsph.edu/index.cfm/go/viewCourse/course/MethodsInBiostatisticsI/coursePage/index/&#34;&gt;I&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;line-height:1.714285714;font-size:1rem;&#34;&gt;and&lt;/span&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://ocw.jhsph.edu/index.cfm/go/viewCourse/course/methodsinbiostatisticsii/coursePage/index/&#34;&gt;II&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height:1.714285714;font-size:1rem;&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height:1.714285714;font-size:1rem;&#34;&gt;Statistics for Laboratory Scientists&lt;/span&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://ocw.jhsph.edu/index.cfm/go/viewCourse/course/StatisticsLaboratoryScientistsI/coursePage/index/&#34;&gt;I&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;line-height:1.714285714;font-size:1rem;&#34;&gt;and&lt;/span&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://ocw.jhsph.edu/index.cfm/go/viewCourse/course/statisticslaboratoryscientistsii/coursePage/index/&#34;&gt;II&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height:1.714285714;font-size:1rem;&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://ocw.jhsph.edu/index.cfm/go/viewCourse/course/EssentialsProbabilityStatisticalInference/coursePage/index/&#34;&gt;Essentials of Probability and Statistical Inference IV&lt;/a&gt;. GAMs, CARTs, neural networks. Good for postgrad level statisticians.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ben Fitzpatrick also introduced me to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lynda.com/&#34;&gt;lynda&lt;/a&gt;, which has a few short courses on statistics and R.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Posterior samples</title>
      <link>/./2013/10/10/posterior-samples/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2013/10/10/posterior-samples/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Open Access publishing is an exciting new development but like any new industry there are those who would seek to unethically make a quick fortune by providing a sub-par service. &lt;em&gt;Science&lt;/em&gt; did some research into this by submitting a fake article with a number of glaring errors (such as non-existent institutions) in it to a number of journals around the world to see who’d accept it. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.npr.org/blogs/health/2013/10/03/228859954/some-online-journals-will-publish-fake-science-for-a-fee?ft=1&amp;amp;f=1001&#34;&gt;The results are quite interesting&lt;/a&gt;. I know of a few instances of work published in a respectable journal being plagiarised and published in one of these scam journals and one case where the authors hastily retracted their submission once they found out the journal wasn’t anywhere near as prestigious as the editors made out. I support the goals of Open Access and web-based publication but be careful. I’ve been poking around the QUT Wiki looking for information on graduation. In the Higher Degree Research portal there’s a link to a brilliant article (three years old) on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.timeshighereducation.co.uk/news/how-not-to-write-a-phd-thesis/410208.article&#34;&gt;how not to write a thesis&lt;/a&gt;. Probably good advice for any PhD student looking to graduate sooner rather than later. Elizabeth C. Matsui has been working with Roger Peng for several years; she has &lt;a href=&#34;http://simplystatistics.org/2013/10/08/the-care-and-feeding-of-the-biostatistician/&#34;&gt;some advice on how to cultivate a successful relationship with the biostatistician&lt;/a&gt; you’ve brought on to your medical science project. I think some of these could be adapted to be more general to cover dealing with statisticians. One of the biggest things I could add here is that you need to recognise that asking someone to “help with the statistics” means dedicating some serious time and effort to figuring out a conceptual model (which will be converted into a quantitative model) that addresses the scientific questions you wish to ask. Asking a statistician to “calculate the correlations” or even more broadly “do the statistics” is like asking a scientist to just “run an experiment” or “do the science”. These things all take time, energy and communication. Further to this, don’t just ask for p-values if you’re dealing with a statistician. P-values represent some probabilistic statement, such as “What is the probability of seeing a test statistic at least as extreme as this if the true value of the parameter was zero?”. Sure, you can do simple tests like ANOVA or Chi-Squared goodness of fit but the real value in working with a statistician is being able to develop models that represent assumptions about the data and then assessing whether those assumptions are justified and looking at the inferences that they provide. As my unit co-ordinator for SEB113 pointed out to me the other day, default hypothesis tests of H&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt;: β = 0 at a 5% significance level may not always be sensible and may not even answer the question you’re interested in answering. And finally here’s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QPKKQnijnsM&#34;&gt;a video that’s almost a year old&lt;/a&gt; that shows a very interesting case of eliciting a distribution from the American public about what they perceive the distribution of wealth in their country is and what they think it is. Turns out the ideal is as far away from the perception as the perception is from the reality.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
