<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
      <title>Eclipse on Sam Clifford </title>
    <link>/./tags/eclipse/</link>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
    <updated>2012-12-11 00:00:00 &#43;0000 UTC</updated>
    
    <item>
      <title>Posterior samples</title>
      <link>/./2012/12/11/posterior-samples/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Dec 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/12/11/posterior-samples/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;line-height:12px;&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.statisticsblog.com/2012/12/information-graphics/&#34;&gt;Nice infographic of Mars missions&lt;/a&gt; showing all attempts and planned attempts&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As much as I love using .csv files to send data back and forth, especially on GitHub, apparently I should &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.win-vector.com/blog/2012/12/pleases-stop-using-excel-like-formats-to-exchange-data/&#34;&gt;stop using Excel-like files to exchange data&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are some really lovely visualisations of quite profound and complex scientific ideas among &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wired.com/wiredscience/2012/12/science-figures-2012/&#34;&gt;The best scientific figures of 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As someone who espouses the beauty of LaTeX and &lt;a href=&#34;http://samclifford.info/2012/08/12/credibility-of-information-given-font-choice/&#34;&gt;the importance of proper font choice&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://typeanatomy.com/&#34;&gt;The Anatomy of Type&lt;/a&gt; is a book I’m considering buying. Maybe I should get it for my sister for Christmas.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://sydneypadua.com/2dgoggles/lovelace-the-origin-2/&#34;&gt;A charming comic with an origin story for Ada Lovelace&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, yes, I do plan on writing more about what I’m actually doing! I’m just working on thesis stuff a lot and trying to organise my final seminar. I’ve got some thoughts on presentations that I’m writing up, so stay tuned. One more &lt;a href=&#34;http://exp.lore.com/post/37688902608/60-seconds-of-awe-in-this-timelapse-of-the&#34;&gt;* Stunning time lapse photography of the eclipse.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2012 Eclipse photos</title>
      <link>/./2012/11/14/2012-eclipse-photos/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Nov 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/11/14/2012-eclipse-photos/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On Wednesday 14 November 2012 a solar eclipse was partially viewable in Brisbane, Australia. We only got 84% coverage (100% in Cairns). The eclipse lasted from about 6-8 am. &lt;a href=&#34;http://conidialcoleopticide.wordpress.com/&#34;&gt;Weiss&lt;/a&gt; made a viewing tube and projection sheet and we took a camera but didn’t get any good photos as we didn’t have a solar film or some other means of removing most of the light from the sun (other than allowing the moon to partially obscure it). Click the pictures for the bigger versions. [caption id=“attachment_635” align=“aligncenter” width=“225”][&lt;img src=&#34;img_1155.jpg?w=225&#34; title=&#34;Weiss using the viewing tube&#34; /&gt;](&lt;a href=&#34;http://samcliffordinfo.files.wordpress.com/2012/11/img_1155.jpg&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;http://samcliffordinfo.files.wordpress.com/2012/11/img_1155.jpg&lt;/a&gt;) Weiss using the viewing tube[/caption] [caption id=“attachment_634” align=“aligncenter” width=“225”]&lt;a href=&#34;http://samcliffordinfo.files.wordpress.com/2012/11/img_1153.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;img_1153.jpg?w=225&#34; title=&#34;Projection on the sheet&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Projection on the sheet[/caption] [caption id=“attachment_633” align=“aligncenter” width=“225”]&lt;a href=&#34;http://samcliffordinfo.files.wordpress.com/2012/11/img_1152.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;img_1152.jpg?w=225&#34; title=&#34;Projection from a pinhole in a sheet on to another sheet. Tiny little sun.&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Projection from a pinhole in a sheet on to another sheet. Tiny little sun.[/caption] [caption id=“attachment_632” align=“aligncenter” width=“225”]&lt;a href=&#34;http://samcliffordinfo.files.wordpress.com/2012/11/img_1151.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;img_1151.jpg?w=225&#34; title=&#34;Looking through the tube at the sun&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Looking through the tube at the sun[/caption] [caption id=“attachment_631” align=“aligncenter” width=“225”]&lt;a href=&#34;http://samcliffordinfo.files.wordpress.com/2012/11/img_1150.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;img_1150.jpg?w=225&#34; title=&#34;Looking through the tube at the sun&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Looking through the tube at the sun[/caption] [caption id=“attachment_630” align=“aligncenter” width=“225”]&lt;a href=&#34;http://samcliffordinfo.files.wordpress.com/2012/11/img_1149.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;img_1149.jpg?w=225&#34; title=&#34;Weiss taking a segment off the tube to make sure the ray hits the viewer&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Weiss taking a segment off the tube to make sure the ray hits the viewer[/caption] I remember watching the transit of Venus earlier from QUT. The Physics discipline had some solar filter sunglasses that looked like 3D glasses and had also set up some telescopes with solar film over the lens to give a closer look at the rare transit. I went downstairs to see the optics people yesterday but they didn’t have anything that they could give me. While astronomy’s not a field I’m interested in as an academic pursuit, it’s still an amazing branch of science that allows us to know a lot about the universe in which we live. I know a handful of people who made the trek to Cairns to see the total eclipse and I’m sure they got some wonderful shots. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.abc.net.au/local/stories/2012/11/13/3631638.htm&#34;&gt;Apparently something like 60,000 people made the trip&lt;/a&gt;. Probably my fondest astronomy memory is going out with my youngest brother to a trip organised by the CSIRO education unit (Brisbane). We spent an evening in Indooroopilly looking up at the stars and planets, ably led by one of the science educators and his collection of telescopes. Some of the telescopes were programmable so you could track objects; one of his telescopes was a collaborative project with a group of high school students who built a working telescope out of wood, glass and mirrors. Space is pretty cool. That humans have managed to explore so much of it from our vantage point here on Earth is awesome. That we have detected cosmic background radiation left over from the Big Bang is astonishing. That we have put men on the moon, sent satellites out past the planets of our own solar system and have put two rovers (mobile science labs, basically) on Mars blows my mind.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Posterior samples</title>
      <link>/./2012/11/14/posterior-samples/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Nov 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/11/14/posterior-samples/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://xkcd.com/1133/&#34;&gt;Randall Munroe explains Saturn V using only the thousand most commonly used English words, and it’s hilarious&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://andrewgelman.com/2012/11/16808/#comment-109366&#34;&gt;Speaking of Randall Munroe, here’s his response to Gelman’s criticism of Munroe’s Bayesian vs Frequentist comic&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://simplystatistics.org/post/35563800852/some-thoughts-on-teaching-r-to-50-000-students&#34;&gt;Some (but not my) thoughts on teaching R to 50,000 students&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.abc.net.au/local/stories/2012/11/13/3631638.htm&#34;&gt;There was an eclipse visible in Australia on the morning of November 14 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://musicmachinery.com/2012/11/12/the-infinite-jukebox/&#34;&gt;It’s getting hammered at the moment, but The Infinite Jukebox analyses songs for similar phrases and builds a series of paths between similar sections so that you can have an infinitely long song.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Infinite Jukebox reminds me a bit about &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UqzVSvqXJYg&#34;&gt;Brian Eno’s work on generative systems&lt;/a&gt; for rule-based music. This in turn reminds me of Brian Eno’s album “Discreet Music”, which features an &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7-Vq4pmzMaE&#34;&gt;automatically played song and three re-arrangements of Pachelbel’s “Canon in D”.&lt;/a&gt; The album is designed to sit in the background and be fairly unobtrusive, but it’s hard not to notice the familiar phrases of “Canon in D”. I find this album good as background music at work. The generative systems video above takes me back to my undergraduate studies in mathematics, where we learned about &lt;a href=&#34;http://staff.qut.edu.au/staff/malletd/&#34;&gt;mathematical modelling using cellular automata&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
