<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
      <title>Communication on Sam Clifford </title>
    <link>/./tags/communication/</link>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
    <updated>2013-12-17 00:00:00 &#43;0000 UTC</updated>
    
    <item>
      <title>Posterior samples</title>
      <link>/./2013/12/17/posterior-samples/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2013/12/17/posterior-samples/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today’s collection of links have the loose theme of engagement between the public and science. Grist, an environmental news service I used to read every single day, have an &lt;a href=&#34;http://grist.org/climate-energy/reddits-science-forum-banned-climate-deniers-why-dont-all-newspapers-do-the-same/&#34;&gt;interesting article&lt;/a&gt; about how on reddit the science subreddit has banned out and out climate denial (more accurately: conspiracy theories) from their discussion. The author, a moderator of the subreddit, wonders why mainstream news services don’t just do the same given that the science is in. If you’re unconvinced about the science, or are convinced that it’s right but are unsure about the specifics, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.npr.org/blogs/13.7/2013/12/16/251437395/global-warming-explained-in-about-a-minute&#34;&gt;NPR has a short article and animation&lt;/a&gt; about the mechanisms of global warming. The authors raise the point that the general public find science a bit daunting, particularly when it’s something as complex as global climate systems. Charlotte Pezaro, a PhD student at the University of Queensland, is &lt;a href=&#34;http://cpezaro.wordpress.com/2013/12/17/making-decisions-in-personally-relevant-contexts-of-science/&#34;&gt;doing research&lt;/a&gt; into how science education plays a role in preparing people to evaluate evidence rather than just preparing them to do science or to memorise scientific facts. Pezaro argues that more than this, a focus of science education should be to develop scientific literacy in the making of decisions in a personally relevant context of science, such as health, nutrition and the use of technologies.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Web presence</title>
      <link>/./2013/12/13/web-presence/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2013/12/13/web-presence/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I first met the friend who’s going to try learning R over the summer by way of a blog that she and a mutual friend of ours ran way back in the day. She recently posted a link to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.theguardian.com/technology/2013/dec/11/guardian-10-year-blog-project&#34;&gt;a Guardian article&lt;/a&gt; about cringing at the blogs we (as a society) had ten years ago and mused a bit on her old group blog. Ten years ago I was being introduced to Livejournal by a fellow engineering student at QUT but as far back as 2000 I was dabbling in blogging and writing webpages. Fed up with some of the attitudes at our high school, a friend and I had joined a webring, where we wrote terrible poetry, passable HTML/CSS and banal updates about the coding of our respective webpages. I’m definitely not going to post a link and I’m glad I never used my name on that site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ten years ago (almost to the day, according to the source) the first version of the ILAQH website went live. If you’re reading this beyond Monday 16 you may not be able to see what I can see now. Below is a screen grab of what I see.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://samcliffordinfo.files.wordpress.com/2013/12/ilaqh.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;ilaqh.png?w=625&#34; title=&#34;ILAQH website 2003-2013&#34; alt=&#34;ilaqh&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The website seems to have not had a design refresh in the last ten years, on account of various factors to do with QUT’s IT policies, not having a postdoc who’s also a professional web designer, etc. ILAQH has been around in one form or another since 1995, which means that as much as I cringe looking at the layout of our old site it could have been much worse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We now have &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.qut.edu.au/research/our-research/institutes-centres-and-research-groups/international-laboratory-for-air-quality-and-health&#34;&gt;a new website&lt;/a&gt; that thematically fits with the rest of QUT’s web presence and is much more appropriate for a university research group who publish good quality work in the top journals in their field, have organised an international conference recently, and have a string of ARC Discovery grant successes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clearly a good web presence is important for research groups but it’s increasingly becoming more important for individual researchers. It’s a way to connect with potential employers, students, colleagues, etc. and a high quality site can really show what sets you apart from others. I’m trying to convince some of the other people at my sort of academic level to get their own websites so that they’re easily searchable online and have a page that’s separate from any university affiliation but also not tied to any one social network (not even the professional ones like &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Samuel_Clifford/&#34;&gt;ResearchGate&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;http://lnkd.in/pWZfxy&#34;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Out of all the blogs and web presences I’ve had, I’m definitely proudest of this one and doubt that in ten years time I’ll be looking back at it and cringing. I’m not a professional web developer, just someone who’s got a Wordpress account and a bit of experience mucking around with software. Any researcher has the skills required to come up with a website for themselves and their research.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Science as storytelling</title>
      <link>/./2013/11/06/science-as-storytelling/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2013/11/06/science-as-storytelling/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I used to not be a very confident public speaker. I remember getting up at a community meeting in 2007 and stammering some words out to a group of residents; it was a disaster. Motivated for the desire for some money to augment my Youth Allowance payments I applied to be a tutor with the School of Mathematics (QUT) during my final years of undergrad and found that I became a bit better at talking to people. My Honours seminar was still a nervous affair but it was much less disastrous than the community meeting. After Honours I had a job teaching mathematics to a group of video game programmers, developing the curriculum to suit their needs and interests and it’s here that I became far more comfortable with speaking. I was coming up with my own material and delivering it to people who I knew were interested in it. That’s a world away from teaching university students, where many may not see the point in learning what I’m teaching. This is especially the case in service mathematics and statistics units. During my PhD studies I got interested in improvised theatre as a creative alternative to the mathematics, statistics and science that was my day. My reputation as someone not afraid to get up in front of 100 people and perform lead to my being asked by one of my PhD supervisors if I’d like to be a tutor in the brand new SEB113 course. Teaching students how to use R for their data analysis? Of course I’m interested! After the end of a very enjoyable, if somewhat disjointed, semester I was asked if I’d consider lecturing the smaller second semester re-run. I jumped at the chance. Restructuring the subject from the way it was run in first semester meant we could focus on the way the material flowed and see if we could smooth out some of the jumps in style, making the unit more consistent and easier to understand. We had to do a lot of work rejigging the slides, writing new workshops and computer laboratory worksheets to accommodate the use of ggplot rather than a combination of base, lattice and MASS graphics. The result was a subject that introduces a diverse list of topics in a much more sensible manner:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Measurement and variation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Visualisation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Summary statistics and confidence intervals&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Inference and sample size, hypothesis tests&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Regression lines of best fit&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Regression with a categorical variable&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Non-linear regression based on process models&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Multivariate summary statistics and regression&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mathematical modelling of process models&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Linear algebra, including the guts of how linear regression works&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Writing scientifically, revisiting the scientific method&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Writing about numbers, conditional probability for understanding hypothesis tests&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Revisiting visualisation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An introduction to advanced quantitative methods&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It became apparent around week 8-9 that what we were doing was telling a story of how to get from calculating means to understanding how to develop a model to either model a process or emulate that process. The discussions about writing scientifically became about how the quantitative reports were telling a story. The first step, the introduction, is like meeting the characters for the first time and understanding their relationships with each other. As we move through the methods and analysis we see the action of the story unfold. The conclusion is the consequences of the action and by relating the analysis back to the motivating aim we can see the arc of the story and understand more about these characters. Now that the teaching is over and the marking of the quantitative workbooks is coming to a close, I’ve got a bit more space in my head to process my thoughts about improvisation and storytelling (we do a weekly show and I’m still doing workshops on the weekend). I’ve picked up a book on my Kindle by scientist-turned-filmmaker Randy Olson, entitled “&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00FASMHP8/ref=oh_d__o00_details_o00__i00?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;psc=1&#34;&gt;Connection: Hollywood Storytelling meets Critical Thinking&lt;/a&gt;”. Olson’s book is all about how any intellectual topic can be made interesting and accessible by treating its presentation as telling a story. He states that we, as humans, engage with stories far more than we do with dry information as we feel stories it in our hearts, guts and sexual organs rather than just in our brains. Not only is the communication of scientific results storytelling but lecturing is storytelling. I’ve thought this semester that lecturing is definitely a style of performance, but the idea that the topics in a unit should follow an arc and tell a unified story means that part of the academic’s role is telling a story in the classroom. For me, that means that elements of comedy, pantomime and suspense make their way into my lectures. Storytelling in science is a very interesting topic and I look forward to making my way through the remainder of the book over the end of year break, ready to start a new semester with a revised narrative arc and better storyboarding, maybe even a few new characters.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Talks</title>
      <link>/./2013/10/11/talks/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2013/10/11/talks/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I’m not sure if I’ve discussed this before but there’s a huge difference in culture between the two research groups I’m involved with. ILAQH (physics) meets once every four to six months at the moment and BRAG (statistics) meets fortnightly. At the fortnightly meetings we spend a few minutes having a quick check-in around the room where we discuss what we’ve been up to for the last two weeks (any papers published, talks given, new research plans) and then someone will give a talk on a topic that is within a semester-long theme. The theme last semester was visualisation, now we’re moving on to the analysis of big data. ILAQH, by contrast, meets at a frequency that doesn’t really facilitate a catch-up. Instead, any big developments in the big projects are discussed and visitors are welcomed and/or farewelled appropriately. Both meetings serve different purposes in different ways. One of the biggest benefits of the BRAG fortnightly meetings is that PhD students get a lot of practice giving talks. You’re almost expected to give a talk once a semester, and students are encouraged to give practice talks for the milestones of their PhD candidature (confirmation at 12 months, final seminar when completed). Given that it’s typically two and a half years between confirmation and the final seminar, being expected to give a talk every few months means that you get practice at talking and that the practice is somewhat regular. This will be especially important for ILAQH students as an overwhelming majority of our students are not native English speakers. Getting regular practice at academic speaking will help when it comes to final seminars. I’ve spoken to Lidia Morawska (Director of ILAQH) about setting up such a system and she thinks it’s a good idea. Now I’ve just got to check that the rest of the group sees it as valuable and then put the legwork in to get it off the ground (organise a time, book a room, etc.).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>BRAG for 2013</title>
      <link>/./2013/02/07/brag-for-2013/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Feb 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2013/02/07/brag-for-2013/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The fornightly meetings for my stats group, BRAG, started up again two weeks ago and I’ve put my hand up to chair the meetings. I totally flubbed it this morning by forgetting we’d switched the start times to 10.30 instead of 11. Today’s meeting was less of a formal meeting and more of an exploration of QUT“s”&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thecube.qut.edu.au/&#34;&gt;The Cube&lt;/a&gt;“, a new resource provided in the Science and Engineering Faculty’s new building. [caption id=“attachment_781” align=“aligncenter” width=“300”][&lt;img src=&#34;cubit1.jpg?w=300&#34; alt=&#34;CubIT, a unique system at the Cube that allows the general public to collaborate with and access research content shared by QUT’s students and academics. Photo copyright QUT.&#34; /&gt;](&lt;a href=&#34;http://samcliffordinfo.files.wordpress.com/2013/02/cubit1.jpg&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;http://samcliffordinfo.files.wordpress.com/2013/02/cubit1.jpg&lt;/a&gt;) CubIT, a unique system at the Cube that allows the general public to collaborate with and access research content shared by QUT’s students and academics. Photo copyright QUT.[/caption] Marcus Rittenbruch showed us a bit about what CubIT is, how it works and what the plans are for the future. There are a bunch of touch screens that the public can interact with as part of The Cube, and CubIT is the system that allows you to use it. If you’re a QUT student or staff member you can &lt;a href=&#34;http://cubit.thecube.qut.edu.au/users/sign_in&#34;&gt;register an account&lt;/a&gt; and upload media (photos, text notes, video) through either the mobile web interface or the iPhone app. Then you swipe in using the card readers at the bottom of the screens and move your media around the screens, including dragging to the top bar so you can make a slideshow on the large non-touch screen. There are plans to include PDF and HTML support so you can run through presentation slides and refer to web pages when necessary. I think that’d be a pretty neat way to give a presentation. There’s a booking system which is yet to be made available online but when that’s up and running it’d be an interesting way to show potential collaborators what we can do. Over the next few meetings in BRAG we’ll be presenting on visualisation, similar to the computational talks that featured in the second half of last year. While not strictly Bayesian in nature, the talks will give examples of how to visualise different types of data and methods of analysis. I’ve put my hand up with Sama Low Choy to talk about some of the guiding principles of data visualisation that Tufte came up with. I know they’ve certainly helped when I’ve been writing papers and hopefully we can come up with a nice little talk that discusses the principles and gives some examples of good and bad graphs and discuss how we can apply the principles to make the graphs better. I’m very interested to see how others approach visualisation, particularly the common issues we have such as parameter summaries and then the specific issues such as visualising mixtures, high dimensional data, spatial information, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Infographics</title>
      <link>/./2012/08/28/infographics/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Aug 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/08/28/infographics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Kasia Piekut has written &lt;a href=&#34;http://mark-making.com/blog/27-communication/240-how-to-get-your-mind-around-infographic-design-and-data-visualisation&#34;&gt;an article on&lt;/a&gt; Mark Making about infographics and some of the most important things to remember. It’s accompanied by a cute infographic about infographics themselves. The potential to make high quality infographics is huge these days, as we have some very clever designers with very good software. But it’s important to remember that infographics aren’t just about pretty design but effectively communicating information in an accessible and entertaining manner. There are some pretty terrible infographics out there, where colour is used to pretty the graphs up without actually conveying information. I try to tell my coworkers to avoid the uninformative use of colour because people will look at a multicoloured graph and ask “What does this change of colour mean?” Often a table or simple plot will do in place of an infographic. As researchers we must resist the temptation to make our graphs so punchy and full of colour that we obscure the meaning of the data. Infographics are a tool for conveying information; we should be careful that we don’t end up with pictures for the sake of pictures. We should also be careful that we don’t end up with graphics that obscure the data and its implications. Edit: I don’t know that this is worthy of its own post so I’ll add it here. &lt;a href=&#34;http://themonkeycage.org/blog/2012/08/28/choices-in-graphing-parallel-time-series&#34;&gt;Andrew Gelman has blogged at The Monkey Cage&lt;/a&gt; about choosing plot styles and how different representations of the same data can be used to give the punchy dramatic message and then give that message a bit more context.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Credibility of information given font choice</title>
      <link>/./2012/08/12/credibility-of-information-given-font-choice/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Aug 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/08/12/credibility-of-information-given-font-choice/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Thanks to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://themonkeycage.org/blog/2012/08/11/potpourri-80&#34;&gt;Monkey Cage blog&lt;/a&gt; (a very good read if you’re a fan of statistics and politics as I am) I’ve come across &lt;a href=&#34;http://opinionator.blogs.nytimes.com/2012/08/08/hear-all-ye-people-hearken-o-earth/&#34;&gt;an opinion article&lt;/a&gt; on the New York Times’ page that discusses whether the font or handwriting style that is used to convey information has any impact on whether we believe that information. It’s worth a read, as is the follow up and the preceding article (an essay and a quiz). There’s a lot of really interesting stuff in there, but one that really leaps out is the ATLAS slides from the presentation about the Higgs Boson. Comic Sans is used to convey fun, light-heartedness, etc. and as far as I’m concerned it simply does not belong in academia. The article goes on to do some analysis of the previous article’s quiz and shows that Baskerville is the font with the most &lt;em&gt;gravitas&lt;/em&gt;. Rather than having me summarise the article here (it’s quite long) it’s probably better to just go and read it. If you’ve ever wondered about whether you should use a particular font (personally, Times New Roman is boring and Cambria is ugly) to convey a particular feeling in your article then this is food for thought. I use LaTeX to write papers and read a lot of papers typeset in LaTeX. As such, my eyes tend to see a lot of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Computer_Modern&#34;&gt;Computer Modern&lt;/a&gt;, which has a bit of a reputation as being an academic font. I wouldn’t publish a school newsletter in Computer Modern, of course, but for “serious” writing, CM is it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Science communication</title>
      <link>/./2012/07/22/science-communication/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Jul 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/07/22/science-communication/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A field within science that has been getting a little attention recently is science communication. Science can be hard to understand. Even if one is a scientist, attempting to come to terms with something outside your field can be very tricky. So if scientists have difficulty explaining their work to each other (try being a statistician talking to applied scientists) then what hope does the general public have in terms of understanding science? As an example, ask people about the significance of the CERN announcements a few weeks ago regarding the search for the Higgs boson. Apart from the awful slides that the ATLAS team presented, the slides by CMS were very information dense, overcrowded and undigestible. &lt;a href=&#34;http://themonkeycage.org/blog/2012/07/18/on-communicating-scientific-findings/&#34;&gt;Arthur Lupia puts the blame on the researchers&lt;/a&gt;. In a nice analogy about getting you and your lost friend out of the woods that you know well, Lupia’s main point is that there are two things you need to know to help your friend get out of the woods:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the woods (your field of work)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;where your friend is (what your audience know)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of communicating your results to your audience, it’s no good only being an expert; you also need to know what level of literacy your audience has when it comes to the topic. There are some academics who are quite good public speakers and give public lectures about both the science they are working on and the philosophy of science. I’ve seen Field’s medal winner &lt;a href=&#34;http://terrytao.wordpress.com/&#34;&gt;Terry Tao&lt;/a&gt; give a good public talk about science (mainly astrophysics) and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.griffith.edu.au/environment-planning-architecture/centre-environment-population-health/staff/ian-lowe&#34;&gt;Ian Lowe&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ies.unsw.edu.au/staff/mark.html&#34;&gt;Mark Diesendorf&lt;/a&gt; are also fantastic speakers, particularly about the issues surrounding climate change. I’d say that these people, all eminent scientists, are good readers of their audience. But people tend not to get their news and information from public seminars by eminent scientists who are good presenters, or even from television programs like PBS’s “&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/nova/&#34;&gt;Nova&lt;/a&gt;”. There are some rare exceptions, such as David Attenborough’s very popular documentaries about nature. Attenborough is a master entertainer and makes geology, zoology and botany very accessible. Part of this is that the natural world, plants and animals are much more concrete than abstract ideas of physics and chemistry and there’s also the fact that animals and plants can look pretty. A chemical, on the other hand, no matter how integral to life on earth, is often still just a solid, liquid or gas. Science reporting in the media is generally fairly poor, at least from my point of view as a statistician. Misinterpretation of relative risk, odds ratios, p values, “significance”, etc. abound. Our newspapers generally do not employ scientists or science communicators to write articles about scientific discoveries. &lt;a href=&#34;http://understandinguncertainty.org/10-best-practice-guidelines-reporting-science-health-stories&#34;&gt;One of the outcomes of the Leveson inquiry into the UK media is a list of guidelines for science reporting&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;State the source of the story - e.g. interview, conference, journal article, a survey from a charity or trade body, etc. - ideally with enough information for readers to look it up or a web link.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Specify the size and nature of the study - e.g. who/what were the subjects, how long did it last, what was tested or was it an observation? If space, mention the major limitations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When reporting a link between two things, indicate whether or not there is evidence that one causes the other.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Give a sense of the stage of the research - e.g. cells in a laboratory or trials in humans - and a realistic time-frame for any new treatment or technology.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On health risks, include the absolute risk whenever it is available in the press release or the research paper - i.e. if ‘cupcakes double cancer risk’ state the&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;outright risk of that cancer, with and without cupcakes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Especially on a story with public health implications, try to frame a new finding in the context of other evidence - e.g. does it reinforce or conflict with previous studies? If it attracts serious scientific concerns, they should not be ignored.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If space, quote both the researchers themselves and external sources with appropriate expertise. Be wary of scientists and press releases over-claiming for studies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Distinguish between findings and interpretation or extrapolation; don’t suggest health advice if none has been offered.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remember patients - don’t call something a ‘cure’ that is not a cure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Headlines should not mislead the reader about a story’s contents and quotation marks should not be used to dress up overstatement.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If these are adopted they will go some way to addressing what I see as the flaws in current science reporting. Even the Australian government’s ABC News sometimes publishes poor quality articles about new science. The ABC has done well in shows about science, particularly “Quantum”, hosted by mathematician/comedian/radio presenter Adam Spencer, and its replacement “Catalyst”. The online news team could probably do with some better science reporters. It’s all well and good to talk about a need for science communicators but how do we find them? How does one become one? The Australian National University has a &lt;a href=&#34;http://studyat.anu.edu.au/programs/7614XMSCOM;overview.html&#34;&gt;Masters of Science Communication&lt;/a&gt;. The course involves &lt;a href=&#34;http://studyat.anu.edu.au/interests/75&#34;&gt;subjects across a wide variety of topics&lt;/a&gt; such as the use of technology in communication, engagement with the public, teaching, ethics, etc. QUT is currently restructuring its Bachelor of Applied Science degree around a handful of majors and many coherent comajors, one of which is science communication. Introducing the ideas of science communication in undergrad is, in my mind, a good idea. Training our scientists to not just be good at chemistry, biology, mathematics, etc. but to be good at communicating their work will help the penetration of their work within their workplace. If the student goes on to postgraduate research then they will likely end up a good public speaker with expertise in a certain field. If the student exits academia after undergrad then they will be able to better make their case and improve the penetration of scientific ideas in their workplace.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
