<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
      <title>Healthy Buildings on Sam Clifford </title>
    <link>/./tags/healthy-buildings/</link>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
    <updated>2013-08-09 00:00:00 &#43;0000 UTC</updated>
    
    <item>
      <title>Conference posters and an accepted paper</title>
      <link>/./2013/08/09/conference-posters-and-an-accepted-paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Aug 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2013/08/09/conference-posters-and-an-accepted-paper/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Thomas Lumley &lt;a href=&#34;http://notstatschat.tumblr.com/post/57747270796/speed-sessions-at-jsm-2013&#34;&gt;has some thoughts&lt;/a&gt; on poster sessions at JSM 2013. Healthy Buildings 2012 had something I hadn’t seen before - poster presenters were given two minutes at the end of the technical session most relevant to their poster to describe the work they are presenting in the poster session immediately after the talk slot. This gave poster presenters a small taste of presenting at a conference without them needing to prepare a full talk. QUT’s Nano and Molecular Sciences discipline had a poster session during its one day symposium a few months ago and the posters were run off &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thecube.qut.edu.au/&#34;&gt;The Cube&lt;/a&gt;, which allowed people to zoom and rotate a static image of their poster (PDF preferred). Our group will have a few posters at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://eac2013.cz/&#34;&gt;European Aerosol Conference&lt;/a&gt; in a few weeks. Mandana Mazaheri and I have been discussing the issues of transporting posters back and forth internationally, including whether or not to print on cloth and the unwieldy nature of poster tubes. I am a big fan of mailing your poster home once it’s presented but a cloth poster can be folded up and put in your luggage and you can just give it a quick iron before presenting it. I’ve also seen way too many posters that are too busy and have gradient backgrounds. Hopefully by teaching SEB113 students about the principles of good visualisation of data QUT can produce graduates who know not to make ugly posters. &lt;a href=&#34;http://pubs.acs.org/doi/abs/10.1021/es4023706&#34;&gt;Our endotoxin paper got accepted in Environmental Science &amp;amp; Technology&lt;/a&gt; after a frantic couple of days of finalising amendments and responses to reviewer comments. This paper gave me a much better understanding of Bayesian hierarchical linear models and I’m very happy with how the paper turned out. The next step is to resubmit our fungus paper, which includes similar modelling but also uses a Multinomial model with Dirichlet prior to look at the proportions of different fungal genera across the UPTECH schools. There’s yet another paper looking at chemicals in floor dust which we’re also finalising that uses a similar methodology to the fungus paper but has its own subtleties due to some chemicals not being present across all schools.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Statistics Done Wrong</title>
      <link>/./2012/08/01/statistics-done-wrong/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Aug 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/08/01/statistics-done-wrong/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.refsmmat.com/&#34;&gt;Alex Reinhart&lt;/a&gt; has written a fantastic article entitled “&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.refsmmat.com/statistics/&#34;&gt;Statistics Done Wrong&lt;/a&gt;” which goes into a lot of the mistakes that scientists made when conducting experiments and performing data analysis. Reinhart is a 20 year old physics major who says that while science has embraced the use of statistics it hasn’t embraced statistics education, often allowing undergraduate students to complete a science degree without taking any statistics classes (it was possible to take a Bachelor of Applied Science at QUT without even taking the first year data analysis unit, you just had to be prepared to do first year chemistry, life sciences and introductory physical science). The article is very good and goes into problems of insufficient statistical power, misunderstandings as to what p values are and what significance is, pseudoreplication when you think you’re doing independent replication, and how big a sample to use. I am not as well versed in statistical design as I would like to be, particularly when working in a lab which does experimental science. One of my supervisors is very passionate about good design, and for good reason; if you design your experiment or observation campaign well you will have a more efficient data collection system, an easier job doing the data analysis and the power of your tests means that you can be more confident in your analysis. As dull as statistics seems to be for first year science students, I could see it being very valuable to run a course on how to set up an experiment, both from a statistical design point of view and what is required of them in their field, and perform data analysis. I don’t think we can expect experimentalists to become great statistical teachers, so it may require an amount of service teaching by statisticians within the science units, as an optional class on basic data analysis techniques doesn’t seem to cut it. I really enjoyed the article and think it’s a great follow up to &lt;a href=&#34;http://samclifford.info/2012/07/12/plenary-speech/&#34; title=&#34;Plenary speech&#34;&gt;what I was talking about at Healthy Buildings&lt;/a&gt;. The next step is to identify how we teach these things to science students in a way that they don’t switch off.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Where to start if you&#39;re going to revise statistics</title>
      <link>/./2012/07/13/where-to-start-if-youre-going-to-revise-statistics/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Jul 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/07/13/where-to-start-if-youre-going-to-revise-statistics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I’d like to think it was my plenary speech that has spurred this, but given that they didn’t see it I’m not sure that it was, but one of the academics in my lab has decided it’s time to refresh their statistical knowledge. I think this is great, because they got their PhD a long time ago and have probably been using the same statistical methods for at least the last ten years. The book they’ve decided to use is the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Schaums-Outline-Statistics-Murray-Spiegel/dp/0070602816&#34;&gt;Schaum’s Outline of Statistics&lt;/a&gt;. I’ve used books from this range before to revise linear algebra, differential equations, etc. and have even taught small courses (privately) based on the topics they cover and in the order they cover them. A flick through the book confirmed that it was full of frequentist testing and other similar statistical methods that I spent my talk saying were a good start but not the end of the analysis when writing a scientific paper. The book’s online summary says it covers the use of MINITAB. I’m glad to see that it discusses the use of software other than Excel to perform analysis but I recommend people use books in Springer’s “&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.springer.com/series/6991?detailsPage=titles&#34;&gt;Use R!&lt;/a&gt;” range because R is free (in terms of both speech and beer) and is much more flexible than MINITAB in terms of programming it and running different types of analysis. Where MINITAB is based on a point and click GUI, making it great for a first year statistics class where students may not be familiar with programming, R is driven by the command line and is more easily scripted. Learning to use R means giving yourself the opportunity to use the many &lt;a href=&#34;http://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/available_packages_by_name.html&#34;&gt;packages&lt;/a&gt; that extend its functionality. The books I’ve used in the Use R! range include &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.springer.com/statistics/computational+statistics/book/978-0-387-93836-3&#34;&gt;A Beginner’s Guide to R&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.springer.com/statistics/statistical+theory+and+methods/book/978-0-387-92297-3&#34;&gt;Bayesian Computation with R&lt;/a&gt;. While I’d definitely recommend these Use R! books, as they’re aimed at people wanting to use R to do better analysis, there are a few others that I’ve found incredibly useful. It’s important for me to point out that my background differs from my colleague’s so they may not find the books as relevant or accessible. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stat.columbia.edu/~gelman/book/&#34;&gt;Gelman et. al - Bayesian Data Analysis&lt;/a&gt;. Around my stats group, this book is called “The Bible”. It’s probably the best textbook I’ve come across. It’s full of information, tutorials, detailed descriptions of the theory and methods and how they can be applied. This is certainly a graduate level statistics textbook, though, and it assumes calculus at what I’d say is probably a second year mathematics degree level. You may find this book difficult if you don’t feel comfortable with multiplying integrals together (which is really what Bayesian analysis is). I sent my colleague a link to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stat.columbia.edu/~gelman/research/published/AOS259.pdf&#34;&gt;Gelman’s Annals of Applied Statistics article on ANOVA&lt;/a&gt;. Might as well plug &lt;a href=&#34;http://andrewgelman.com/&#34;&gt;Gelman’s blog&lt;/a&gt; while I’m talking about him. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Biostatistics-Bayesian-Introduction-Probability-Statistics/dp/0471468428&#34;&gt;Woodworth - Biostatistics: a Bayesian introduction&lt;/a&gt;. I found this very useful in giving a more applied approach to introductory Bayesian statistics. There’s a good review of the book &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.theannals.com/content/39/7/1376.2.full&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and I agree with the reviewers about the importance of the preface in that it talks about the philosophy of statistics in science and discusses the differences between frequentist and Bayesian statistics. The book walks the reader through a lot of the topics which frequentist statistics deals with but in a Bayesian setting. I find this sort of comparison very useful (and appreciate when Mike Jordan says that a lot of machine learning techniques are just Bayesian statistics with a different name) as most people who have taken a statistics class will have seen linear modelling, ANOVA and a little about statistical design. The book also introduces the use of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.openbugs.info/w/&#34;&gt;WinBUGS&lt;/a&gt; as a tool for Bayesian modelling. As an aside, I attended an introductory course run by my supervisor, Kerrie Mengersen, where she was teaching us how to use R to write a Gibbs sampler for a very simple problem and how to do it in WinBUGS as well. One of the other attendees, the leader of a medical science research group, had it in their head that they would use Excel to write the Gibbs sampler because it provides nice reports (summary stats, plots, etc.) through a plugin they had. Comparing the time it took WinBUGS and R to run the code against the Excel’s run time was probably what convinced me that Excel was one of the worst pieces of software that one could use for statistics. Great for spreadsheets, awful for statistics. A non-technical book which does a good job extending the philosophical discussion to the history of Bayesian statistics and its use in solving some very complex problems is &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Theory-That-Would-Not-Die/dp/1452636850&#34;&gt;Sharon Bertsch McGrayne’s The Theory That Would Not Die&lt;/a&gt; (which I like to think of as the “A Brief History of Time” of Bayesian statistics). It’s very readable and really drives home the importance of Bayesian statistics and the profundity of Bayes and Laplace in developing this approach. I really don’t think there’s much use revising the basics of frequentism as I disagree with its interpretation of probability and find the idea of confidence intervals problematic. Hypothesis testing is also another problem that I have with frequentism and I think we’re going to see a lot of scientific papers in the near future converting the p values for their ANOVA into a “sigma” level as a result of CERN’s announcement of the 5 sigma certainty of their search for a new boson. Tony O’Hagan has &lt;a href=&#34;http://bayesian.org/forums/news/3648&#34;&gt;a good post&lt;/a&gt; about the “sigma” issue on the ISBA forums. Edited to add: TL;DR? Got a maths degree and some familiarity with stats? Read Gelman. Don’t have a maths degree? Read Woodworth. Want to understand what Bayesian stats is but don’t want to read a textbook? Read McGrayne. Want to know how to use R? Read a Use R! book. Once you’ve got a decent understanding of what statistics is, read papers for specific topics because there is almost never a book about what you want.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Plenary speech</title>
      <link>/./2012/07/12/plenary-speech/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jul 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/07/12/plenary-speech/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This morning I gave a speech as part of the plenary session “Standing on the shoulders of giants”. I was joined on stage by Mengyan Gong from Tsinghua University and Joana Madureira from the University of Porto and the three of us were to talk about our position as students within the field of air quality and how we see ourselves contributing. After the three of us gave our ten minute talks, Professor &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.linkedin.com/profile/view?id=21633181&#34;&gt;Charles Weschler&lt;/a&gt; gave a talk about what we currently know about biochemistry and microbiology &lt;em&gt;vis a vis&lt;/em&gt; the role of chemicals and microbes in indoor air and health. I think it was a great session and I’d like to thank Lidia Morawska for coming up with the idea and &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.bus.qut.edu.au/sefdean/&#34;&gt;Martin Betts&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ce.berkeley.edu/people/faculty/Nazaroff?destination=people%2Ffaculty%2FNazaroff&#34;&gt;William Nazaroff&lt;/a&gt; for chairing the session.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;hb-plenary.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Thursday morning speakers Professor Charles Weschler, Ms Joana Madureira, Mr Sam Clifford and Ms Gong Mengyan. Photo courtesy Professor William Nazaroff.&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Thursday morning speakers Professor Charles Weschler, Ms Joana Madureira, Mr Sam Clifford and Ms Gong Mengyan. Photo courtesy Professor William Nazaroff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spoke about the need for better statistics in science and how it was up to supervisors to encourage their students to look at novel approaches for data analysis and for students to be curious, creative and willing to learn in order to ensure that the field does not grow stagnant. I have &lt;a href=&#34;http://samcliffordinfo.files.wordpress.com/2012/07/hbplen.pdf&#34;&gt;uploaded the slides&lt;/a&gt; (which are quite spare) and a transcript of what I planned to say is available below (perhaps I should try to get this published in Indoor Air as a letter). I did vary from the script in a few parts and I will post the video online when it’s available. I will try to include links in the transcript to references so people can find out about these techniques that I get so excited about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“Quantitative questions, quality answers”&lt;/strong&gt; A talk for the “Standing on the shoulders of giants” session&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I, as a student, am to further the field of indoor air and built environmental health it will be by standing on the shoulders of giants. The scientists, engineers and others who have gone before me in this field have developed a rich body of ideas and questions that have gone unanswered as a result of there being other work that they must do. But as one moves up the academic ladder, writing grant applications and supervising postgraduate students the chance to investigate some of these questions in depth arises. A team of PhD students with a diverse skill set can be assembled to assist the other academics in the team and to help drive the research output of the group. This has happened with my group’s UPTECH project, which is the topic of a session later today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to Graham Farquhar of the Australian National University, Canberra, one of Australia’s most cited academics, the key to producing high quality science is to start with a really good hypothesis driven question that no one has answered and answer it. That seems fairly straight forward? In the case of UPTECH, the unanswered question is “What is the effect of exposure to airborne nano and ultrafine particles emitted from motor vehicles on the health of children in schools?”. Data collected in this project include two weeks of indoor and out aerosol and meteorology measurements at each of 25 primary schools. Indoor microbiology measurements are taken in one or two classrooms at each school and health diagnostic tests are performed on the students in these classes, accompanied by a take home survey which includes questions about family health history, demographics and housing characteristics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project generates a huge amount of data that has the potential to reveal some very interesting relationships. But to do so requires statistics beyond ANOVA and linear regression. The same can really be said of any modern scientific project. Don’t get me wrong, ANOVA is a great tool for exploratory data analysis [1] and testing whether a term in a regression model is zero or not. But to stop the analysis at descriptive statistics and testing for equal means across groups is to cheat yourself out of the opportunity to examine why these differences arise and really get to know what your data is telling you. ANOVA can be replaced with a Generalised Linear Model with factor terms. Any measured covariates can then be included in this GLM rather than just calculating the correlation between the covariate and the response. If the effect is suspected to be non-linear there are a range of regression models which are commonly used in the statistical and computer sciences but have not found their way into the natural sciences and I will talk about these soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The development of new statistical techniques and the ubiquity of computers in the workplace means that there is really no excuse for using statistical techniques that were developed for agricultural field trials are limited in their ability to explain variation in a data set. Expecting senior academics and industry practitioners to maintain statistical education throughout their careers is a bit of a tall ask in some cases. There’s so much work to be done keeping up with the science that the statistics often falls by the wayside. In my mind, the role of the supervisor is to present a problem and then direct the creativity and curiosity of the student. The role of the student is to answer the research question in a paper which weaves together the experience of the supervisor with high quality research and statistical modelling appropriate to the data and hypothesis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And there’s much more to data analysis than doing ANOVA. If you suspect that there might be homogenous groups within a set of observations, why not try a clustering algorithm like k-means [2] or a finite mixture model? [3] Don’t know how many groups there are? Try an infinite mixture model [4]. Think that certain covariates might have a different effect within those groups? A Dirichlet Process Mixture of GLMs is an option [5]. The Indian Buffet Process will help you identify common patterns across a bunch of correlated covariates and reduce the dimension of your data [6]. If you suspect the effect of humidity on particle number concentration is non-linear but aren’t sure about what it’s going to look like you could try a spline model [7,8]. For a smooth spatial relationship across a network of monitors you can use a Gaussian predictive process with a Matern class covariance function [9] or go all out and use a Gaussian process with non-parametric covariance [10]. Want to combine the effect sizes from some previous studies of the same thing to estimate an overall effect? Use Bayesian meta-analysis rather than a weighted average [11].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are all common approaches in the statistical community and I have seen them applied to scientific problems, many related to air quality or health. These techniques are much newer than ANOVA and their development in statistics and computer science means that professional scientists may not ever be exposed to them. So it’s up to students to be aware of new techniques which are applicable to their research. But is it too much to expect that all students are well versed in such a range of statistical techniques? Probably. Especially when you consider that a lot of these things aren’t taught in undergraduate science degrees. Science graduates are the obvious choice when recruiting science PhD students or industry practitioners. But science and engineering is strengthened by solid statistics. And the statistics are solid when a group’s capacity for statistics is solid, whether by employing one directly, choosing candidates with a strong statistical education, building links with a statistics research group at a university or providing for the ongoing statistical training of early career researchers and/or students. Our science must not just demonstrate that something is happening but attempt to understand why that effect occurs. We must quantify it and how and why it varies. Highly influential work, such as the work presented by our keynote speakers, arises when appropriate statistics raises high quality experimental science to where it belongs. The reader has before them a clear picture of what is happening and why. I see my role in my group, and through it, my role in our broad field, as fostering statistical creativity and curiosity. I am there to help provide tools which the people around me can use to solve these unanswered problems. Encouraging people to step outside the “ANOVA and linear regression in Excel” frame of mind has motivated them to ask questions about how best to fit some data which shows a non-linear effect, how to write code to process output from our instruments that will calculate summary statistics and generate plots, how to look at trends in time series data, and so on. In return, I’ve been given the opportunity to work on some really interesting air quality problems with some people who really know their science. So I pick up some more knowledge about aerosols and health, they get exposed to new ways of analysing data, and we get to present our interesting results to the world with robust and novel analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[1] Andrew Gelman. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stat.columbia.edu/~gelman/research/published/AOS259.pdf&#34;&gt;Analysis of variance - why it is more important than ever&lt;/a&gt;. Annals of Statistics, 33:1-53, 2005.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[2] Lloyd., S. P. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.nyu.edu/~roweis/csc2515-2006/readings/lloyd57.pdf&#34;&gt;Least squares quantization in PCM&lt;/a&gt;. IEEE Transactions on Information Theory 28 (2): 129-137, 1982.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[3] Darren Wraith, Clair Alston, Kerrie Mengersen, Tareq Hussein. &lt;a href=&#34;http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/env.1020/abstract&#34;&gt;Bayesian mixture model estimation of aerosol particle size distributions&lt;/a&gt;. Environmetrics 22 (1)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[4] Brian Kulis, Michael I. Jordan. &lt;a href=&#34;http://arxiv.org/abs/1111.0352&#34;&gt;Revisiting k-means: New Algorithms via Bayesian Nonparametrics&lt;/a&gt;. ICML 2012.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[5] Lauren A. Hannah, David M. Blei, Warren B. Powell. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.princeton.edu/~blei/papers/HannahBleiPowell2011.pdf&#34;&gt;Dirichlet Process Mixtures of Generalized Linear Models&lt;/a&gt;. Journal of Machine Learning Research 1: 1-33, 2011.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[6] Thomas L. Griffiths, Zoubin Ghahramani. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gatsby.ucl.ac.uk/~zoubin/papers/ibp-nips05.pdf&#34;&gt;Inﬁnite Latent Feature Models and the Indian Buffet Process&lt;/a&gt;. Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems 18, 2005.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[7] S. Clifford, S. Low Choy, T. Hussein, K. Mengersen, L. Morawska, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1352231011004766&#34;&gt;Using the Generalised Additive Model to model the particle number count of ultrafine particles&lt;/a&gt;, Atmospheric Environment 45 (32): 5934-5945, 2011.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[8] S. Clifford, B. Mølgaard, S. Low Choy, J. Corander, K. Hämeri, K. Mengersen, L. Morawska, Bayesian semi-parametric forecasting of particle number concentration: penalised splines and autoregressive errors, in prep, 2012. &lt;a href=&#34;http://arxiv.org/abs/1207.0558&#34;&gt;arXiv&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[9] Banerjee, S.; Gelfand, A. E.; Finley, A. &amp;amp; Sang, H. &lt;a href=&#34;http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/j.1467-9868.2008.00663.x/abstract&#34;&gt;Gaussian predictive process models for large spatial data sets&lt;/a&gt;. Journal of the Royal Statistical Society B 70: 825-848, 2008.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[10] Emily Fox and David Dunson. &lt;a href=&#34;http://arxiv.org/abs/1101.2017&#34;&gt;Bayesian Nonparametric Covariance Regression&lt;/a&gt;, 2011.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[11] Blangiardo, M.; Hansell, A. &amp;amp; Richardson, S. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1352231010008642&#34;&gt;A Bayesian model of time activity data to investigate health effect of air pollution in time series studies&lt;/a&gt;. Atmospheric Environment, 45: 379 - 386, 2011.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Healthy Buildings</title>
      <link>/./2012/07/09/healthy-buildings/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Jul 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/07/09/healthy-buildings/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am taking a break from the final session of the day to catch up on some thesis related emails. Figured I might as well write up what’s happened so far. The welcome reception at GoMA last night was quite good. Dr Bruce Flegg, Minister for Housing and Public Works, gave a good speech welcoming us all and stressing the importance of what we do. I was very impressed with how across the topic Flegg seemed to be. Dr Flegg has a background as a GP and is all too aware of the problems associated with unhealthy workplaces with things like mesothelioma and asbestosis. He has seen people who have developed health issues associated with accidental environmental exposure (so not people installing these materials like Bernie Banton). Flegg also spoke about the need to ensure that public housing stock, particularly in our indigenous communities, are of a high quality in terms of their energy efficiency but also in the way they promote health and are appropriate to the communities and regions in which they’re built. At the opening I also got to chat with Susan Savage, the Assistant Dean of Teaching and Learning in the new Science and Engineering Faculty at QUT. We discussed changes to the first year Bachelor of Science program that sound very promising. A common first semester will expose students to what science is and how it is done before students choose a major in their second semester. Mathematics will be embedded in each subject to make sure that our students continue to be exposed to it rather than doing a single Data Analysis unit and then thinking that they’ll never have to do statistics again. The opening plenary symposium, “Balance of Power”, was a discussion by two international speakers about the issue of a compromise between energy efficient buildings and healthy buildings. Professor Jiang Yi from Tsinghua University spoke about the issues of growing energy demand in the search for thermal comfort and presented some very interesting case studies where Chinese buildings have been built to maximise the availability of natural ventilation and light while still providing a very high quality of thermal comfort for the occupants. His message was that a combination of decentralised air conditioning systems that don’t work against each other can augment a default system of natural ventilation (with office windows which can be opened, for a start) to drastically cut our energy usage and ensure a ready supply of fresh air. The second speaker, Philippa Howden-Chapman discussed the problems faced in the New Zealand housing stock. New Zealand is a first world country but most of the public housing stock was built around World War II, prior to the first global oil shock, and is characterised by poor insulation and unflued gas heaters (often LPG). As a result, people in public housing are facing the choice of “heat or eat”. And even if they can manage to heat themselves, NO2 levels in the home tend to be three times higher than in homes without an LPG heater. Her group has done a lot of work to intervene in the worst affected homes and improve thermal comfort, health and energy efficiency. New Zealand has the lowest per capita energy use in the OECD despite being so damn cold. But heating an uninsulated house can be very expensive. The big finding is that if the government spends the money retrofitting homes they save a lot in terms of public pharmaceutical provision, hospital visits and lost productivity and education. An econometric analysis showed a 3.9:1 return on investment, with the investment in a house paying for itself if a single hospital visit in that house can be avoided. I spent the parallel sessions this morning doing AV support for two sessions. The venue has done a great job making it as easy as possible for presenters so the most I had to do was look for two missing speakers and walk people through how to use the pointer. The first session I attended was all about ventilation and there were some very interesting presentations about filtering incoming air and how being a bit clever about our behaviour in the home can lead to much better air quality. The second session focussed on regional solutions and included three talks about stoves in the developing world. A lot of poorer regions such as rural Kenya and Andean Peru rely on the use of solid fuels such as dung and the homes typically do not have very good ventilation. Some new stove designs were developed with community feedback in order to arrive at a design which was both energy efficient and didn’t depart from the cultural aesthetic of the typical oven design. Other considerations included the cost to the end user, provision of local jobs in assembling and maintaining the ovens and ensuring that the indoor air quality was improved beyond the energy efficiency gains. One of the more novel approaches for this was to use a thermoelectric device that could power an air blower with waste heat from the oven. This meant that particulate matter and incomplete combustion byproducts (CO mainly) were removed much quicker. Excess energy from these thermoelectric devices can be used to charge mobile phones (and something like 40% of homes in rural Kenya have mobile phones!). Some very inspiring work, showing that science can have a real impact in the developing world. I’ve also caught up with the two other students in my plenary session, Joana and Mengyan. The three of us will be meeting with our session chairs on Thursday morning (QUT SEF Dean Martin Betts and UC Berkeley Professor William Nazaroff) to discuss the session but today’s chat was a bit of getting to know each other and discussing what Brisbane’s like. Joana was very interested in what sort of Australian foods she could take back to Portugal for her friends. Vegemite, Tim Tams and Iced Vovos. The conference is going well overall. The QUT Events team and the Brisbane Convention and Exhibition Centre staff have done an amazing job making sure everything’s as clear as possible. It’s a great venue (the new wing of the BCEC) and the conference is bringing together people from 40 countries, be they academics, students, consultants, industry practitioners or vendors. There are 160ish students in attendance (many of whom I’ll meet tomorrow night at the student event) and I’ve heard that something like three quarters of attendees are from overseas. I’m looking forward to the next few days.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
