<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
      <title>Bayes on the Beach on Sam Clifford </title>
    <link>/./tags/bayes-on-the-beach/</link>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
    <updated>2012-11-12 00:00:00 &#43;0000 UTC</updated>
    
    <item>
      <title>Group photo from Bayes on the Beach</title>
      <link>/./2012/11/12/group-photo-from-bayes-on-the-beach/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Nov 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/11/12/group-photo-from-bayes-on-the-beach/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;photoshop-master1.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://samcliffordinfo.files.wordpress.com/2012/11/photoshop-master1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Group photo from Bayes on the Beach&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Attendees of the 2012 Bayes on the Beach meeting. Photo credit: Luisa Hall (photographer, pictured far left) and Sam Clifford (photo editor, third column of people, second from back). This photo is a composite of a photo taken by Luisa (without her in it) and a photo taken by the venue staff (with Luisa in it). The keynote speakers were Matt Wand (front row, yellow shirt), Kim-Anh Do (second row, second from right) and Dave Woods (not picutred). Murray Aitkin is standing up the back. The conference organisers were Professor Kerrie Mengersen (third from the front on the far right), Nicole White (second from left in the floral dress), Jannah Baker (second row, fifth from left), Matt Moores (far right up the back) and Dow Jaemjamrat (not pictured).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bayes on the Beach</title>
      <link>/./2012/11/08/bayes-on-the-beach/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Nov 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/11/08/bayes-on-the-beach/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve spent the last three days at the Bayes on the Beach conference/workshop in &lt;a href=&#34;https://maps.google.com.au/maps?q=caloundra&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;sll=-19.457034,145.879162&amp;amp;sspn=35.100111,39.506836&amp;amp;hnear=Caloundra+Queensland&amp;amp;t=m&amp;amp;z=14&amp;amp;iwloc=A&#34;&gt;Caloundra&lt;/a&gt;. The meeting is an annual event where Bayesian statisticians (usually Australians who know Kerrie Mengersen) get together for a very casual set of talks, workshops and other activities in a beachside town.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;design&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Design&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We arrived in Caloundra on Tuesday morning and got down to business with a keynote talk from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.southampton.ac.uk/maths/about/staff/davew.page&#34;&gt;Dave Woods&lt;/a&gt; (University of Southampton). Professor Woods’ talk opened a day in which the over-arching theme was experimental design and made the point that any design is at least implicitly Bayesian. I really agree with this point because any design is based on the prior experience of the experimenter or is pieced together from a review of what’s been done previously. I don’t know of any situation in which an experimental study was carried out totally at random without choosing appropriate covariate values. I don’t have much of a head for design but I think after seeing the talks on Tuesday (particularly Liz Ryan’s, which others in her session praised as giving a good review of utility) I’m a bit more aware of what it all means. What really helped was &lt;a href=&#34;http://pharmacy.otago.ac.nz/our-people/academic-staff/stephen-duffull&#34;&gt;Stephen Duffull&lt;/a&gt; (University of Otago) in his Thursday talk where he spelled out D-optimality (wanting to maximise the effect) and P-optimality (wanting to get the best estimate of parameters). D- and P-optimality work in opposite directions quite frequently (killing all your patients doesn’t tell you much about the parameters in your model, for example) but it’s possible to trade them off with a DP-optimal design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;workshops&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Workshops&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of my favourite aspects of the Bayes on the Beach meetings is the workshops. At my first Bayes on the Beach (2009) we were shown how to do a Bayesian meta-analysis to combine the results of a bunch of disparate studies that dealt with the same topic. Ever since then, I’ve been looking forward to learning some more statistics or getting to grips with interesting data. &lt;a href=&#34;http://datasearch2.uts.edu.au/science/staff/maths/details.cfm?StaffID=11641&#34;&gt;Matt Wand&lt;/a&gt; (University of Technology Sydney), &lt;a href=&#34;http://data.aims.gov.au/staffcv/jsf/external/view.xhtml?partyId=900000428&#34;&gt;Julian Caley&lt;/a&gt; (Australian Institute of Marine Science) and &lt;a href=&#34;http://staff.qut.edu.au/staff/lowchoy/&#34;&gt;Sama Low Choy&lt;/a&gt; (Queensland University of Technology, my associate supervisor) each pitched a problem that people could have a look at, not necessarily solving but, working towards a solution. Wand presented some really interesting spatio-temporal data of extreme rainfall in NSW which I was very keen to sign up to but Kerrie suggested that it might be a bit more of a challenge to do something other than spatio-temporal modelling of environmental data. Sama presented some work that she’s been doing on combining elicited opinions into a subjective prior that represents the aggregate knowledge of experts. I ended up in Caley’s group, where we worked on some data that &lt;a href=&#34;http://scholar.google.com/citations?user=T-nbIuUAAAAJ&amp;amp;hl=en&#34;&gt;Julie Vercelloni&lt;/a&gt; is dealing with as part of her PhD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;reef-workshop&#34; class=&#34;section level4&#34;&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Reef workshop&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Caley, Vercelloni and Mengersen (among others) are working on coral coverage in the Great Barrier Reef in six sectors that run up the length of the reef (2600km). Within each sector there are reef shelves and on each shelf there are multiple reefs with multiple measurement patches. The question we attempted to answer was “How different are the long term trends in coral coverage at these reefs?” Caley has data going back to about 1994, reported annually, which when pooled looked very boring but when plotted (very well by Vercelloni) grouped by reef shelf within sector indicated that there might be quite a lot of interesting variation which may not be so straight forward to model. Our group split up into a few subgroups with different approaches and I ended up working with James McKeone and a few others on a model inspired by &lt;a href=&#34;http://samclifford.info/2012/10/19/anova/&#34; title=&#34;ANOVA&#34;&gt;Cari Kaufmann’s functional ANOVA with GP priors&lt;/a&gt;. Over the next day or so McKeone took what we’d discussed and written down as a model and came up with quite a general Gibbs sampling scheme that is flexible enough to admit any linear predictor. I’m fairly certain James and I both had P-splines in mind but I did talk later to Matt Wand about O’Sullivan splines and I think it might be conceptually easier to use Wand’s low rank thin plate smoothers, particularly as Vercelloni’s quite new to Bayesian statistics and has a background in ecology rather than computational statistics. It was interesting to see how the other workshops went on the Thursday afternoon recap. Sama’s group had split into three groups, each tackling the issue of elicitation with a different topic and a different angle. I must say that my favourite was the group who did an elicitation of predictions of the outcome of the US Presidential Election. &lt;a href=&#34;http://conidialcoleopticide.wordpress.com/&#34;&gt;Luisa Hall&lt;/a&gt; even managed to elicit my opinion for her survey without me even realising it (we talk a lot about politics)! The other groups asked about how risky a life-saving operation would have to be for them to not take it and average completion time for PhD students (which Sama gave a talk about on Thursday).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;real-time-updates-for-mean-field-variational-bayes&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Real time updates for Mean Field Variational Bayes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matt Wand also gave a talk and tutorial about using Mean Field Variational Bayes (a name he attributes to Mike Jordan) to do live, real-time updates of posterior estimates with streamed data such as stock trading. Rather than going into the content of the talk, I suggest you read &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.uow.edu.au/~mwand/ovbpap.pdf&#34;&gt;the paper&lt;/a&gt; he’s written with Tamara Broderick (University of California, Berkeley) and his PhD student Jan Luts (University of Technology Sydney) and check out &lt;a href=&#34;http://realtime-semiparametric-regression.net/&#34;&gt;their website&lt;/a&gt; with neat examples, e.g. &lt;a href=&#34;http://realtime-semiparametric-regression.net/SydneyRealEstate/&#34;&gt;the Sydney rental market&lt;/a&gt; (which I think would be fascinating with the train lines superimposed).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;games-and-posters&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Games and Posters&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tuesday and Wednesday evenings had Luisa and I running some games (&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fictionary&#34;&gt;Dictionary&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://boardgamegeek.com/boardgame/38159/ultimate-werewolf-ultimate-edition&#34;&gt;Werewolf&lt;/a&gt;) before the poster sessions. It’s interesting running games like this with Bayesians because Dictionary is basically a problem of credibility of unknown experts and Werewolf is all about updating an initially uninformative prior with information based on peoples’ behaviour as they accuse others while trying to avoid being lynched. The poster sessions themselves were quite good, with a wide variety of applications and methodologies being presented. Everyone seemed quite keen to talk about their posters and they were generally of a high quality. On Thursday afternoon I gave my talk about spatio-temporal modelling of the UPTECH data as a case study for INLA. I got a few questions about the versatility of INLA and my choice of random walk and spline models instead of other bases as well as comments about the spatial modelling I’m doing. Definitely some things to think about for the next papers I write.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;a-success&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;A success&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The organisers of Bayes on the Beach (Nicole White, Matt Moores, Jannah Baker and Dow Jaemjamrat) all did a really good job and I think everyone had a good time but was also inspired. I had a few minor issues (timekeeping is a perpetual bugbear of mine and I’m yet to go to a conference that runs totally on schedule) but think that the meeting did a really good job of bringing together a disparate group of researchers and introducing them to each other and providing ideas for future work and employment opportunities (Kim-Anh Do did a really good job of selling the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mdanderson.org/&#34;&gt;MD Anderson Cancer Center&lt;/a&gt;). I think the challenge for future Bayes on the Beach meetings will be managing the growth in the number of attendees. I look forward to next year’s meeting; I might even have some time to go to the beach!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Summary of the last week&#39;s Christian Robert visit</title>
      <link>/./2012/08/24/summary-of-the-last-weeks-christian-robert-visit/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Aug 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Alexander Ivanov</author>
      <guid>/./2012/08/24/summary-of-the-last-weeks-christian-robert-visit/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I didn’t have any one on one meetings with Professor Robert but he did address two of my stats research group’s meetings and gave two seminars as part of his AMSI talk. In addition to this, there was a few hours one afternoon where QUT statisticians presented some of the Bayesian computation that is worked on here. Christian’s first talk to BRAG focused on model choice and comparison and &lt;a href=&#34;http://samclifford.info/2012/08/16/a-few-things-from-today/&#34;&gt;I wrote about it last week&lt;/a&gt;. The second talk to BRAG (&lt;a href=&#34;http://storify.com/samclifford/christian-robert-s-second-brag-talk&#34;&gt;Storify&lt;/a&gt;) was to finish off the themes on improving MCMC methods that he mentioned. We picked up where we left off, with a discussion of simulated tempering. The choice of &lt;em&gt;α&lt;/em&gt; is probably the key concept here, and Christian recommends choosing a scale based on the number of data points (if π&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt; is the original likelihood, try using π = π&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1/&lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; for &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; data points). Allowing &lt;em&gt;α&lt;/em&gt; to take multiple values (or even have a distribution) means that we now have a space of target posteriors. By moving around in this space of posteriors we are less likely to end up with sticky Markov chains because a sharply peaked posterior in one posterior will likely not be as sharply peaked in another posterior. Robert gave a reference to a paper by Radford Neal which deals with tempering [1]. Another way to ensure movement throughout the posterior space is to either subsample the data or to perturb the data with a small amount of noise. These will again change the posterior (ever so slightly) and help exploration of the space to find the modes. A change of variable is another way to flatten out the posterior. Parallel computation is another option; running the same model with different starting values and using the posterior density (a one dimensional value for each simulation) to get a sense of what the maximum value of the posterior might be. Low density models can be dropped in this way as they are not near the global mode of the posterior. I find this approach quite interesting and if I had a bit more time I’d try implementing it. Some exploration of low density modes is burn-in, but if the exploration is trapped at a local mode (and tempering, etc. aren’t getting it out of there) then perhaps it ought to be dropped. Robert then went on to talk about using auxiliary variables to create joint densities where we can move along level sets of the posterior to get large jumps in the parameter of interest. This is probably where I got lost, but I did manage to get that there’s a paper by Girolami and Calderhead [2] where this is formalised as Langevin and Hamiltonian Monte Carlo. Some of the members of BRAG will be presenting LMC/HMC at a future meeting and I look forward to it. It’s always interesting to find out that so much Bayesian computation started out as a branch of physics (the Metropolis(-Hastings) algorithm as a solution for the Ising/Potts model, for example). I’ve used Storify to publish my notes from the two AMSI sessions (&lt;a href=&#34;http://samclifford.info/2012/08/21/christian-roberts-talk-on-simulation/&#34; title=&#34;Christian Robert&amp;#39;s talk on simulation&#34;&gt;simulation&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://samclifford.info/2012/08/22/christian-roberts-talk-on-abc-for-model-choice-and-open-floor-on-bayesian-computation-2/&#34; title=&#34;Christian Robert&amp;#39;s talk on ABC for Model Choice and open floor on Bayesian computation&#34;&gt;ABC for model choice&lt;/a&gt;) that were part of Christian’s tour. I missed the one at UQ about Rao-Blackwellisation, unfortunately. Some of his slides from his talks are available online at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.slideshare.net/xianblog/presentations&#34;&gt;Slideshare&lt;/a&gt;. The open floor after the ABC talk was quite good as it gave me a chance to see what people are working on. While I have seen a few pyMCMC talks before there seems to be quite a lot of energy from Chris Strickland and Clair Alston for the development of new models in the pyMCMC framework. I’ve previously spoken with Chris about how to go about using it for spline models and spatial modelling and I hope that once I finish my PhD I’ve got some time to check out pyMCMC in greater depth. If you want to have a look, you can clone it from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://bitbucket.org/christophermarkstrickland/pymcmc/&#34;&gt;git repository on bitbucket&lt;/a&gt;. It was also interesting to see the work Ewan Cameron and Tony Pettitt have been doing on ABC for astronomical data (evolution of galaxies, etc.) and the work of Chris Drovandi, James McGree, Liz Ryan and others on using Sequential Monte Carlo with ABC for adaptive clinical study design. All in all a good week of seminars with lots of interesting ideas. &lt;a href=&#34;http://bayesian.org/forums/conferences/3606&#34;&gt;Bayes on the Beach 2012&lt;/a&gt; is &lt;a href=&#34;http://bragqut.wordpress.com/beachbayes2012/&#34;&gt;coming up&lt;/a&gt;. This is one of my favourite events of the year because it’s a chance to get away from uni with a bunch of statisticians and discuss some interesting problems and do little workshops. The beach is also quite a nice part of it and there’s usually some sort of games night (last year I contributed a game which is basically Chinese Whispers mixed with Pictionary and we all had a lot of fun trying to figure out what was going on). It’s also a really good chance for early PhD students to present a poster in a very friendly environment so they can get used to talking to others about their work. I’ve also managed to land myself on the list of presenters for the School of Mathematical Sciences’ “Postgrad Day”. While not a member of the school, two of my supervisors are and I’ve been working on statistical methods during my PhD. I will present the work I’ve been doing with my Finnish collaborators in a 20 minute slot. This will be a sort of practice run for my final seminar and is what I should have submitted to ISBA 2012 (but when abstracts closed we weren’t nearly ready enough). It’ll be good to have an audience of mathematicians and statisticians, because I always feel awkward explaining statistical research to aerosol scientists, chemists, physicists and microbiologists. Perhaps I need to focus a bit more on pitching a particular aspect of my work to the audience I’ve got. [1] [Neal, R. M., (1996) “Sampling from Multimodal Distributions using Tempered Transitions”, &lt;em&gt;Statistics and Computing&lt;/em&gt; 6, pp. 353-366](&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.springerlink.com/content/x6417mm4h7845735/&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;http://www.springerlink.com/content/x6417mm4h7845735/&lt;/a&gt;). [2] [Girolami, M., and Calderhead, B., (2011) “Riemann manifold Langevin and Hamiltonian Monte Carlo methods”, &lt;em&gt;Journal of the Royal Statistical Society - Series B&lt;/em&gt; 73(2), pp. 1-37.](&lt;a href=&#34;http://people.stat.sfu.ca/~cao/Research/GirolamiCalderhead.pdf&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;http://people.stat.sfu.ca/~cao/Research/GirolamiCalderhead.pdf&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
