<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Sam Clifford - Bayesian Statistics</title>
    <link>https://samclifford.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Sam Clifford - Bayesian Statistics</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 21 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://samclifford.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Progress, anxiety and context</title>
      <link>https://samclifford.github.io/post/progress-tests/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://samclifford.github.io/post/progress-tests/</guid>
      <description>One of the challenges when teaching first year students with a diverse range of maths backgrounds is that you’ll encounter students with maths anxiety. Exactly what it sounds like, maths anxiety prevents students from being able to engage with material that would be otherwise within their grasp. Whether they’re Maths A students who have always struggled, Maths B students who got through without really understanding how, or mature age students for whom high school maths is a distant yet painful memory, some students will almost refuse to attempt anything new.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>https://samclifford.github.io/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://samclifford.github.io/about/</guid>
      <description>BioI’m a statistician working at Queensland University of Technology on a range of environmental and environmental health problems such as jaguar conservation, reef conservation, and air pollution and its health impacts. In addition, I teach mathematics and statistics to first year science students in the unit SEB113 - Quantitative Methods in Science.
Much of my work makes use of the following techniques, which one could consider my research interests</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UPTECH paper complete</title>
      <link>https://samclifford.github.io/post/uptech-paper-complete/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://samclifford.github.io/post/uptech-paper-complete/</guid>
      <description>After what seems like a lifetime, the UPTECH paper I’ve been working on is undergoing final proofing (Clifford et al. 2018). The paper looks at classic spirometry outcomes like FEV1 and FVC, markers of inflammation like the fraction of exhaled nitric oxide and the amount of C-reactive protein in the blood. Through a health history and demographics questionniare that got sent home with the 655 participating students we have information about their coughing, wheezing and asthma status over the last 12 months, as well as whether the home’s been flooded or had mould in that period, the presence of gas cooktops, pets, a garage, carpet, air conditioning, cigarette smoking, and many other variables which didn’t make it into the final models.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://samclifford.github.io/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://samclifford.github.io/about/</guid>
      <description>Bio I’m a statistician working at Queensland University of Technology on a range of environmental and environmental health problems such as jaguar conservation, reef conservation, and air pollution and its health impacts. In addition, I teach mathematics and statistics to first year science students in the unit SEB113 - Quantitative Methods in Science.
Much of my work makes use of the following techniques, which one could consider my research interests</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://samclifford.github.io/page/cv/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://samclifford.github.io/page/cv/</guid>
      <description>For the most up to date publication list, please check the Google Scholar and ORC-ID links in the upper right of the page.
A three page CV listing recent employment and key publications can be found here</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Curriculum Vitae</title>
      <link>https://samclifford.github.io/page/cv/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://samclifford.github.io/page/cv/</guid>
      <description>For the most up to date publication list, please check the Google Scholar and ORC-ID links in the upper right of the page.
A three page CV listing recent employment and key publications can be found here</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>